Unseen speaker: ...
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Sergeant at Arms is directed to make the proclamation.
Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: All persons are commanded to keep silent under pain of penalty while the Impeachment Court is in session for the trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The Impeachment Trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte is hereby called to order. We shall be led in prayer by Senator-Judge JV Ejercito.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Amon namin mga pangyarihan, lumalapit kami sa iyo nang may pakumbaba. Batid namin na ang karunungan ng tao ay may hangganan. Ngunit ang iyong katotohanan at katarungan ay nanatili magpakailanman.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Sa
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: pagtupad namin ng aming tungkulin binang mga senator judges, hinihiling namin ang iyong gabay sa lahat ng aming gagawin. Pagkalooban mo, nawa kami ng tapat na puso at malinaw na pag-iisip. Sa buong panahon ng paglilitis na ito, Panginoon, nakikiusap po kami na kayo niyo kami sa landas na makatarungan na may patas na pagtingin sa karapatan ng bawat isa. Dalhin niyo kami sa liwanag pagkat nakapiring ang aming mga mata, hindi man po namin hiningi, ngunit ipinagkatiwala sa aming konstitusyon ang timbangan ng katarungan. Kumiling nawa ito sa karapat-dapat na pagkalooban nito. Nawa ang inyong salita ang maging gabays sa aming paglilingkod at pagdala sa amin sa katotohanan. Kagaya po ng Winika sa Leviticus 19.15, Do not pervert justice, do not show partiality, but judge your neighbor fairly. Lagi po naman tatandaan ang tagubili niyong ito. Amma, anuman ang maging bunga ng paglilitis na ito, hindi nawa itong makita bilang tagumpay ng isa at pagkatalo ng iba, kundi para sa kabubuti ng sambay ng Pilipino. Lahat po ng aming gagawin ay para sa kalulugod mo at hindi para sa kapinabangan ng sino mang tao, mga partido o kanilang mga pansariling interes. Kundi ito'y para sa pagpapatibay ng aming mainstitusyon ng pamalaan at sa pagpapanatili ng tiwala ng mamamayan sa demokrasya ng aming bayan. Bum puso po naming nananalangin na sa lahat ang aming gagawin, lagit-lagi naming kayong pinupuryan. Amen.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Senator-Judge Aquino. Senator-Judge Cayetano, Alan. Senator-Judge Cayetano, Pia. Senator-Judge Dela Rosa. Senator-Judge Ejercito. Senator-Judge Estrada. Senator-Judge Go. Senator-Judge Hontiveros. Senator-Judge Lacson. Senator-Judge Lapid. Senator-Judge Legarda. Senator-Judge Marcoleta. Senator-Judge Marcos. Senator-Judge Padilla. Senator-Judge Pangilinan. Senator-Judge Sotto III. Senator-Judge Tulfo, Erwin. Senator-Judge Tulfo, Raffy. Senator-Judge Villanueva. Senator-Judge Villar, Camille. Senator-Judge Villar, Mark. Senator-Judge Zubiri. The Presiding Officer, Senator-Judge Escudero. The Senate President, Senator-Judge Gatchalian.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: With 17 senators present, the Chair declares the presence of a quorum.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: We note the presence of Senator-Judge Bong Go. We have 18. And Senator-Judge Imee Marcos. We have [unclear] senators present.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: If there
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: are no objections, we dispense with the reading of the July 8, 2026 Journal of the Senate sitting as an impeachment court and consider the same as approved.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Clerk will please call the case before the impeachment court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: 2026. In the matter of the impeachment trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sen. Rafi Tulfo is seeking recognition. What is the pleasure of Sen. Judge Rafi Tulfo?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Thank you, Presiding Judge Escudero. Short inquiry lang po for the defense, particularly kay Atty. Mark Vinluan. Atty., you know what? During the last hearing, when you delivered a manifestation in reply to the prosecution's statement regarding the fourth article of impeachment, You said, and I quote, The truth of the matter is this. She and her family were threatened, and while her response was unconventional, it was justified. What triggered her response was a question about Operation Romanov, which is the plot to eliminate VP Sara and her family. End of quote. Now, Atty. Bin Luan, this Operation Romanov that you mentioned, Are you referring to the Operation Romanov mentioned by the blogger Princess Maui during the online press conference of BP-SARA?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Okay. So, the question was raised during the press conference by this Princess Maui, but I did not see her name as a list of defense witnesses in the pre-trial order. So, will you be presenting her as your witness?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, at this point, it will depend on... What will be established by the prosecution, the defense reserve its right to call or not call any witness depending on the course of the trial.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Oh, I see. Okay. So, in other words, will you also be presenting any other witness to prove this threat or this operation, Romanov?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor. That will be part of our evidence in chief.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: May this court know now? Kung sino-sino itong mga witnesses na inyong i-present? Of course,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: of course, Your Honor. We are not at liberty to disclose that at this time. Again, it will depend on the course of the time.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Your Honors, Presiding Judge, the first time I've heard about this Romanov is during the Maisog Leaders Forum in Davao City. That was on January 28, 2024. Correct me if I'm wrong. It was mentioned by Mayor Baste Duterte.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: At that time, hindi ko alam anong ibig sabihin ng Romanov at sino mga ito. In fact, ginugil ko yan. Sino itong family Romanov? So napagalaman ko, apparently, they were the ruling family in Russia that was murdered by the Bolsheviks in the night of July 16, 1918. Malapit-lapit na sa anniversary, 108th anniversary. Kasi ano ba tayo ngayon, July 13. Anyway, may relasyon ba ito sa binanggit ni Bastet sa sinabi ni Princess Maui at yung binanggit mo? Nakakarelasyon ba yung tatlo?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, I have no personal knowledge of what Mayor Bastet said so I cannot comment on that, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: So hindi mo napanood yun? No, Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Okay. And last question. What did you mean when you said that BP's arrest response was unconventional?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, it was a description, Your Honor, of the statements that she made during that press conference.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Why is it unconventional?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, the basic meaning of the word is, it will explain itself, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Okay, that's all, Presiding Judge. Noted and entered into the records.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, what is the pleasure of the Honorable Defensor, one of the members of the panel of prosecutors. You may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proceed,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sir.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Thank you, Your Honors. Your Honors, before we proceed, With the examination of our second witness, Your Honors, the prosecution is in receipt of a letter dated July 10, 2026 from NBI Director Melvin A. Matibag requesting that his testimony be scheduled or calendared at the earliest setting considering that the National Bureau of Investigation, Your Honors, has been invited by the Federal Bureau of Investigation. In coordination with the Royal Thai Police for a regional summit on scam center compounds and transnational organized crime. In that regard, Your Honor, the prosecution would like to request that the scheduled testimony of NBI Director Melvin Matibag be scheduled tomorrow after the testimony of our second witness, Atty. Jeremy A. Lotoc.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: After the testimony of your second witness.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Yes, your honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But the supposed witness scheduled for tomorrow is Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Zulaika Lopez for the gentleman's manifestation in the last hearing.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: That's correct, your honor. After we have dispensed with the testimony of NBI Director Matibag, we can proceed with the schedule of witnesses as provided in the list to the senator judges last week, your honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: To include Captain Belio, if I'm not
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mistaken?
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Yes, we can proceed with Atty. Lopez and Captain Belio as manifested last week, Your Honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Cayetano, Alan?
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Mr. Presiding Officer, if no one objects, I will not object to having Director Matibag yesterday, but maybe as a caution to government officials, my good friend, Congressman Defensor. I read over the weekend that Director Matibag is writing because he is to be in a convention meeting the FBI next week. So actually, we're going to be here 30 weeks. We have put aside many, many important things. We have put aside many foreign trips, many local trips, whether it's to help dun sa tinamaan ng Nang lindol sa Mindanao or tinatamaan ng baha ngayon because we have to be here two o'clock until matapos tayo every Monday to Wednesday then after the sauna every Tuesday to Wednesday. I find it in bad taste that a bureau head will dictate to us that he's not available next week. I was Secretary of Foreign Affairs. That's why you have undersecretaries. That's why you have deputy director. So, I mean, I admire the patience of the prosecution, no? But even the prosecution, they have a way of timing and laying down the witnesses, eh. So, I don't want later on to say na eh dapat natanong ko muna ito sa unang witness, kaya lang si director matibag inuna dahil ganito o ganyan. I'd like to put that on record and ask my colleagues if that's acceptable to us. At least those who are not in jail or the 21 of us are here. The whole government, nakatutok. We put aside so many important things. And then one witness, who is in the government, who is a bureau head? Will tell us, sorry, but because he has to be with the FBI, siya na yung mauna tomorrow. That might be a bad precedent, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: May I be allowed to give a
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: reply? The gentleman
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: will please respond to the appoint of Senator-Judge Alan Cayetano.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: With due respect to the Honorable... Senator Judge Alan Peter Cayetano, we will always respect the decision of the honorable court. However, we will only be advancing his testimony one day based on the subpoena that we have requested the honorable court. He is scheduled to testify until Wednesday and that we will not disrupt the scheduled list of witnesses. We will simply advance it one day.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Would you respect, Congressman Representative Defensor, I ask That question poignantly last week. If Matibag will be one of your witnesses for this week and you said no. In fact, you corrected Atty. Ligutan when he mentioned Director Matibag as one of your witnesses and instead gave me a list of Lotoc, Zulaika Lopez, and Captain Belio. Matibag was not included. In fact, I don't think we issued a subpoena.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For Director Matibag for this week, given your manifestation after you took over, given that you have, as you said, control and supervision over the private, the counsel for the prosecutors. So he's not in your list this week. He's not being advanced for a day, sir.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: May I respond, Your Honor? Please
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: so.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Your Honor, that's correct. I gave a list of witnesses scheduled for Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday. However, Your Honor, to add, I also added that since NBI Director Matibag has been requested for a subpoena to testify within the week. I also added in my statement that we will inform the Honorable Court which day we can present the Honorable Matibag and I was expecting him to be presented on Wednesday after the testimony of Captain Belinda Bello, Your Honors.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I confirm that but the situation is Given the one-witness-per-day rule that we supposedly have under the rules of court, no subpoena has yet been issued to Director Matibag to appear this week. Can the Clerk of Court kindly confirm that for us on the record?
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: No subpoena has been issued for NBI Director Matibag.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: respond, Your Honor? Senator Judge Alan Cayetano is recognized.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: My statement and my question to the court is not really addressed to the prosecution. You will have to do the best you can to represent what you're fighting for. So I commend you for adjusting. But my recollection is because I'm also waiting for his testimony. And my recollection last week is that we will not see him this week. And I think 11 days. 11 days ang sa article na to. So we're on day 4. So kung hindi siya pwedeng next week, that's day 7, 8, 9.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Again, I don't want to dictate sa prosecution or ano. But to suddenly say na tomorrow na siya. When I'm preparing for our oral argument tomorrow and the other witnesses, it's a
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: little bit, it's a small inconvenience for today. But I hope it doesn't become a rule, especially for a bureau head.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: I mean, if no one else objects, but if someone objects, I don't think it's really a good rule. You know, rules are important. I'll have to keep, you say technicalities, and no, rules are important. So even yung notice, we agreed on, siding officer, three day ba? Five day notice?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Five days for witnesses not mentioned in the pre-trial order. And
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: then three days kapag ka...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Three days given the fact that we will be announcing the witnesses for the following week on the last day.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Anyway, I said my piece but I hope we will not be able to move faster if we have to accommodate the witnesses especially if they're in government.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: May I add something,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor? Before the Honorable Defensor, the Presiding Officer would like to hear from the Council for the Respondents. Atty. Vinlun, what say you?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor. We would have to oppose. On the basis of the following, number one, it will be in violation, your honor, of the impeachment
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: court's directive that was given last week insofar as the identities of the witnesses and as well as the order of the presentation. Number two, your honor, it will be again as mentioned by Senator Judge Cayetano, a violation of the five-day notice rule since while he was subpoenaed the week before, your honor, we are learning that
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: he will be presented this week. The five-day notice will not be observed. Number three, the prosecution cannot compel also the defense and this impeachment court to present witnesses according to their schedule, considering also that these witnesses have already been identified and determined. Of course, it will be a violation of the basic tenets of fair play. And to join again the manifestation of Senator Judge Caytana, it will set a bad precedent. And so far, surprise witnesses will be allowed at any point of the proceedings. Number five would be, it will also violate our right to cross-examine intelligently. We have done our best to prepare for
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: their witnesses. However,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: these last-minute changes really affect the preparation involved, Your Honor. And insofar as laying down the case that we want to establish and finally if there are violations of these proceeding rights there will be a violation of a
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: procedural due process which of course can give way to another ground to further delay the proceedings moreover your honor
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: um we If the prosecution would also allow, can we also get a copy, Your Honor, of that invitation? And may we inquire of the prosecution
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: if the particular travel authority has already been made? Because, Your Honor, we received information as well that
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the FBI had already conducted a summit, a regional summit of some sort, but it was conducted of June. In June of, in other words, last month, Your Honor, also in Bangkok, Thailand. So, we would have to, again, manifest and we would have to study, Your Honor, the invitation and counter-check and do the proper verification as well. So that, if
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: it is indeed viable, then we would understand, Your Honor, why it has to be attended to by Director Matiba, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Um, Senate President Gatchalian, recognized. You may proceed, sir.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Thank you, thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Sinusuportahan ko po yung statement ni Senator Judge Allen Cayetano. Dahil hindi lang naman po yung councils ng prosecution at defense na naghahanda. Pati mo mga senator judges naghahanda rin. At sa totoo lang itong weekend, marami rin sa ating mga senator judges ay pinag-aaralan kung ano yung kanilang maitatanong sa mga testigong ihaharap ngayong linggo. Marami po ay pinag-aaralan po yung mga ebedensyang inupload na para po sa ating mga senator judges. At hindi po ito konting ebedensya, pinag-uusapan po natin dito. Libo-libong mga papel at libo-libong mga ebedensya. Kung bigla pong may isisingit na testigo, hindi ho rin makakahanda po yung ating mga senator judges sa kanilang pagtatanong at hindi rin ho nilang mababasa yung mga dokumento at ebidensya na nakakabit ho doon sa testigong iharap. Kaya napakahirap naman po na naghahanda ho tayo pero biglang may mga ganitong supresya na hindi ho natin paghahandaan at hindi naman ho yan magiging maayos at For the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: record, Chair would like to confirm the statement of the Honorable Defensor, I will quote,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We'll take for both parties. With the permission of Senators, Senator Judge Cayetano and the Senate President, may we defer our ruling on this matter and ask the Council for the Prosecution to submit to us the letter given to you by Director Matibag for us to be able to look at it. Copy furnished, of course, the Council for the Respondent so that we can adequately go over it. And hopefully come up with a ruling before the day is over.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Would that be possible?
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: We will submit the letter. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, we shall do it that way. Kindly furnish a copy to counsel for the respondents as well for their review.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor. Your Honor, if the travel authority is also available, if we can ask for a copy.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Travel authority, if it's already issued.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Yes, of course. Kindly furnish us that as well. Your Honors, we will submit in good faith whatever the prosecution has received from Director Matibag, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: As well as kindly communicate with him, if possible, if he already has a travel authority for the same, so that we could evaluate it based on what you have. We cannot evaluate it based on what you don't have. So we will presume if you don't have it, it's not yet there.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, one last addition. Considering that there's a if and when they provide the travel authority, I understand, Your Honor, that one of the requirements is also the official invitation from the foreign body. So if they can also provide that, Your Honor, so that we can do a full review of this matter.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Vinluan, it's not really for the full review of the counsel for the prosecution but rather for this court's evaluation whether or not to allow the motion of the counsel.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Your Honors, I respectfully request that counsel for the panel of House prosecutors, Atty. Virgil Ligutan, be recognized for the presentation of our second witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Ligutan, counsel for the prosecutors, is recognized to present the prosecution's second witness. You may proceed, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mayong hapon sa atong tanan, the second witness for the prosecution is no other than Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc. We call to the witness stand, Atty. Lotoc.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly situate Atty. Lotoc to the witness stand.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lotoc, please remain standing as the Clerk of Court administers the oath so far as the prosecution's second witness is concerned. Clerk of Court is recognized.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Please raise your right hand. You,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Jeremy C. Lotoc. I, Jeremy C. Lotoc.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Do swear. Do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: swear.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: That the evidence you shall give.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That the evidence that I will be giving. In
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: the case now pending.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: In the
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: case now pending,
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: between the Philippines and Vice President Sarah Zimmerman Duterte,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: shall be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth. So help
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: me
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: God.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your witness, counsel for the prosecutors.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc, you may sit down.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your honors, the testimony of our second witness. Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc is offered to prove the following. Number one,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Jeremy Lotoc is a lawyer by profession and he was the chief of the Cybercrime Division of the National Bureau of Investigation, or NBI, in 2024.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: [unclear] ang dating Speaker ng House of Representatives. Pangatlo, napag-alaman ng NBI na ang mga pagbabanta ng Vice Presidente ay
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: seryoso at totoo matapos nilang isaalang-alang ang mga sumusunod Una, the manner of the respondent's delivery of the statement that she intended her remarks to be Real and serious threats. She was not merely joking when she uttered those threats.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pangalawa, mga kababayan, even before that fateful press conference on November 23, 2024, bago yung press conference na iyan,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May nakontrata ng mamamatay tao yung vicepresidente bago pa man ang press conference na iyan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pangatlo, ang utos ng vicepresidente sa asasin na huwag siyang titigil hanggat hindi napapatay ang Pangulo ng Pilipinas, ang Unang Ginang, at ang Speaker 4.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The result of the investigation, and after determining that the respondent's threats are serious and real, led the NBI to file complaints for three counts of grave threats and one count of inciting to sedition. 5. This witness, Atty. Lotoc, will identify and authenticate the affidavit of investigation, the annexes, as well as a couple of videos in relation to the NBI's investigation. 6. He will also testify on such other matters as are relevant and material to the impeachment of the Vice President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council for the Responder, Atty. Vinluan.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Subject for cross, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you so much. The Council for the Prosecutor may
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Dag-hagsalamat, Mr. Presiding Officer, Honorable Judges.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc. Sir. Maupay Ngakulup Haibo.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Maupay Ngakulup man, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Waray-waray po. We are both waray-waray. At the same time, Siwano. Atty. Lotoc, pwede bang mas malapit pa sa microphone para marinig ng sambayanan lahat ng isasagot ko sa mga tanong ko? Yes, sir. Now, Mr. Lotoc, kindly state your name, edad, and other personal circumstances.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I am Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc, 50 years of age, and currently the Regional Director of the NBI Bangsamoro Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao. Sir. Sinabi mo
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ikaw ay isang abogado, Atty. Lotoc, di ba? Opo. Na yung tanong, kailan ka naging membro ng ating Philippine Bar? I
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: was admitted to the Philippine Bar and took my lawyer's oath in 2013, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 2013. Now, Mr. Lotoc, ano ba yung current position mo, occupation mo, kung meron man?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The Regional Director of the NBI Bangsamoro Autonomous Region in Muslim Mindanao, Sir. Ikaw ay
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: isang NBI Regional Director for BARM. Now, yung tanong is how long have you been with the NBI? I've been in the NBI for the past 12 years, sir. 12 years. Tanong is, I think, based on my counting, that would be since 2014. Tama po ba? Opo, Your Honor. Now, kailan ka ba na-designate as the NBI Regional Director ng BARM? I was designated in January this year. As Regional Director of the NBI-BARM, sir. January 2026. Now, prior to your designation as the NBI Regional Director for BARM, ano ba yung previous position mo within NBI? I was the Regional
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Director for Region IV-B or MIMAROPA, sir. I think July 2025.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: July
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 2025
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you became. Okay. Now, prior to your designation, As NBI Regional Director for Mimaropa, what was your previous position kung meron man? I was the Chief of the NBI Cybercrime Division, Your Honor. Chief ng NBI Cybercrime Division. Now, kailan ka? Kailan ka na-designate as Chief ng NBI Cybercrime Division? I was designated in February 2023, Sir. 2023, no? Now, Sinabi mo ikaw ay naging chief ng NBI, Cybercrime Division. Now, yung tanong Mr. Atty. Lotoc is, what were your primary duties and functions bilang jepe ng NBI, Cybercrime Division?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Primary duties, among others, to plan, direct and supervise the investigation of... Cybercrime cases pursuant to Republic Act 10175 and other relevant laws. And part of my duties and responsibilities is to investigate high-profile cases pursuant to Republic Act 10867, specifically crimes committed by, through and with the use of information and communication technology, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, of course, you are aware Ikaw ay tumitistigo sa impeachment trial ng respondent. Now, yung tanong is, kilala mo ba yung respondent sa kasong ito? Yes, Your Honor. Okay, yung tanong now is, why
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: do you know her? She is the incumbent vice president of the Philippines and she is the subject of the investigation by the NBI, Cybercrime Division, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, nasabi mo, she is the subject. An investigation ng NBI Cybercrime Division. Now, yung tanong Atty. Lotoc is, kailan ba? Kailan nagsimula yung investigation ng NBI Cybercrime Division on the respondent? November 23, 2024, Sir. November 23, 2024. Yung tanong na Atty. Lotoc is, why? Why did the Cybercrime Division commence? An investigation on the Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We were directed by the then Director of Justice, IDP Santiago to conduct an investigation with regard to a certain video involving an online press conference held on November 23, 2024 where the Vice President uttered that she had already contracted a person.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: To
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: kill the President, Lisa Marcos and the former Speaker of the House, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, yung tanong Atty. Lotoc is, sa pagkakaalam mo, or kung alam mo, ba't yung NBI yung inaktasang gumawa ng investigasyon na ito? Well, under the law, specifically
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Republic Act 10867, the NBI has primary jurisdiction to undertake investigations On cases, among others, cases involving threats to security and assault against the persons of the highest officials, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, threats or assaults on or against highest officials, nasabi mo, di ba? Now, yung tanong nga to ni Lotoc is, sino ba yung mga highest officials na kung may threat or may assault sa kanila, NBI has to do it, an investigation? Sino yung mga officials na ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. They are the President, the Vice President, the Senate President, the Speaker of the House, and the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: All
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: right. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: so you mentioned Presidente, Vice President, tsaka yung iba pa. Now, you mentioned, Atty. Lotoc, that the NBI conducted an investigation on the respondent's statements during an online media briefing On November 23, 2024. Yung tanong na atty. Lotoc is, what
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: exactly did the respondents say on that day that resulted to the investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: On that online press conference held on November 23, 2024, the vice president uttered the following.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Huwag kang mag-alala, ma'am, sa security ko sapagkat may kinausap na akong tao. Ang sabi ko sa kanya, pag pinatay ako, patayin mo si BBM, si Lisa Marcos, si Martin Romaldez. No joke, no joke. Nag-bill-in na ako, ma'am. Ang sabi ko sa kanya, pag namatay ako, huwag kang tumigil hanggat hindi mo sila mapapatay. And he said yes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Atty. Lotoc, yun yung statement. Sino ba yung mga membro ng investigation team na galing sa division mo, yung cybercrime division?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We have Atty. Van Angluben, the then Executive Officer for Operations ng Cybercrime Division; Atty. Vanessa Asuncion, the Executive Officer for Administration back then; John Mark Calilung, the agent on case; and myself, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You mentioned Agent John Mark Calilung.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The same person who testified before you?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, how did your division commence the investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I instructed the team, specifically Agent Kalilong, that for this particular case, We have to follow the five phases or stages of cybercrime investigation, sir. So you instructed
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: John Mark Calilong to follow four stages of the investigation? The theme and John
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Mark Calilong, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now you mentioned, Atty. Lotoc, yung four stages ng cybercrime division for the information ng ating honorable judges sa kanyang publiko. This is the question now. Ano ba yung four stages ng investigation na ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: And then the legal evaluation and case filing as the final phase, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: these are the four stages.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, if you know, if you know, what was Agent Kalilong's response, and if any, sa naging instruction mo sa kanya, nasundin yung four stages ng cybercrime investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, he said yes, and then he proceeded to identify He proceeded to identify and preserve the digital
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: evidence in question. You said that you instructed Agent Kalilong to identify and preserve digital evidence. Yung tanong now is, what is this evidence that you are referring to?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: An online press conference held on November 23, 2024, which was streamed through the Facebook page of one Atty.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Herminio Lopez Roque Jr. or Harry Roque, Your Honor. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: it was the Facebook page of Harry Roque who livestreamed the video? Yes, Your Honor. Okay, now. Is she with us?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: After Agent Calilong identified and preserved yung sinasabi mong video, which you said is the first stage of the investigation, ano yung nangyari after that kung meron man tsaka kung alam mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The agent in case proceeded to collect that digital evidence and generated hash value on that digital evidence and at the same time stored that. In a data carrier, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alam mo, Atty. Lotoc, this is the first time na narinig natin yung term na hash value. And I think it's just proper na yung next question ko para malaman ng publiko. Atty. Lotoc, ano ba yung hash value na iyan?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, under the implementing rules and regulations of Republic Act 101.75 or the Reorganization and Modernization Act of NBI, hash value refers to Matematical algorithm applied
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: to the
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: information like the file, the physical disk or the logical disk, in this case, the digital evidence, thereby creating a digital fingerprint or DNA for that information or digital evidence, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, to create a fingerprint for the video, is that what you're saying? Yes, Your Honor. In this case, the video. Alright. Now, Mr. Witness. After the identification, preservation, collection and hashing, so far these are the two stages, what happened next, if any, in relation to your investigation on the Vice President's statement?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We proceeded to the analysis
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: and attribution phase. Now, ano yung nangyari, kung meron man, tsaka kung alam mo, in this analysis and attribution phase?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: In the analysis, we established the intent, the motive, the capability of the Vice President to carry out the threats [unclear] mentioned, as well as we proceeded to identify the individuals present in that press conference on November 23, 2024, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. So sinabi mo, you proceeded to identify the different individuals in that video. Siguro 'yung publiko, they're now interested. So what happened? What happened pagkatapos n'yong mag-proceed sa pag-identify, sino ba 'yung nasa video na 'yan?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: First, we identified media personalities from the Philippine Daily Inquirer, the Manila Times, Reuters, SMNI, et cetera. And then we also identified the Vice President herself, who in their presence openly and publicly uttered that she had already contracted a person to kill the President, Liza Marcos, and the former Speaker of the House, and instructed the person to be relentless in killing the three. It was streamed through the Facebook page of Harry Roque, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We continued the open source investigation to determine if there were utterances made by the Vice President in previous dates,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, ano ba yung naging resulta kung meron man tsaka kung alam mo sa naging open source investigation ng NBI into sinasabi mong mga previous statements ng Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We have found a press conference dated October 18, 2024 streamed through the official Facebook page of the Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: And we were able to identify, for us, being the investigator, at least three material lines or utterances made by the vice president, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. So you said in that press conference, sinabi mo you found three utterances or statements ng vice president. Among others, sir,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: yeah.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Among others. So let's focus on these three. Ano ba yung three statements na sinasabi mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: first one, The Vice President uttered, Gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya ba? And then the second one, the Vice President uttered, I realize toxic na itong relationship. Referring to the relationship between the Vice President and the President. And then number three, I imagine myself cutting his head. Okay now, recap,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sinabi mo, gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya. And then sinabi mo rin sa third, I imagine cutting his head. Based on your investigation, Atty. Lotoc, kaninong ulo ba yung rinerefer ng Vice President na gusto niyang tanggalin? The President of the Republic of the Philippines. Yung ulo ng Presidente ng Republika ng Pilipinas. Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What proof, if any, do you have that the Vice President said this?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We have that video, Your Honor, dated October 18, 2024. Now, kung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: maaalala mo, Mr. Witness, saang portion or portion ng video na iyan, maririnig yung Vice President. Sinasabi yung mga katagang, gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya. Imagine myself cutting his head.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, if I may refer to my notes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, I move that.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may do so.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, counsel for respondent may observe as the witness peruses his notes. Your Honor, may we also be allowed to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: do the same?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Similar order with respect to the counsel for the prosecutor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, from time stamps 1 hour 35 minutes and 57 seconds. 1 hour 36 minutes and 10 seconds.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: then 1 hour 36 minutes and 52 seconds. And then 1 hour 36 minutes and 58 seconds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, so for your honor, for the record, Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: your honor, please, sorry. The gentleman mentioned two timestamps. So question, if those portions are shown to you, Will you be able to identify the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: same? Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, at this juncture, Your Honor, please, the video has already been identified, marked and identified by our previous witness, and it is marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-11 for the prosecution. We move that these two portions with individual timestamps as mentioned be shown to this witness for his identification, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Where is the USB,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: counsel? We move that we be allowed to unseal the marked exhibit that was presented last time. It's with us. It's with the prosecution.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly unseal the document in the presence of the counsel for respondent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witnesses instructed to unseal the USB.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: This has been previously marked. So after the unsealing... Council for the Prosecutor and for the Respondent are instructed to kindly accompany each other to the tech booth to make sure it is the same, one and the same USB that will be played.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kung may bala kayong buksan ulit, huwag niyo na masyadong i-tape na madami.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Para hindi masyadong matagal pag i-unseal.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For the record, this will be timestamps 1 hour 35 minutes to 57 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes and 10 seconds for the first timestamp, I mean for the first portion. And the second portion is from 1 hour 36 minutes to 52 seconds to 1 hour 36 minutes and 58 seconds.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Gusto
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: ko tukanggalin yung ulo niya ba.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: I realized toxic na yung relationship.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There's one more council, right? Yes, Your Honor. Waiting for the second video consisting
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: of 6 seconds only, Your Honor, please.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Imagine myself cutting his head.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, thank you so much. Your Honor, please. May I proceed, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, may I proceed? Mr. Witness, what
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: relation, if any, do those videos have, portions of the videos have, with the video you mentioned earlier?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's the same video I mentioned, Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor. Okay, thank you so much. Let's proceed. Atty. Lotoc, now, after you discovered these previous statements by the Vice President, what happened next, if any? In relation to the investigation you conducted on the Vice President's statements on November 23, 2024?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. We have also discovered reactions from the recipients, specifically from the President himself, the Speaker of the House, relevant government agencies tasked to secure the life of the President and the national security, Your Honor. Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much. Let's focus on the President. Kasi it's his head. Ulo ng Presidente.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Let's focus on the precedents. Now, what did he say again in particular?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I may refer to my notes, sir?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, you
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: may do so. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Among others, quote, Nakakabahala ang mga pahayag na narinig natin itong mga nakaraang araw. Nandiyan ang walang pakundangang pagbumura at ang pagbabanta ng planong ipapatay ang ilan sa atin. If that's how easy it is to plan for the death of a president, how about ordinary citizens? That kind of criminal action should not be overlooked. That is my belief."
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa naging mga pagbabanta ng bisipresidente laban sa buhay niya, could you just summarize exactly ano ba yung tugon ng former Speaker ng House of Representatives?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. If I remember it right, I think the Speaker issued a statement during the plenary session, November 25, 2024, which was published in the ANC Digital. And then, among others, The former speaker stated that the utterances were dangerous, unprecedented.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Isa itong banta sa demokrasya at sa siguridad ng bansa.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. Now, Mr. Witness, Atty. Lotoc, sinabi mo rin na may mga ahensya ng gobyerno na nagbigay din ng kanilang tugon sa mga pagbabanta ng vice-presidente. If you may, anong mga ahensya na ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. For one, the Presidential Communications Office, the Philippine National Police, the National Security Council, and the Armed Forces of the Philippines.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Let's focus on muna sa Presidential Communications Office. Na ano ba yung statement ng Presidential Communications Office kung alam mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I remember it right, the PCO,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As an active threat. And directed the Presidential Security Command
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: to,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think, investigate the matter. As an active threat. It was the Executive Secretary who directed the... Presidential Security Command Sir, based on that statement.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, sinabi mo rin yung Philippine National Police. Yung tanong is kung maalala mo, ano ba yung sinabi ng PNP in response sa naging mga pagbabanta ng vice-presidente sa buhay ng presidente sa kayong dalawa pa?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, if I may refer to my notes. Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so, Your Honor. You may do so, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The Philippine National Police issued a statement relative to the press conference made by the Vice President. The Philippine National Police threats any threat to the safety and security of the President and all public officials with the utmost seriousness. In light of the Vice President Sarah Duterte's recent statement, which directly referenced an assassin contracted to target the President, The PNP recognizes the grave nature of this matter. The safety of the President is a national concern, and any direct or indirect threat to his life must be addressed with the highest level of urgency.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The PNP
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: used, based on your statement, as the response of the PNP, The PNP used the term assassin in referring to the person contracted by the Vice President to kill the President and two others?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, it was not just the PNP. Even the Presidential Communications Office also used the term assassin, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, what about the National Security Council? Ano bang sinabi ng NSA kung alam mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, Your Honor, if I may refer to my notes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Pwede na ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, may the witness be allowed to refer to his notes once more.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may do so, Mr. Witness. Thank you,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, the question was about the statement of the NSC, right? Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Quote, the National Security Council considers all threats to the President of the Philippines as serious. Any and all threats against the life of the President shall be validated and considered a matter of national security. End quote.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, sinabi mo rin na yung Armed Forces of the Philippines, or AFP, nagbigay din ng kanilang response sa naging pagbabanta ng vicepresidente, kung alam mo, tsaka kung maaalala mo. Ano ba yung sinabi ng Armed Forces of the Philippines?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Same,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, if I may refer to my notes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For orderly proceeding, Your Honor, please. I think it's proper for a third decision to ask to be recognized first.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Depends. What is the pleasure of Council for Respondent Attorney season?
Sheila C. Sison: We'll just state an observation on the notes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, we agreed that only one counsel shall speak. In so far as the presentation of a witness is concerned, this was objected to by the Council for Respondents even if it was asked for by the Council for the Prosecutors.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We will do that, Your Honor. For
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the record, we are not objecting but you know, for a properly proceeding, Atty. Sison,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council, it's okay. The Chair will make a ruling. Atty. Vin Luan can handle that with your permission. Atty. Sison.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, I'd just like to share the observation that the witness is reading from notes, from
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: his notes and not directly from The document that he identified.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And if I may reply to that, Your Honor, to that non-issue, Your Honor, if I may? Yes, Your Honor. Yes, counsel for the prosecution. Your Honor, wala po sa rules na kailangan
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: na yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: tugon ng isang witness, sinabi niyang notes, dapat based sa isang dokumento. In fact, Your Honor, please, yung iniisip ng ating rules, yung mga notes na ginawa mismo ng witness. For the public, if you're interested, you may look at Rule 130, Section 16 ng Rules of Court. Andun yun. Pupwedeng tingnan ng isang testigo yung notes na ginawa niya. Rule 130, Section 16. Before
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I recognize counsel for respondent, Senator Judge Lacson, what is your pleasure, sir? Thank you, Mr. President Officer. This is relevant to the discussion.
Sen. Panfilo “Ping” M. Lacson: The gentleman may proceed and he has two minutes. Yes. You requested to refer to your notes a number of times during your direct examination. Ang tanong ko, are you referring to an investigator's notes or notebook or simply notes?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. During the investigation, I have copies of the affidavit of investigations that we have.
Sen. Panfilo “Ping” M. Lacson: I ask that question because my understanding of an investigator's notes or notebook, to be credible,
Sen. Panfilo “Ping” M. Lacson: Ito ang
Sen. Panfilo “Ping” M. Lacson: ginawa niyo mismo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. During the investigation. Thank you for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the clarification. Thank you, Senator Judge Lacson. Noted and entered in the records. Counsel for Respondent, what is your pleasure?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, that was a mere manifestation, Your Honor. We just want to put it for the record.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: There being no objection, some witness may proceed and answer, or counsel may proceed with his questions.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The Armed Forces of the Philippines. Ano sinabi ng Armed Forces? Are we done? Not yet?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Okay. So, let's go back. Yeah, if I may, Your Honor. Witness
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may continue to answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: On November 23, 2024, General Romeo S. Browner, Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces of the Philippines, issued the following statements, quote, The Armed Forces of the Philippines is a professional organization focused on its mandate to protect the people and the state. Our personnel are loyal to the Constitution and the chain of command, unquote. Hindi ko na po binasa lahat, sir. Okay, now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: After you and your team discovered these responses, Atty. Lotoc, what happened next, if any, kung meron mo, tsaka kung alam mo, in relation sa investigation niyo, sa mga statements ng Vice President on that day, November 23, 2024?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We issued subpoena to the media personalities present during the online press conference of November 23, 2024.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: For them to appear on December 4, 2024, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You issued a subpoena to the media personalities that you said andun sa media conference na iyon to appear on December 4, 2024. Now, sino ba yung mga media personalities na pinasubpoena ng NBI?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, Your Honor, if I may refer to my... You may do so, Mr. Reyes. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: First to the late Demsi Saidin Reyes of the Philippine Daily Inquirer, and then to Red Whore Marquee J. Mendoza of the Manila Times, Bons Magsambol of Rappler, Ana Rosario Malindo Uy of the Manila Times, Jason Rubrico of the SMNI, and Mikael Flores of the Reuters, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Now, Mr. Witness, yung tanong now is, ba't kailangang isampinan ng NBI itong mga media personalities na ito na mag-appear sa NBI sa araw na iyon, December 4, 2024?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, they were there during the online presscon and they participated the press conference. So, ang tingin namin meron silang personal knowledge kasing nandoon sila at nag-participate po sila kaya... We deemed it proper to issue subpoena on them.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So you said na they were subpoenaed to appear on December 4, 2024 in the NBI. Now, what happened on that day, December 4, 2024, if any, and if you know in relation to the investigation you conducted?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The agent on case reported to me that Mr. Reyes and I think Mr. Magsambol appeared before the Office of the Cybercrime Division and participated in the process of the interview.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, how do you know that these two individuals, at least Dempsey Reyes, may his soul rest in peace, and Magsambol appeared before the NBI on that day, December 4, 2024?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Aside from the fact that the agent in case reported that to me, he showed to me the minutes of meeting wherein the signatures of The late Mr. Reyes and Magsambol were affixed on it, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: May nakapirma ko sila doon sa minutes of meeting, sir. All
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: right.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Now, thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so much, Atty. Lotoc. Now, Atty. Lotoc, you said that your team interviewed members of the media. You issued subpoena to them and they appeared. Now, what else happened, if any, in relation to the investigation you conducted?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We issued subpoena at testificandum to the vice president herself to shed light in the investigation we are conducting, sir. So you're telling
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the public that you, NBI, also issued a subpoena to the vice president? Yes, Your Honor. Proceed, Your Honor. Now, what proof, if any, do you have that in fact the NBI issued a subpoena addressed
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: to the vice president? We have copy of that subpoena at testificandum dated November 25, 2024, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, kung yung subpoena na binigay ng NBI sa vice-presidente may petsang No. 25 taong 2024 ipapakita sa iyo, makikilala mo ba yung dokumentong ito? Opo. Now, we are now in the process of presenting to you a subpoena at testificandum. Dated on even date, December 25, 2024. That is... For
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the record,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: this is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-4 for the prosecution. Have you perused the same, Atty. Lotto? Yes, Your Honor. Question, what relation, if any, does that document have with the subpoena you mentioned?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: This is the same subpoena I mentioned, Sir. Thank you so much. So the NBI issued
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: a subpoena to the Vice President. Your Honor, can
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: we just make a comment?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondents, recognize.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: may we just put on record that Exhibit P-4-4 is a photocopy and it was not the original or the certified.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: are ready to produce that. That's the next step we are supposed to do. We have a copy of the certified true copy. We invite the defense to check the same for comparison. Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondent.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, it is a faithful reproduction of the certified true copy, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted for the records. Counsel
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: for the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: prosecutors may
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: proceed. Now, Mr. Witness, we would like to know.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How did the Vice President respond, if any, if at all, and if you know, to the NBI's subpoena issued
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: to her?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, the Vice President did not appear, Your Honor. Instead, she sent her lawyer, Atty. Paul Lawrence Lim, if I'm not mistaken.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: she did
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: not appear?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sir. Okay, now, question. If you know, if you know, What was the Vice President's reason for failing to appear at the NBI, in the NBI despite the subpoena issued to her?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think the Vice President in effect was saying there were office matters to tend to so she cannot attend the scheduled subpoena.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How did the respondent, the vice president, inform you that she could not attend the Sampidna because she was attending to, quote, office matters, unquote?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: There was a letter, I think, dated November 28, 2024, which was submitted by the council of the vice president, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So the letter, December 20, 2024. Now, kung yung kopya ng letter na yan ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify mo ba yung letter na ito? Now, we are
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: in the process of showing you a copy of the letter dated November 28, 2024. Counsel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for the Prosecutor may approach as well as Counsel for the Respondent.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. This is the same letter that I've mentioned.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, can I make a manifestation at this point?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Prosecutor may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, the letter from the Vice President's lawyer is not marked in exhibit.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If the defense will agree, we move that the same be marked as an additional exhibit for the prosecution and the specific marking that we are asking the court to follow is Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-32 for the prosecution, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Counsel for the respondent? We have no objection to that, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So ordered. So marked. Thank you so much. Now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong ginawa ng NBI after yung Vice Presidente hindi sumipot sa NBI despite the subpoena kung meron man?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Puntahan natin yung letter na iyan Kung alam mo, ano ba yung sinabi ng NBI sa letter na iyan na pinadala sa Vice President after hindi siya sumipot despite the subpoena sent to her?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, the document would speak for itself. No need for the witness to read.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think the counsel
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: is— Witness
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may answer, if he knows.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, among others, sir, sinabi ko doon sa letter namin na— Nung December 2, 2024 na ini-inform namin ang Vice Presidente na iniimbestigahan din po namin yung alleged threat against sa kanyang life at sinabi namin na kailangan namin yung kanyang presensya para may makuha kaming information para ho may mapagsimulan kami
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: doon
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sa investigation against threat to her life, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What proof, if any, do you have that the NBI issued another subpoena addressed to the Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We have that copy of the subpoena dated, if I'm not mistaken, December 2, 2024.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotto, kung yung kopya ng pangalawang subpoena ipapakita sa iyo, ma-identify mo ba? Yes, sir. Now, we are now in the process of showing you that subpoena, the defense may also check. Counsel for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the prosecutor as well as respondent may approach to compare.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And for the record, that second subpoena addressed to the vice president has been previously marked as exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-6 for
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: the prosecution. That's the same subpoena I mentioned, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, so that's the same subpoena. Do we have any observation from the defense? Counsel for respondent.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The document is a machine copy, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Machine copy.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: we move that the certified true copy in our possession be compared with the photocopy identified by the witness, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, this has not been marked, right? This has been
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: marked this time, Your Honor, please. This
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: has been marked already?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Same officer, Rick. Observation, Your Honor, as the last document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Meaning, it is a photocopy?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It is the same as the photocopy of... The copies are the same, but it is not the original, just a photocopy of the original, Your Honor. That was certified.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wait, so... I do not get it, Consul.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor... The other document that the prosecution is showing is a certified copy, Your Honor. So, in other words, it is the same as the photocopy that was previously marked, Your Honor. But certified? Correct, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Noted. Thank you. You may proceed. Now, you also mentioned, Atty. Lotoc, yung isang letter, this time, it's dated December 2, 2024. Now, kung yung letter na iyan ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify mo ba ito? Yes, sir. Now, we are in the process of showing you a copy of that letter that is previously marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-5, with sub-marking P-Roman numeral 4-5, small letter A. May you peruse the same and answer the question after perusing the document, what relation, if any, does this document have with the one you mentioned?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The same document that I mentioned, sir. Okay, thank you so much. Now, a picture with us. Sa pangalawang sabbina, Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the document again is a photocop, machine copy.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, we move that the certified true copy that we have in possession be compared with the photocopy that is marked in exhibit for the prosecution office.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for Responder is instructed to so view the certified true copy and make the corresponding manifestation of their observation.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Faithful Reproduction of the Certified Copy, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Noted.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Thank you so much. Proceed, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Atty. Lotoc, ano ba yung naging tugon, kung meron man, tsaka kung alam mo, ng Vice Presidente sa pangalawang sabina na in
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: -issue ng NBI? Yes, Your Honor. The Vice President, again, did not appear, but instead sent her lawyer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Another letter. Another letter? Yes, Your Honor. Submitted to the Office of the Cybercrime Division. Okay now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kung alam mo ano ba yung nilalaman ng letrang iyan, yung pangalawang letter ng Vice President in response to the second subpoena ng NBI?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I remember it right, sinasabi doon we must take the obvious. The NBI is under the... Administrative Supervision ng Secretary of Justice who is an alter ego of the President and the Executive Secretary is the Chief Alter Ego so may narapat daw niya makinig sa kanyang Council at hindi na mag-appear sa subpoena ng NBI. Now, what proof as any do you have of that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: letter?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: have a copy of that letter, Your Honor. Kung yung kopya ng letter na yan ipapakita sa iyo, ma-identify mo ba? Yes, Your Honor. Now, we are showing you a copy of the letter dated December 10, 2024. The question after you peruse to say what relation, if any, does that document have with the letter you mentioned?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The same document that I mentioned, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, manifestation, the same letter coming from the Vice President's Council. Ang mga mga
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The letter states, if any?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, the counsel for the Vice President stated that the Vice President is confident that the NBI will also investigate the alleged threat against her life. 'Yun po 'yung tenor ng letter na 'yon, sir. Now—
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: eto yung tanong now. You mentioned earlier
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That the Vice President stated that she already contracted an assassin to kill the President and the two others. Now, Atty. Lotto. Wait, wait, wait. Not yet done. Not yet done. No question yet.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Please proceed, Council. As the head, as the head of the investigation team,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: what was your impression of
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the Vice President when she declared, That she already contracted an assassin to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kill the President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House of Representatives.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Objection, Your Honor. Call
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: for an opinion. Opinion. You may cite the rule, Your Honor, please. And misleading
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: as well, Your Honor. She never mentioned the word assassin.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, may I reply to that, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the prosecution is recognized.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The term assassin [unclear]. It is the same term used by the PNP and by the PCO. So it's not plucked out of thin air, Your Honor, please. So we have basis for using the term assassin.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But, Your Honor, counsel mentioned that it was VP Sara who mentioned it, and that was phrased in his answer. So we are objecting to that, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the understanding that the witness will base his answer on his investigation or knowledge insofar as the investigation that he himself conducted and led is concerned, and not as a conclusion of fact and law, the witness may answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What was your impression?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. To me, as the chief investigator at that time, the utterance as made by the Vice President was serious.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Serioso, tsaka totoong pagbabanta. Now, what made you say that? Na yung pagbabanta ng vicepresidente ay both Serioso at Totoo
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Reactions from several government agencies, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Content and context. Now, exactly, yung tanong is, exactly, exactly, how did you analyze the content and the context of the entire press conference?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We considered several factors, Your Honor, in the analysis of that content and context. Several factors. To be exact,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kung alam mo, ilang factors kinonsider nyo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: At least four. Number one, the delivery or manner in which the utterances were spoken. Number two, the literal meaning of the statement.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Number three,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: the nature of the instruction.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Number four, the relationship between the parties. So, four factors. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc, let's go to the first factor. Let's go to the first factor. The delivery of the manner in which the threats were spoken. What made you say that the respondent was both serious and real when she uttered those threats?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Based
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: on his investigation, counsel, he may testify as to that. Witness na yan, Sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The Vice President was furious and fuming mad when she uttered those. Could you repeat it? Furious and?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And fuming mad, Sir. Fuming mad. Furious and fuming mad. Now, what made you say na yung Vice Presidente was both furious, furious, and
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: fumingly mad? Well, nakita ho namin dun sa video nung nirun ho namin, Your Honor, if I'm not mistaken, I think more or less walong beses ho siyang galit na galit at nagmumura at minumura yung Presidente, si First Lady, and then si former Speaker of the House, sir. Walong beses? If I'm not mistaken, more or less, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, and then you're referring to the video. Now, in what particular portions of the video, okay, Did the Vice President hurl invectives or, sa Tagalog, pagmumura kung sa Cebuano pamalikas kung hawaray-waray buyayaw? Mga ilang beses? Walo? In what particular portions?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, if I may refer to my notes. You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may do so.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In the interest of time, while the councils are doing that, I move that the previously marked and identified exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-10, which is the flash drive containing the video of that press conference, be unsealed in the presence of councils from both sides.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed. And
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: then you may now answer, Mr. Witness, anong mga timestamps ba ito? Your Honor,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: from timestamp? 53 minutes to 27 seconds and 53 minutes to 39 seconds. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 53 minutes 27 seconds to 53 minutes 39 seconds. The second time stamp if you may?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 54 minutes to 03 seconds and 54 minutes to 08 seconds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 54 minutes 03 seconds to 54 minutes 08 seconds. That's the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: second time stamp. What about? The next timestamp if you know?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 55 minutes to 42 seconds and 56 minutes to 07 seconds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 55 minutes 42 seconds to 56 minutes 06 seconds. What about the fourth timestamp if you know?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 58 minutes to 38 seconds up to 58 minutes to 47 seconds 58
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: minutes 38 seconds to 58 minutes to 47 seconds what about the fifth time stop if you know um
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: one hour zero two minutes and 25 seconds one hour zero two minutes and 32 seconds sir one hour zero
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: two minutes to 25 seconds to one hour zero two minutes 32 seconds what about the next the sixth time stop if you know um
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: one hour
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 05 minutes and 08 seconds up to 1 hour, 05 minutes and 31 seconds. 1 hour, 05
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: minutes, 08 seconds to 1 hour, 05 minutes, 31 seconds. What about the last timestamp, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 1 hour, 08 minutes and 43 seconds. And in 1 hour, 08 minutes and 54 seconds, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 1 hour, 08 minutes, 43 seconds to 1 hour, 08 minutes, 54 seconds. Your Honor, we move that those seven timestamps identified by the witness be shown in sequence, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ordered, counsel for the prosecutors will kindly give the flash drive to be unsealed by the witness. As witnessed by counsel for the respondents thereafter.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For council of the parties to kindly accompany each other to the tech booth so that the USB may be played with respect to the specified timestamps of the witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I think we
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: have two more.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Gusto ko lang magtrabaho. Gusto ko lang tapusin niyo ng show niyo sa House of Representatives para makabalik na kami.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: think we have two more.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I think
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that will be the last. That will be the last council. That's the seven timestamps. Let me confirm. Atty. Magalyon.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. We have one more. We have two more round, please. I was told we have two more time stops. Two more. Thank you.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Nakangampanya tayo. Takasakay tayo sa aeroplano. Magkatabi tayo. Nagre-reklamo ka. Putang ina ka. Walang pera.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: last one.
Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte: Maalis mo man ako sa presidential race, hindi pa rin ikaw ang presidente. Tingin ako. Walang bubotos niyo. Please lang.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wala.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, Your Honor, those were the seven timestamps, portions of the video where the Vice President hurled invectives and profanities. Now the question is, may I proceed, Your Honor? Counsel, to clarify, the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Vice President hurled invectives period, not necessarily against the three officials mentioned. Most of them were against the three
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: officials, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I only counted or heard one or two. Out of the seven, I heard Representative Chua, but he's not one of the subject matters of this case. But just for the record, does the witness confirm that? Out of the seven timestamps, there are approximately two or three that mentioned either all three or one of the top officials. Would that be correct, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think more than that, sir, if you can see the context. Make your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: voice
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: louder. Louder.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I'm not mistaken, I think five times referring to either Martin Romaldez or Liza Marcos or the president.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The rest were either congressmen or a particular congressman.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I'm not mistaken, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness, itong mga seven timestamps kung saan nagmumura, nagmumura yung vicepresidente. Why? Is this a factor in classifying her threats as serious and
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: real? Yes, Your Honor. It's very much a factor because we want to establish the intent of the Vice President and that intent is crucial in our investigation. We want to determine whether those utterances made by the Vice President
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So what was your conclusion? Your Honor. So what was your conclusion? Was it serious or real?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yeah, Your Honor. Okay, serious and real. Let's go to factor number two. So two out of four factors now. Sinabi mo 'yung literal meaning, utterances of the Vice President, literal meaning. Why is this a factor in your conclusion na seryoso at totoo 'yung pagbabanta ng Vice Presidente?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The Vice President had already contracted a person to kill the President, Liza Marcos, and the former Speaker, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Siguro, so the public will understand, I want you to answer in Tagalog. Ba't mahalaga sa inyo, sa imbestigasyon n'yo, na 'yung pagkukontrata ng tao na papatay sa Pangulo, sa kanyang asawa, nangyari ito bago pa man 'yung press conference? Ba't mahalaga sa imbestigasyon n'yo 'yan?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Basically, it's indicative of intent that the utterance was deliberately made by the Vice President, and it really shows serious, actual, and real threat.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc, let's go to the third factor. Yung third factor is now sinasabi mo, yung nature ng instruction. Now, could you tell the public and the court, ano bang ibig sabihin ng factor number three, nature of the instruction?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. In those utterances, the Vice President said, wag kang tumigil hanggat hindi mo sila mapapatay. It shows persistence on the part of the Vice President that she was
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: is alarming
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: from the point of view of law enforcement agencies.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, in Tagalog, if you may, ba't mo nasabing nakakaalarma? Nakakaalarma 'yung sinabi ng Vice Presidente?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, puwede hong mag-take advantage 'yung ibang grupo diyan, ibang individual. God forbid may mangyari sa Vice Presidente for one reason or the other. Mati-trigger ho ngayon 'yung instruction. And then, papatayin ngayon, God forbid again, ang Presidente, Liza Marcos, ang former Speaker. And, in fact, even 'yung triggering na phase na 'yun, puwedeng mag-take advantage doon 'yung ibang grupo, thinking na pag in-assassinate natin ang tatlo, ang sisisihin ang Vice President. So marami hong anggulo, Your Honor. Para sa amin sa law enforcement, medyo magiging disorder, magiging chaotic, magiging anarchy 'yung society pag hindi siya na-address. 'Yun po 'yung sa amin as investigator, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: But was she not only joking, Atty.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Lotoc?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Jackson, leading, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There's basis to that, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sustained,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now. Now. Let's proceed,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Witness. So far, you mentioned, ito yung mga factor. Manner, literal meaning, nature of the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: instruction. Ano pa yung fourth factor kung alam mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The relationship between the parties, meaning the relationship between the vice president and the president.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: what about the fourth factor? Why is it significant to investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, in one of the utterances made by the vice president, she characterizes the relationship with the president as toxic. If I'm not mistaken, at least three times niya binigyan siyang term ng toxic, referring to the relationship between her and the president, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, what were your reasons, if any, that made you conclude na nasabi na ng vice president that toxic yung relationship niya between her and the president?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Objection calls for an opinion. Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Investigation. Witness may answer. Part of his investigation.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, una, yung resignation niya as Secretary ng Department of Education.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Pangalawa, yung utterances niya noong October 18, noong sinabi niya na, I realize toxic na itong relationship.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Gusto kong tanggalin yung ulo niya ba? And then I imagine myself cutting his head.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What else,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: if any?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The reaction of the recipient of those utterances, Your Honor. The reaction from the President himself. So
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the reaction from the President himself. Now, you already mentioned kanina ano yung reaction ng President. Yung tanong na ato ni Lotto is, why did you consider? Yung reaction ng mga recipients ng pagbabanta, kagaya ng President. Let's focus on the President. Ba't nyo kinonsider yung reaction nila?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, we want to establish whether the recipient of those utterances felt intimidated by those statements or did they took it serious and actual threat.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Material sa amin yun, Your Honor, if only to establish the mens rea. Mens
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: rea ng krimen. Now, let's focus on the President. Let's focus on the President. Ito yung premise now. Based on your investigation, what was your impression of the President based on his reaction? Was he intimidated?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, yung opening statement ng Presidente, ang sabi niya, nakakabahala. Ang mga narinig natin itong mga nakaraang araw. Ito 'y
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: isang kriminal na pagtatangka. Papalagan ko ito. Yes, Your Honor. The President took the threat by the Vice President as serious
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: and real. Now, Mr. Witness, aside from yung reaction ng mga recipients, we focus on the President. Ano pa yung ibang mga factors na kinonsider nyo kung meron pa man?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. We find it, this is from the point of view of the investigator, we find it disturbing when we tried to compare the utterances made in October 18 and the utterances made in November 23.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: May nakita kami doon at least tatlo o apat na medyo, sabi ko nga, disturbing from the point of view namin.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Disturbing? Tatlo o apat na disturbing na?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Utterances. Now, let's go to that. You said you compared the utterances on October 18 and November 23. Sabi mo, you found at least three or four disturbing statements. Tama ba? Now, ano ba 'yung three statements na ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, we are trying to establish the patterns and the consistencies of those utterances. For instance, noong October 18, ang sabi niya is,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Walang number one ang Pilipinas na ito. Para sa akin, number two lamang ito. Walang number one. And then we compared it in November 23. Ang sabi niya, nireiterate niya, I do not recognize anybody above me. That's number one, Your Honor. The number two,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: ang
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sabi niya noong October 18, hindi marunong maging presidente yung nakaupo. Kasalanan ko ba yun? And then we compared it in November 23. Ang sabi niya doon, This country will go to hell because that person who's sitting, sabi niya is, doesn't know how to be a president and who is a liar. Then number three, ang sabi niya sa October 18, meron akong limang impeachable offense na alam kay BBM pero papasa ba dyan sa house? Siyempre hindi. Then i-compare namin yung November 23. Ang sabi niya doon is he was lying through his teeth para makuha lang yung voto ng mga tao and then nagmura na siya P.I. Ka, BBM, Lisa Marcos, and Martin Romaldes, Your Honor. What
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: do you mean by P.I.?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Putang ina, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. You said that you found these three comparisons disturbing. Now, these three, ano yung significance ng three comparisons na ito sa investigasyon niyo? Kung meron man.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Based on these patterns and consistencies in the utterances made by the Vice President,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: it
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: appears that these statements have tendency to steer up the people against the government, have tendency to disturb the peace of the community, Have tendency to undermine the peace and order, the public peace and order, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Mr. Witness, given all these findings, sinabi mo seryoso tsaka totoo yung mga pagbabanta ng Vice Presidente, anong ginawa ng division mo kung meron man
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: in
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: relation to the investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We executed, Your Honor, affidavit of investigation and we recommended criminal charges.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 3 counts for grave threats and 1 count for inciting prostitution, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, now, na-mention mo yung affidavit of investigation. For clarity, anong date ng affidavit of investigation na sabi mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: February 10, 2024. Ah, 2025, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: February 10. Kung yung affidavit of investigation and the annexes ipapakita sa'yo, ma-identify mo ba yung affidavit na ito? Yes, sir. I'm showing you now a copy of the affidavit of investigation. May page February 10, 2025. That is previously marked for the prosecution as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-3. You peruse the documents and access. I move that the defense be allowed to peruse the same. And the question is, what do these documents have? What relation, if any, do these documents have with the documents you mentioned?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council for both parties may approach.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Manifestation, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council for the Respondent may proceed.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, we'd just like to manifest, Your Honor, that the marked document, permanently marked by the prosecution, does not contain any annexes. And the other set of documents that he is comparing it to has affidavit annexes, your honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I can reply to that, your honor, please. Counsel for the prosecution
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: will please reply.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Number one, the affidavit of investigation, the annexes thereto, ay makikita yung mga annexes, most of them. As separate documents that have been pre-marked. Ulitin ko, yung mga hinahanap ng depensa, ng mga annexes sa affidavit and investigation, nasa record ng Senado yan, because na-marka separately, because they have been identified separately also by the previous witness. I hope that satisfies. Council, what does Council
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for the Respondents say?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, is that an admission that
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The affidavit of investigation was stripped of its annexes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, if I may, ang klaro namang sinabi ko. Can I reply to that, Your Honor, please? Sir, I would like to clarify the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: matter instead. Are all the annexes listed and identified in the footnotes of the affidavit of investigation? Marked or pre-marked by the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: prosecution? I can answer that. Most of them, Your Honor, please. And I can identify ano yung mga hindi na-marked saka yung reason. So most, not all? Yes, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And for the record, that the affidavit of investigation that the witness is identifying and that you have marked does not contain any of the annexes mentioned in the affidavit of investigation without prejudice, of course, to the annexes that you already marked.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And identified by either this or other witnesses?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor. Not attached specifically to the affidavit but found in the same record of the witness. Not attached to the document
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: that the witness is identifying right now? Yes, Your Honor. Does that satisfy the counsel for this matter? Your Honor, we're
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: not objecting as to how they marked it. We're just manifesting it for the record. That
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: it's not
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: there?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes. So noted. Witness may answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, this is the same document that I... Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You have? You have?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, this is the same document that I mentioned.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. May I proceed, Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now. Atty. Lotoc, ah, sorry, sorry.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Just to manifest, Your Honor, that
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: again,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the comparison, Your Honor, was made with the certified true copy, not the original, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you. So noted. Thank you so much.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Please proceed, counsel, for the procedure. Atty. Lotoc, sa pahing ng 28 ng Affidavit of Investigation, may makikita ang perma sa ibabaw ng pangalang S.A. Jeremy Lotoc. Makikita mo ba yan? Yung tanong, kaninong perma ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: This is my signature, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And sa page 29 ng affidavit, may makikitang pirma sa ibabaw ng pangalang S.A. Jeremy Lotoc. Kaninong pirma ba ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, sa akin, pirma ho ito, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, at this juncture, the prosecution moves that the two signatures of the witness be marked as Exhibit P-Roman numeral 4-3-1, that's for the first, and the other one P-Roman numeral 4-3-2. Reason is these signatures have not yet been marked in evidence, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: No objections to that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor. Thank you so much. Now, may I proceed, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc, in paragraphs 202 and 203, Ang naging answer ng Vice President dated May 25, 2026 to the Articles of Impeachment, which document forms part of the record of these courts.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sinasabi ng Vice President na
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: she was merely exercising her
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: freedom of expression. Freedom of expression, sinabi niya. That's protected, yung pagbabanta niya. Are you aware of this defense? Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotto, as
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: a lawyer and as the head of the NBI Cybercrime Division, that's the basis, Your Honor. Do you agree with this?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Objection, Your Honor. Calls for an opinion. This is not part of the investigation. She's
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: a lawyer, Your Honor. It
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: does call for an opinion and it's not part of the investigation, Counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly reform your question. I know where you're getting at but kindly reform your question. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, Atty. Lotak, you are aware of the defense that it's a freedom of expression. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In your investigation, did you consider this, if at all, and if any?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Objection, Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, of course, Your Honor. We consider that whether mag-fall fault ba siya sa confines ng freedom of speech. And what was your finding? That's the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: basis now.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: What was your finding? Well, una, three reasons, Your Honor, if okay lang.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Una, when the second highest official of the land openly and publicly uttered that she had already contracted a person to kill, the highest official of the land, the First Lady and the former Speaker, and that she instructed the person to be relentless in killing them, we
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: failed to see any amount of freedom of speech in that utterance, Your Honor. That's number one. Number two, we talked to ourselves.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If we allow the argument that it is within the bounds of freedom of speech, if we allow that to become the norms of our society, then who would...
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Patayin mo si senador ganito pag itong nangyari. Patayin mo si congressman ganito pag ganito ang nangyari. Patayin mo si justice ganito pag ganito ang nangyari. So imagine, Your Honor, the anarchy, the disorder, and the chaos it would bring to our country. And number three, Your Honor, as a lawyer and being in the law enforcement, freedom of speech Protects lawful expression, but it does not protect utterances that satisfies the elements of a criminal offense. Like this one, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Satisfies the elements of a criminal offense like this one. Ito yung tanong daw, Atty.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Lotto, based
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: on your finding.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Based on your affidavit of investigation, did
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the Vice President commit
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: a crime? Objection,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor. Leading and calls for conclusion of law. Based
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: on his investigation, let the witness answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sustained, but the Presiding Officer will ask the question to the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Based on your investigation, Atty. Lotto, Was there enough basis to file a criminal complaint as you did for the crimes you charged the Vice President with prima facie evidence only? Not as to whether or not she indeed committed it or not because only a court of justice can determine that.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Based on our findings, we believe that... The Vice President committed the crime of grave threats and inciting persecution.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Only insofar as satisfying the requirement of prima facie evidence sufficient to file a case.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Prima facie evidence with reasonable certainty of conviction. Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: that would be a more complete description of what you have to comply with before you can file a case.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Yes, Po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel may proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Let's continue. Atty. Lotoc. Kita magpapadayon. Hinanatod mga pakianang. Hinaimaw pagbaton. Hinanakot mga pakianang.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, may I be allowed to make a manifestation? As I understand, only Filipino and English may be used, because I cannot understand what he was saying. Can we ask that he state his statement in Filipino or English?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, the Filipino language encompasses all the languages and dialects. It includes our very own Waray-Waray.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: But, counsel, the rules state only Filipino and English. I will let it go once in a while, but not each time.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We will submit, Your Honor. Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may proceed, counsel for the prosecutors. Proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Marceau Through the letter said that the vice president was confident in your office's assurance that the alleged threats to her were also being investigated. Malala mo sagot mo yun doon? Yes, Your Honor. Now, what did the NBI do if any on the alleged threats? This time sinasabi niya to her, to the vice president kung meron man.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. We started the investigation on the alleged threat against the life of the Vice President.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You started. So, what was the result? If any, if at all, if you know, to that investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, the fact that we issued a letter dated December 2, 2024, we informed the Vice President that we are investigating on that alleged threat against her life and that we want... Any information that would give us any investigative lead on that matter, Your Honor? Unfortunately, the Vice President did not appear. So wala ho kaming makitang pagsisimulan na imbistigahan.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: May nakita kami sa I think 75 PNP personnel as far as the security of the Vice President is concerned.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If you know, if you know, ilan ba yung natira? Sa Vice Presidential Security and Protection Group, if you know. Pagkatapos ma-remove yung sinasabi mong 75 personnel of that VP-SPG, if you know.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, based on, if I'm not mistaken, based on the record, the COA record, I think more or less 335 security personnel. Kung di ako nagkakamalay, base doon sa...
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 335 personnel protecting a single person, the Vice President? Based on
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: that record, Your Honor. Based on the news, yeah. 335.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Last point, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wind up, Counsel. Yes, Your Honor. Now, Mr. Witness, you mentioned earlier that your office considered in its investigation In the November 23, 2024 online briefing, na aside kay respondent, yung vice-presidente, tsaka yung mga media personalities, okay, na nabanggit mo, sino pa, kung meron pa, yung nandun sa online briefing ngayon, kung alam mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, 'yung pinakaunang part ng video, si Atty. Zuleika Lopez.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Zulaika Lopez. Now, yung tanong, Mr. Witness, ano yung na-observe mo kung meron man, okay, about Atty. Zulaika Lopez during that online media briefing?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Objection vague, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Oh, Your Honor, what's vague? Okay. Witness is smart enough to answer if he knows. Witness may answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Well,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: based on that video, it appears na nagko-complain si Atty. Zulaika. I'm referring doon sa paglipat niya from H.O.R. to women correction facilities, I think. And then yung health issue niya. So parang kinukomplain din niya na yun. At yung nangyari sa kanyang pagka-health in custody sa H.O.R.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: All right. Now, Atty. Lotoc, what significance, if any, do these complaints ni Atty. Lopez have in your investigation on the threats made by the Vice President in that online media briefing?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. We take that into account. Tiningnan namin 'yung sitwasyon, 'yung issue ni Atty. Zuleika. But when we see the bigger picture, taking all the pieces of the puzzle, una, it has nothing to do with the Vice President contracting a person because even before Zuleika Lopez appeared in that video, the Vice President had already contracted a person to kill the President and Liza Marcos and the former Speaker. And when we consider all the facts and circumstances, the instance where Atty. Zuleika was complaining does not diminish, it does not alter, it does not affect the totality of the findings that we have in our investigation, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Senator
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Judge, is counsel for the prosecutors done?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Ligutan, are you done? Yes, sir. You're done? Before cross-examination, Chair would like to recognize, with the permission of Senator Judge J.V., Sen. Judge Bam Aquino had earlier sought recognition. Shea will recognize him first. Thereafter, Sen. Judge Tulfo Irwin. Thereafter, Sen. Judge Ejercito and then Sen. Judge Ontiveros. Sen. Judge Aquino is recognized. You have two minutes, sir.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Yes. Maraming salamat, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Atty. Lotoc, meron pa po bang ibang grupo sa NBI ang nag-imbestiga doon po sa Mga utterances ni Vice President Sara Duterte noong November 23 to 24?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: During our time, insofar as the Cybercrime Division is concerned, yung Cybercrime Division, Your Honor, and the team, that was yung binuo ni former Judge, Director Judge. So kayo lang po? At that time, Sir. Hindi ko na po alam ngayon kung sino yung mga team na, kasi nalipat na po ako sa...
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yung
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: tanong ko po kasi ay nakatukoy dun sa taong nakausap o sinasabing nakontrata ni Vice President Sara Duterte para patayin yung Presidente, First Lady at former Speaker. So tinuloy niyo po ba yung investigasyon para mahanap ang taong ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, aside from the fact, Your Honor, na nag-i-issue kami ng subpoena sa Vice President para makakuha ng information, kasi we need a validated information, we need a confirmed information. Nung in-issue namin ng subpoena yung mga media personalities, bawat isa sa
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: kanila na nag-appear, tinanong din po namin, nandoon ka ba nung sinabi ito ng Vice President? Hindi
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: ko po tinatanong kung
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sinabi ba ito o hindi. Dahil may witness
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: rin po tayo nung nakaraang linggo na nagsabing nasabi nga ito at napanood naman natin po
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: lahat. Ang tanong ko, tinuloy niyo ba yung investigasyon para matukoy ang taong ito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Nagtanong kami, Your Honor, we tried to elicit information both from those people who have personal knowledge during the online press conference.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Unfortunately, wala akong kaming ma-establish na validated information na confirmed. In fact hanggang ngayon nag-aantay po kami. Hindi yung katulad dito sa nangyari may apparent commission of the crime dahil nandiyan yung big U eh. So ang
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: ibig niyo pong sabihin bilang NBI hindi niyo nahanap yung taong ito pero literal niyo itong sabi niyo literal itong pag-assess niyo dun sa statement dahil ito mismo yung nasabi ng Vice President.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, if If the second highest official of the land, sinabi yan, hindi ho biro yan. Medyo mabigat ho yan. At yung pagkasabi pa niya na may kasamang galit at mga pagmumura. We took it very seriously, Honor.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Alright, I have a question for the defense. Sa lahat ng mga sagot ninyo, Atty. Vin Luan, parang hindi ko nakita na tinanggi ng inyong kliyente o ng depensa. Na may nakausap ang vice-presidente na tao para gawin yung mga bagay na ito. Tama ba? Wala ito sa mga sagot ninyo? We deny
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: that, Your Honor.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: You deny?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: That is not accurate, Your Honor, and we will present evidence or counter-evidence. Okay,
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: so let me clarify. Sa lahat ng sagot ninyo so far, hindi pa ninyo tinatanggi ito, pero in your time presenting evidence, you will deny?
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Ang nabanggit doon ay freedom of expression. Was there an exact statement there na hindi totoo?
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: We
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: maintain our position that we denied it, Your Honor. It is there in our answer.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: General denial and there were also specific denials.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Okay. We'll take a look, Mr. Presiding Officer. Hanapin natin ito. And if I may come back to this once we take a look at the records, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The gentleman may do so at the appropriate time. With the permission of Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo, since nakatayo na po si Senator Judge Ejercito, ang papaunahin ko ng bumuna siya. Senator Judge Tulfo, rather Ejercito is recognized. You have two minutes, sir.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: May we know if the NBI has the authority to issue subpoena against impeachable officials? Kasi kanina po sa mga pinresent kanina, subpoena po ang inyong pinadala sa Vice President instead of a mere invitation. Yan lang po. Clarify ko lang po.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Under Republic Act 10867, the NBI has authority to issue subpoena. As a matter of fact, the case involving the Vice President falls under Section 5, Paragraph G, which the NBI has primary jurisdiction to undertake investigation, Your Honor.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Likewise, for the information, may we know what constitutes a grave threat that will prompt the NBI to conduct an investigation as compared to a light threat? What are the elements that are needed to be present to be considered a grave threat.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, for grave threat, Your Honor, if naalala ko siya, if a person threatens another person with the infliction upon the latter's person, property, or honor, or that of the latter's family with a wrong Atty. Giorgio R. Or
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: with any wrong, amounting to a crime, if that threat is with condition or without condition or with monetary consideration, yun po yung kabuan sa grave threat.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: May kondisyon? Or walang kondisyon?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The crime of grave threat, Your Honor, can be committed with or without condition. With or without
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: condition.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: So as an investigator, have you ever investigated and filed a complaint for grave threats apart from this one? Again, Your Honor? As an investigator, have you filed any case or investigated and filed a case for grave threats against anyone aside from this one, excluding this one?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: think me, nag-start po kasi ako as counter-terrorism and then organized crime group and then cybercrime.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala akong maalala, Your Honor, kundi ito lang. I mean, so far as my being in the NBI is concerned, Your Honor.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Ah, so ito lamang yung ano, ito pala yung kaso na naimbestigahan niyo concerning greed threats, yun o?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think yung iba, may mga na-investigahan, Your Honor. Pero again, sabi ko, yung sa sarili ko po, yung experience ko from counter-terrorism hanggang sa Organized Transnational Crime Group hanggang sa Cybercrime Division, ang naalala ko lang, Your Honor, kasi matagal na ho yun eh, kung ano yung nasa record, I think itong great threats na to is, pag hindi first time, Atty. Dung ko lang na-experience.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Gano'ng katagal kayong parte nitong Cybercrime Division? Bukay na
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: lipat? Since 2018, Your Honor. Nagsimula ako bilang Investigation Agent. And then 2022, I was designated as Chief of the Digital Forensic Laboratory Division. And then 2023, designated as Chief of the Cybercrime Division, Sir.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: So, more than five years kayong nandito sa Cybercrime Division ng NBA? Opo. That's all, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator Judge Erick Soto. Senator Judge Tulfo Irwin is recognized. You have two minutes, sir. You may proceed when you're ready.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Thank you, Mr. President or Presiding Officer. I'd like to direct my clarificatory question to the witness on the stand, Mr. Presiding Officer. Atty. Jeremy Lontoc, What findings, if any, convince the NBI the motive of the respondent to kill the President and two other people? Meron pong bang kayong nakitang motibo? Kasi maaari pong sabihin lang nung isang tao sa sobrang galit niya. Napag-usapan na po kanina yan, di ba? Spur of the moment. Pero did you find any motive? Bakit niya po gagawing patayin ang Pangulo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. As I've said before, when we take into consideration all the facts and circumstances surrounding that issue, nagkaroon ng hindi magandang relasyon yung dalawa.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Nagbato na ang vicepresidente ng mga salitang mabibigat laban sa presidente.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Pinapakita doon sa October 18 na toxic na nga yung relationship nila. Galit na galit si Sarah dahil sinasabi ng vicepresidente is politically motivated yung pag-attack sa kanya. And then at the same time, pinagtutulungan siya ng buong gobyerno. So, then na-trigger ho yun, if my memory serves me right, nung incident nangyari noong 23 November 2024.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So parang nagpatong-patong na siya, convolution ng iba't ibang issue. So nakita ho namin, talagang galit ang Vice President sa Presidente.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Okay, so you saw that the Vice President is very angry, right? Galit po siya. Did the investigation uncover any evidence that the respondent had taken steps to carry out these threats or these statements that she made in public and online? Did you have or did you uncover any evidence?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, insofar as the Cybercrime Division is concerned, we focused on the investigation on the alleged grave threats and inciting to sedition. Ngayon, pagdating doon whether or not merong na-execute na o may inutusan, I think ang makakasagot po niyan, Your Honor, 'yung aming Director, kasi sa kanya po 'yung pool ng information. But at the same time, 'yung jurisdiction na 'yan, nasa Intelligence Service po namin. Kami ho, nasa Investigation Service. So insofar as the NBI Cybercrime Division is concerned at that time, naka-focus po kami sa grave threats and inciting to sedition. But insofar as whether meron na bang in-engage ang Vice President, jurisdiction ho 'yan ng aming Intelligence Service, and maybe ang makakasagot niyan 'yung aming Director kasi siya po 'yung—
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: answer that because he is the recipient of a pool of information from different—
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: mean inciting to sedition will be answered by the director, is that correct? Kasi parang hindi po natalakay kanina in inciting to sedition, is it?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, inciting to sedition, in our investigation, we were able to establish that those utterances from 18 October 2024, November 23, 2024, and other facts and circumstances, even the November 26, 2024, we believed that those utterances have a tendency, Your Honor, to stir up the people, to go against the government, to disturb the peace of the community, and to undermine public safety and public order. I think those are the elements of inciting to sedition, Your Honor.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: I have two questions, Mr. Presiding Officer. So you're saying they're intertwined: killing the President and then inciting the people to revolt against the government? They're intertwined, is that what you're saying?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on our findings.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Based on your findings.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: What could be the motive of the vice president inciting people to sedition, to revolt against the government, when in fact she will be the next president of the republic? She's been saying and everybody knows and she's been claiming. Why do you think? Did you look deeper? Why incite to sedition?
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: In fact, you're the vice president. Usually, in our country, usually, Mr. Witness, the vice president would run for presidency. What could be the motive?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, what we have established is the fact that the relationship between the two were already hostile. And what we established is the fact that the vice president has committed great threats and inciting to sedition.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That is our focus, Your Honor. Insofar as the deeper motive, I have
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: no personal knowledge. All
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: right. Well, I'm running out of time. Can you identify the strongest piece of evidence which you relied in deciding to file these cases before the Department of Justice? And what is the status of this case, Mr. Witness?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, the piece of evidence that we attached or we incorporated in our investigation is sufficient and has satisfied the requirements of the quantum of evidence required which is prima facie evidence. With reasonable certainty of conviction, and the fact, Your Honor, that the Department of Justice has issued certification stating that your referral, your transmittal, has complied all the elements of the crime charge and therefore good for preliminary investigation.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: What is the status of the case, Mr. Witness? It's ongoing, Your Honor,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: if I remember correctly. It's ongoing, Your Honor.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: One very, very quick question, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Do you
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: think at this point you have an airtight case against the respondent? I
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: believe so, yes, Your Honor. Otherwise, the Department of Justice would not issue a certification stating to the effect na kompleto ang elements namin, na nakuha namin yung requirement, at ready na siya for preliminary investigation.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Thank you, Mr. Witness. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator Judge Tulfo. Senator Judge Ontiveros, Senator Judge Villanueva, and thereafter, we pause for a 10-minute break.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may proceed, ma'am. You have two minutes.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Atty. Lotoc?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: In the affidavit of investigation dated February 10, 2025, the NBI recommended that grave threats and inciting to sedition be filed against
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: the vice president. Could it be due to those cases that were just brought out of emotion or there was an intense trigger that led to that?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't think, Your Honor, kasi wala naman sa elements ng grave threats yung situation na iyon.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As long as we were able to satisfy the elements for grave threats, Your Honor, and when the Department of Justice certifies na kumpleto yung elemento doon,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. Hindi ho yan mag-matter dun sa findings namin.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: At yung sinabi po ninyong elements of grave threats, yun po yung apat na inanumerate nyo kanina. Ano pong elements of grave threats?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Number one, that a person threatened to inflict another person.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: On the latter's person, owner of property, or that of the latter's family with any wrong. That's the first element. The second element, that wrong amounts to a crime. Then the third element is my demand for money or my condition in imposed.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: In our investigation, mayroon hong tatlong acts para makumit yung great threats. Base doon sa tatlong elements na sinabi ko, the offender have complied with the threat na sinabi niya, the offender hindi niya na comply yung threat na sinabi niya or yung pangatlong act, yung walang condition yung threat na yon.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Two times you mentioned the word condition, Atty. Lotoc. I will ask that later. In DOJ, there is a criteria of reasonable certainty of conviction before filing a case. Yes, Atty. In NBI, what is the procedure you follow before recommending a case?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, sinusunog din ho namin yung quantum of evidence na prima facie evidence with reasonable certainty of conviction. Kaya ho, kung makikita niyo yung yung pong aming processes o yung phases, yung pang last po niya is legal evaluation. Meaning, pag meron na ho kaming conclusion bago ho namin ito i-submit sa Department of Justice, We have
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: a referral from the legal division. We are helping our legal experts. They are the ones evaluating. They will qualify if the requirements are satisfied
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: and if they can be submitted to the Department of Justice for purposes of preliminary investigation, ma'am.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Thank you, Atty. No matter how you approximate it.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor. And that is on the basis of our cherished principle, the two-pillar rule in investigation, thoroughness and legality, Your Honor.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: All right. Salamat po.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Eto, in principle, kailangan po ba ng patunay na may Kinoontratang asasin para maituring na grave threats ang mga sinabi.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, in so far as the crime of grave threat is concerned, hindi po iyon kailangan.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Alright.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Speaking of condition, kanina na binanggit niyo dalawang beses. Posible po ba ang grave threats kahit may kondisyon ang banta? Ibig sabihin yung kapag ito nangyari sa akin, ito ay mga gawin mo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Very
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: much possible, Your Honor. As I have said, grave threats can be committed with or without condition. As a matter of fact, meron akong naalala ng isang case, SPO2 Jamaica versus Atty. Bangot. Ang sabi huto ni SPO2 Jamaica, if I lose my job, I will break your head or I will So it's for us, it's a kind of event-based condition na matitrigger yung execution and threat pag nangyayari yung event. But then when the Supreme Court decide, nag-decided Supreme Court, ito sabi niya, the threat was absolute. So it's
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: absolute
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: yung threat, you know, hindi conditional. So parang ganito akin sa situation dito, meron siyang sort of event-based condition. If the event happens, the offender will now be
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: triggered by the threat that was uttered by the offender, Your Honor. So,
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: we can say that there is jurisprudence because you can see a correlation in the case of the rule of SC-90PO-2-Jamaca and the case
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: of
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: the Vice President. Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Alright. Last question, Atty. Lotoc. As an attorney, as a general rule, when can we say that freedom of speech
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: is beyond free speech and becomes a grave threat or inciting to sedition?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, we consider the two tests. Number one, I'm not
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: a big cash owner, but it's like
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If I may, Your Honor, just to refer my notes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Kindly turn on the mic. Witness may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: so. Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We consider, Your Honor, the clear and present danger rule and the dangerous tendency rule. But among the two, the dangerous tendency rule, meaning if If the speech would have a tendency to create chaos or to create illegal acts, then that should be restricted. Pag may tendency ho na magiging ganon ang resulta.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: So, huli po, Atty., masasabing bang may parang spectrum? Pwedeng nagsisimula?
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Thank you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: noted and entered into the records senator judge Villanueva you may have you have two minutes sir you may proceed thank
Sen. Joel Villanueva: you president presiding officer uh just a few questions to our uh witness Mr. Witness, it's been mentioned several times the importance of your investigation that it falls under yung prima facie evidence with reasonable certainty of conviction. And nabanggit niyo po na fulfill po lahat yan, no? Kaya siguro nagkaroon ng first report at second report. Is that correct? Yes, Your Honor. And can you just for the record give us an idea? Ano yung mga boxes that you have to fill in para pumasok po dito?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You mean, Your Honor, the comment of the Department of Justice? Yes,
Sen. Joel Villanueva: to make it clear that it indeed goes into the Frimafaci evidence with reasonable certainty of conviction.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, basically, Your Honor, the requirements that the DOJ gave from our point of view were administrative.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi ho 'yon 'yung sustansya noong aming affidavit, kasi hindi ho namin binago 'yung affidavit namin. 'Yun pa rin ho 'yon, eh. Ang nakita ho ng DOJ doon, 'yung affidavit of, I think, authentication na kailangan i-attach doon, and others, 'yung TSN, affidavit of transcription. This is, from our point of view, to satisfy the requirements of admissibility. So
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: it
Sen. Joel Villanueva: didn't change despite of your fourth stage, the legal evaluation. In that stage of legal evaluation, was it considered, Mr. Witness, what the Vice President mentioned and even some of the defense panel, that it is actually a conditional threat and it appears that the Vice President during the presentation of the video
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Insofar as the threat against the life of the Vice President, the very reason why we issued a subpoena and sent a letter was for us to have the chance to talk to the Vice President and elicit some information.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: But you think—
Sen. Joel Villanueva: it is important if it is a conditional threat It is also important to look at this aspect.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor, I think
Sen. Joel Villanueva: so. Thank you.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Mr. Witness, I would
Sen. Joel Villanueva: like to understand the standard used by the National Bureau of Investigation. If the so-called assassin is not
Sen. Joel Villanueva: identified or located, does that automatically mean that the threat is no longer credible or actionable? Or... Does the NBI still consider the statements uttered and the surrounding circumstances and the totality of the evidence before deciding to proceed with further investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. The threat was absolute. We followed the test of mens rea, Your Honor, in considering whether the threat is true.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We examine the utterances objectively and we interpret the same in light of the circumstances where the utterances was made, the manner in which they were spoken, the person to whom they were addressed, the relationship between the parties and the reactions of the recipients of those utterances, Your Honor.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Yes, thank you, Mr. Witness. I have here with me, yung binanggit po niyo sa notes ko, yung four stages, identification, and pag-preserve yung digital evidence, collection of evidence, analysis and attribution, legal evaluation, and then you have the three statements. Binanggit niyo rin, tanggalin ulo niya, toxic relationship, and I always see myself cutting his head. Now you also mentioned the factors considered, delivery manner, literal meaning, nature of the instruction, relationship of the parties, and last but not the least, yung utterances na binanggit niyo doon sa October 18 and November 20. Last question, Director Luntok. Bukod po doon sa authentication ng recordings, maaari niyo po ba sa amin ipaliwanag yung What were the NBI's actions
Sen. Joel Villanueva: in assessing the statements of the respondents? For example, you mentioned the different things that happened here because the statement you
Sen. Joel Villanueva: mentioned in the video is no other than our Vice President. So did her position? Her access or authority is affected by how your investigation was conducted.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. As I have said a while ago during the direct examination, in the analysis phase, we considered the intent, the capability, and the motive, Your Honor. The fact that she is the second highest official of the land, And definitely she's capable of doing so. And then there is that motive in the sense na may mga issues na sila. Galit na ang vice-presidente. Din na-trigger dito sa November 23.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: And you would say it's not the usual? The usual. It's
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: not the usual.
Sen. Joel Villanueva: Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Ruiz. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, Senator Judge Villanueva. We will be pausing for a break, Senator Ban.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: What is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the pleasure of Senator Judge Aquino?
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: No, just a point of order, Mr. Presiding Officer. May we tackle this after the break if they have identified it in their pleading?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: This is in relation to your question earlier. After the others shall have been able to speak, Senator Judge Aquino, we shall be pausing for a break for 15 minutes. We shall resume.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: On
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: 459,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: we shall resume at 5 p.m. When we resume, we shall recognize Senator Judge Tulfo, Senate President Gachal Yan, and thereafter, Senator Judge Cayetano and Marcos.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The trial is resumed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator Judge Tulfo Rafi is recognized for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: his intervention.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You have two minutes, sir. You may proceed when you're ready.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May we ask the clerk of court the location of the witness? Where is the witness?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly situate the witness at the witness stand.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Henceforth, the clerk of court is directed to kindly make sure.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That if a time is given by the Presiding Officer that the witness will already be at the witness stand by that time.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sergeant at Arms is directed to be more mindful in so far as the time of the court is concerned in bringing the witness back to the witness stand whenever we go on recess. Attorney Locke, you shall be under the same oath. You may sit down. Thank you, Your Honor. Senator Judge Tulfo, you may proceed.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Mr. Witness, do you consider yourself as an expert when it comes to threat assessment?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Threat assessment, Your Honor?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: An experienced investigator, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: There's a difference between an investigator as opposed to threat assessor. Somebody who assesses a threat. Being given against a person or individual, kasama dyan halimbawa mag-imbestiga ka, tatanong ko sa mga testigo, tatanong ko sa mga taong nakarinig tungkol doon sa banta, titignan mo yung security detail niya, saan siya nakatira, etc., etc.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Just an experienced investigator, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: As an experienced investigator. So sa ginawa mong pag-imbestiga whether or not merong real or imminent threat against the Vice President, Um, sino-sino po yung mga naimbita nyo at na-interview?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Um, yung media personalities po, your honor. From late Saidin Reyes to Bones Magsambol to others. Lahat po sila tinanong namin kung kilala nila yung kinausap ni VP Sara, yung tao na kinontrata.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Did
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: you also invite Princess Maui, yung influencer na nagtanong kay VP Sara during that online press conference?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I believe so, Your Honor. I asked the executive officers back then at ang sabi nila sakin hindi ho nag-appear chief. So you
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: invited her pero she failed to appear?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor, yun po yung report sa akin ng ating mga Executive Officers.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Okay, so masasabi niyo ba na talagang merong imminent threat, real and imminent threat against the life of the Vice President based on the investigation you conducted?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Against the life of the Vice President, Sir?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Yes. Vice President. Kasi siyempre, pag nag-iimbestigat doon sa Presidente, dapat imbistigan mo rin yung threat against the Vice President para patas.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes po. Precisely, the reason po, Your Honor, kung bakit ho namin inimbitahan ang Vice Presidente, may separate ho kami na sulat noong December 2. Ininform po namin siya na, Ma'am, iniimbestigahan din ho namin 'yung alleged threat against sa life mo, at para ho ma-expedite ito, bigyan ninyo po kami ng any information na puwedeng maging lead doon sa investigation namin. Unfortunately, wala ho kaming natanggap na information. Hindi naman po kasi nag-appear ang Vice President, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Pero nagpadala ba siya ng representative to represent her doon sa subpoena ninyo na pinadala sa kanya?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Nagpadala siya po ng representative and then with a letter, sir. In fact, dalawang beses po 'yung letter na 'yon. 'Yung unang letter niya, ang sabi niya hindi siya maka-attend kasi nga meron siyang office matters to attend to.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Yeah, yeah. Sorry to cut you off. Napakinggan na natin 'yan para mapaiksi tayo. So sino 'yung representative na pinadala niya, at ano ang napag-usapan ng NBI investigator at saka noong representative?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think it's Attorney Paul Lawrence Lim, if I'm not mistaken.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: one who talked to him, Your Honor, was the former Director Jaime B. Sanchalos. What was
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: discussed during that meeting? Between Atty. Lawrence
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Lim
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: and the people from the NBI, particularly the investigators investigating the threat against the Vice President.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 6 years ago may threat ang vice-presidente so hopefully confident ang vice-presidente na iimbestighan nyo rin yung issue na yon. So
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: 6 years ago pero hindi nyo ba nasabi?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 6 years, 6 months. 6 months nga tayo. 5 to 6 months. Alright.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: So
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sinabi nung
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: representative ni VP Sara na 6 months ago there was a threat against the life of the vice-president.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yun po yung nasa letter. Okay.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Inusisan nyo ba kung ano yung threat na pinagsasabi niya?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We conducted, Your Honor, an open source. We did not validate, aside from the removal of 75 personnel, security personnel from BPSPG and then transferred to Manila.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, insofar as Cybercrime Division is concerned, pero hindi ko po alam baka yung Intelligence Service namin meron o kaya yung Director may alam.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Last na lamang, Mr. Witness. Kasi sabi mo, ulitin ko dun sa six months ago, naka-receive ng threat against Black, ang BP. Sabi mo kanina, sabi ng abogado, right? So, kasi kuha ko sayo, if I was the investigator, I would say, okay, ano yung threat six months ago? Pwede ka bang magpakita ng mga ebedensya? Pwede ka bang makita ng proof or mga witnesses na pwede na ma-interviewin to that effect?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, ang nag-usap po, Your Honor, si the then Director Judge Jaime Vicente Agua at saka yung lawyers, Your Honor.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: So, okay. Last na naman po. Now, can you say in certainty na talagang wala o meron threat against the life of the Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: your investigation, based on your experience.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, given that we don't have
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: validated information that confirmed any data, I will not comment, Your Honor. I need that. Thank
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: you, Mr. Witness. Thank you. Thank
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you, Senator Judge
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Rafi
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tulfo, Senate President Gatchalian, thereafter, Senator Judge Alan Cayetano, thereafter, Senator Judge Aimee Marcos. You may proceed,
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Senate President. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Mr. Witness, I heard earlier when you were being
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: questioned by the prosecution that the statements of Atty. Zolaica Lopez have nothing to do with the threat made by the Vice President. Is that correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Kinonsider namin siya doon sa totality ng aming investigation. Then nakita namin na even before noong situation ni Atty. Zuleika, base doon sa utterances ng Vice President, meron na ho siyang kinausap.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: So 'yan ang next na tanong ko. Ibig n'yo ba sabihin na even prior to this video, meron na siyang nakausap na kinontrata?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's the utterance, Your Honor. Ang sabi niya, 'Huwag kang mag-alala sapagkat may kinausap na akong tao.' Ang sabi ko sa kanya, 'Pag namatay ako—'
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Based on his statements, based on your analysis,
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, and we believe that the Vice President will not lie
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: because he is very
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: angry.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: You said that over the course of the questions.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Threat is actionable. I don't remember, Your Honor, using the word threat. Actionable threat.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Threat is actual, sorry. Threat is actual. So, I take this to mean that he really
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: has someone to talk to.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's what we believe, Your Honor.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: And if that's what you believe, because this is a warning to our President,
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Did the NBI investigate if there really was a contract for this land?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, I think a couple of months ago, our director submitted
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: something.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: He formed a task force to investigate threats against… The life of the president. Kaya lang hindi na ako part nun, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: July 2025, nalipad na ako sa ibang region. So wala na po akong idea. I think yung intelligence service namin at yung director, yun ho yung pwedeng makasagot, Your Honor. Actually,
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: yun ang next na tanong ko dahil tayo dito sa ating bansa, sanay tayo sa whole of government approach, whole of nation approach.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: In this case, the NBI.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I believe so, Your Honor. The fact na mayroong binuong special task force.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: At kasali kayo doon?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi po ako kasali.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Bakit hindi kayo kasali doon? Ako nagtataka. Dahil kung banta ito sa buhay ng ating Pangulo at nanggaling sa opisina ninyo 'yung source, dapat kasali kayo.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You mean, Your Honor, since nasa regional office ako, noong nagbuo ng task force, definitely ita-tap nila 'yung mga regional offices. Meron ba diyan sa region ninyo na information or intelligence na ganito? Meron hong ganoong practice, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I can't answer that, Your Honor. Our intelligence service is in their forties. And our director. And
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: was there
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: a coordination? Because this is the President, no less than our President. Was there
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: a coordination between you and the task force of the NBI, along with the NSE, the PSG, and other national agencies? Is this our
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: president? Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Did
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Did you or the task force do that?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, insofar as the cybercrime division during that time, our focus is the investigation on the threat against the life vis-a-vis the November 23, 2024 utterances. Now, insofar as you're saying, Your Honor, the answer to
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: that is our intelligence service because that's what
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: it is. It's like a deep-dive intelligence gathering.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: My only point
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: is, on this very important topic, I expect the NBI to have a whole-of-agency approach because you came from there.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The memo issued
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: by the Director created a task force, and the task force is being tapped by all the regional offices. Anong information meron kayo dito sa Central Office?
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Anong resulta nun? Last question, Mr.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Presiding Officer. In so far as the NBI-BARM is concerned, yung hawak ko pong region, meron kaming ongoing investigation pero hindi ho related doon sa kausap ni Zara. Meron kaming giniinvestigahan na nag-threaten sa Presidente sa matter of fact na-identify namin.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: On going pa siya, nagaantay lang kami ng order galing sa taas kung ano yung guidance. Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, Mr. President. Thank you, Mr. Senate President. Noted and entered in the records, Senator Judge Alan Gaetano is recognized. You have two minutes, sir. Mr.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: President, susundan ko na yung kay Senator Wynne, Senate President.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Yes, Your Honor. Good afternoon, Mr. Wynne. So, de-derecho yung ko na. So, what we're trying to figure out here kasi is are you really Are you investigating
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: whether there's a threat to VP Sara and whether she threatened the individuals mentioned, including the president? Or are you only investigating the video and finding if there's a crime? So I asked Agent John Mark Calilum. He said he wasn't talking
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: to PSG. I said PSG but they're now
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: PSC, right?
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: So, did you speak to the Presidential Security Command about the threat on the President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, in terms of correspondence between the Presidential Security Command and the NBI, the Director will
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: be able to answer that. I don't know if they have
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: anything to
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: talk about. We have a so-called need-to-know basis. Our focus is— The
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: problem with your answers, Witness, is that if that's your answer, you didn't investigate it properly. Because you didn't get the information from your intelligence. You did not get your information from the task force. You did not get your information from the Presidential Security Group. Did you talk to the CIDG? May you answer first. Did you talk to the CIDG? No, Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor. But
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: they also investigated, right?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so, Your Honor, because they have a
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: statement.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: So that is also the question of the Senate President. If you really investigated the whole thing and you are the head and you should investigate, Why don't you talk to the other investigators? Maybe they know that you don't.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It's a matter of intelligence. I don't know if they can
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: talk or if they don't talk with the Director or with the Intelligence
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Service. I'll take that answer but I think at least you know what's on our minds and what we want clarified. Secondly, sir, all of you, the four of you signed the February 10, February 2025
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: NBI Affidavit of Investigation. Tama po ba? Di ba?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Our Affidavit
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: of Investigation. Tapos
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: kasama
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: dito
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: yung verification n'yo. Basically saying that based on the records, tama tong lahat.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Verification ng ano po, Your Honor? Sa dulo, nag-sign kayo ng verification. Verification of non-forum shopping, Your Honor? Yes. And
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: that, aside from non-forum shopping, give me some latitude because to explain the question. We read and understood its contents, and the allegations therein are true based on authentic records. Yes, Your Honor. So may mali ba dito factually? Wala. Na-review mo naman to, no?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: May konting typo dyan, which is normal naman.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi typo. Factual.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Insofar as I'm concerned, lahat po
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: ba nag
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: -prepare?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Team po. Ang team po namin with the— Tapos pinapirma sa inyo. We helped to draft an affidavit of investigation on our legal basis and then we agree and we concluded that this is it. Then
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: someone typed it up, then you signed. I asked this because when I asked Agent Mark John Calium, he said it's conditional but he thinks it's absolute. You answered the same thing, it's absolute but it's conditional.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The utterances itself, Your Honor, is what we call event-based condition. That is our
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: classification. That is the utterances, Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: I'll take that answer. I think that is more
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: factual. But in paragraph 51,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: was VP Duterte ever Secretary of the Department of Justice?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. Department of Education. Nakalagay
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: dito, to recall, VP Duterte resigned as the Secretary of the Department of Justice and she herself admitted that her relationship with the President has become toxic and she would imagine her strangling him and cutting off her head. That's typo, Your Honor. That's not a typo. A typo means yung department naging depart. Department of Justice and Department of Education are two different things. Ang
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: alam namin. Yes, sir. Department of Education.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: I just filed my counter affidavit sa ombudsman about the obstruction of justice. Ilang beses ko kailangan basahin. Kasi nga, pag may mali, pinirmahan niyo na sinasabi niyo. But anyway, going back to the condition, you mentioned the case of SPO2 Hamata. Yes, sir. But isn't it true that the Liz Mota of that case was really res judicata and double jeopardy? The Supreme Court did not take up
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: whether or not a condition. Yes, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Right? Yes.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: So that wasn't on point because I was going to ask, is there a difference if the condition is legal or illegal? For example, if I told you, if I get removed as Senate President, I will also remove
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: you. Okay. First of all, I will be legally removed as Senate President. We always vote. There's nothing there. But if illegal, or if you kill me, I will also kill
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: you. Is there a difference if the condition of why I will act or why I'm threatening you is an illegal act?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, under the law, Your Honor, it says there that even the condition is unlawful. So, regardless of the nature of the condition.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: want to get into your mind when you sign this because this case is a bit
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: noble for me. Even as a lawyer, I have to do more research and see what these grave threats mean. Because you keep mentioning, we keep mentioning here that this is the second The highest official in the land. And therefore, if the president is a
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: trinite. But who was the vice president claiming that he could kill him?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, Your Honor, that is the reason why we issued a subpoena. In your
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: reading of his statement, who is the
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: president referring to
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: as the person
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: who will operate Operation Romanoid? Who is he
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: trying to
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: sell?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, first, if we're talking about Romanov, Your Honor, we know that the first person Romanov killed was Mayor Baste, I think, in January 2024. Yes,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: that's irrelevant. My question is, in the mind of the Vice President, who is he
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: trying to
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: convince to kill him? You said you investigated, so your testimony is long.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Agent John Mark. So, of course, kasama sa investigation ninyo, sino sa mind ni Vice President ang magpapapatay sa kanya?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, again, Your Honor, since wala kaming makuhang valid information, Ano,
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: hindi ba klaro sa video na ang pinagbibintangan niya is the First Lady, the President, and the Speaker of the House? Sabi niya, pag pinatay ako, patayin mo silang tatlo. So ang pinagbibintangan niya na magpapapatay sa kanya, yung tatlo.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I cannot answer to that, Your Honor. Senator Judge Allan kindly wind
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: up. But you have to be able to answer that because you're the one who investigated. And that is crucial. Why? Because part of your self-defense, so for example, if I know, nasa sa senator judge, pag hindi ako bumoto one way or the other, papapatayin ako ng batik. Whatever, chief PNP or papapatay ako ng whoever. So pag sinabi kong, pag ako pinatay, si ganito nagpapatay sa akin.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: And then ang difference, I don't usually give a threat na patayin mo rin. So could it be that actually that was the defense of the vice president? Para hindi siya patayin.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't know the state of the... But
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: you've testified all throughout this afternoon that you went into her state Based
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: on the series of events, Your Honor.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Yes, and based on her statement. And the series of events is nag-away sila ng administrasyon. And the series of events is that sinasabi niya. Pag ako'y pinatay, eto tatlo ang papatayin niyo. Okay, last question. Kay Atty. Lopez, tinanong din to ng Sen.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Tulfo. At di ko na itatanong pero napahapyawan ni Sen. Erwin din to yung… Tungkol kayo, yung sinabi ni Atty.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Lopez, sabi mo, even before kasi nangyari yun, nakausap na ni Vice President yung papatay.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's the literal meaning of the statement. Yes, that's the
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: literal meaning, but did you believe her? Well, she's the Vice President, sir. So
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: she also said freedom of expression, so you also believe her?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Not based on the evidence that what we gathered, sir.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Okay, so I'll stop there, but I'll read to you. Sinabi niyo kasi sedition. Pero tignan niyo po yung page 25 nung sarili niyong affidavit. Si Princess Maui ang sinabi niya, ano po ba ang pwede niyong maging remedy para matapos na ito? Lalot nagsisigaw na po ang taong bayan na mag-people power na. So actually, I would consider ang naguudyok si Princess Maui. Of course, we can discuss people power but... Pero tignan niyo po ang sagot niya after yung sa pagpatay. Ang laban ay wala dyan sa EDSA, ma'am. Wala dyan sa mga highway. Ang laban, ma'am, nandun sa loob ng palasyo. Yan ang problema. We appreciate yung expression niyo ng discuss, ang pagkamuhi, ang hopelessness kasi it reflects kung ano nararamdaman ng maraming milyon-milyon. Alam ko yan, ma'am.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: So if I look at that statement, parang baliktad. Parang sinasabi niyang huwag kayo mag-people power.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Actually, kung babasahin po natin 'yung buo, may sinabi siya doon na natutuwa siya sa ginagawa nila. [unclear]
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We based everything on the evidence that we've gathered. Thank you, Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Mr. Witness. Thank you, Senator-Judge Alan Cayetano. Senator-Judge Marcos, thereafter Senator-Judge Aquino. Senator Marcos, you may proceed, ma'am, when you're ready.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Thank you very much, Presiding Officer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Opo, ma'am.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Okay, I'd like to affirm lang yung sinabi mo kanina na noon nangyari nga itong hating gabi na interview ni Vice President sa Zoom, agad-agad inorderan kayo, inonstructionan ang NBI na…
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think between 12 noon and 1 p.m. And then mayroong instruction na nanggaling kay Director Santiago: 'Jeremy, may kumakalat sa social media. May mga utterances na ginawa ang Vice Presidente. Imbestigahan natin since may cyber aspect ito. Imbestigahan mo na.' Doon po nagsimula 'yon.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Tama. So anong araw 'yon? Kasi andito sa inyong affidavit of investigation at 'yung sinabi ninyo na 'on even date.' Ang tinutukoy mo ba 'yung November 23 din?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: November 23, ma'am, kasi natapos ho ang—
Sen. Imee Marcos: Oo, gabing-gabi kasi 'yon, di ba?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Madaling-araw po, nang ala-una, ma'am.
Sen. Imee Marcos: That's right. So nag-meeting kayo kaagad-agad? Ganoon ba?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi, ma'am. Hindi po kasi namin alam 'yon.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Kailan kayo inutusan na mag-imbestiga?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Noong during noong lunchtime, noong may meeting kami ni then-Director Santiago, pero iba ho ang iniimbestigahan namin, [unclear].
Sen. Imee Marcos: Kailan kayo sinabihan ng DOJ na mag-imbestiga? Anong araw po?
Sen. Imee Marcos: 23. Pareho lang. Yun ang sinabi ninyo kanina nung tinatanong kayo ng council ng prosecution. Yan din ang nakasaad. On even date ang nakasabi sa inyong abinabit.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, ma'am.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Okay. So, nag-umpisa na kayo. Kunento nga ninyo. Four-phase yung investigasyon. Nag-umpisa sa identification. Nagbigay kayo ng hash value. Nag-preserve kayo ng data.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Nag-research at natuklasan ninyo na meron palang October 18 video na press conference na naman ni OVP na nasa Facebook, at may mga sinasabi na naman na puputulin 'yung ulo. Tama ba 'yon? 'Yung October 18 ang nakita ninyo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's the continuation in the analysis phase, Your Honor.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Yes, Your Honor. Kasi nag-research na kayo bilang fourth phase nga ng inyong imbestigasyon. Tama po ba?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi po, Your Honor. 'Yun 'yung third phase po, 'yung analysis and attribution.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Pa-attribution. So third phase. Pero bandang huli na. Ang pinagtatakahan ko, kung inutusan kayo noong November 23 na magkaroon ng imbestigasyon, bakit napakaaga? November 6, 2024, a subpoena was issued to ABS-CBN requiring them to submit an authenticated copy of the video pertaining to the 18 October press conference. Nandito ito sa affidavit ninyo, nasa page 8, number 14. Kung inutusan kayo noong November 23, ang ibig ba sabihin, November 6 pa lang, minamanmanan na si Vice President?
Sen. Imee Marcos: Iniimbestigahan na siya bago pa 'yung Zoom conference sa Kongreso?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. I believe that's a typo, 'yung date.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Sorry?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: That's a typo, Your Honor, 'yung date. Kasi makikita doon 'yung date noong appearance ng taga-ABS-CBN, which is consistent ho siya doon sa ibang inisyuhan ng subpoena.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Kaya ba yung
Sen. Imee Marcos: appearance? Kasi hindi ko nasusundan yung timeline ninyo eh. Parang ah, yung November 23 yung utos, pero November 6 pa lamang, may sabpina na. Patag
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: ka
Sen. Imee Marcos: ganun?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Taypo ho yan, Your Honor. Hindi ho yan November 6. Taypo na naman,
Sen. Imee Marcos: katulad ng Department of Justice.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, Your Honor. If I may refer to my notes, Your Honor.
Sen. Imee Marcos: O-o, pakita mo na lang sa akin kasi nahanap ko hindi ko masundan eh. This is page 6, number 14 po. November 6, 2024, subpoena to ABS-CBN.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Wala naman yatang date na binibigay tungkol sa appearance ni Patria Morales at yung iba pang
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: kaya ABS.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Paki-turo
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: lang kasi hinahanap po namin.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: For
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: information,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the time of Senator Judge Marcos is over. Kindly.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Yes, but he's still responding to the same question, if you will allow.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Siya po yung makagaling, di tayo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We're only counting the questions that you asked, not the answer. Neither are we counting the waiting time for the witness to answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I check ko lang po, Your Honor. Kasi
Sen. Imee Marcos: yung mga sumunod na meeting doon sa page 13, sa number 30 at sa mga sumunod, yung mga tinutukoy doon, yung mga media na nandun sa Zoom conference. Hindi naman siya yung ABS na humawak ng camera noong October 18. Iba naman yung mga tinutukoy doon eh.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lutok, the question of the Hon. Marcos is on page 6, paragraph 14. You said you sent a subpoena on November 6, 2024.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Unfortunately, because the annexes are not part of the document marked, it's not here. So, the question is quite clear. If it's a mistake, then what is the correct date of the subpoena? If I can see the real subpoena, Your Honor. Kindly talk to the mic, please. If
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I can see the real subpoena, Your Honor, because the subpoena was signed by our assistant director.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As I said,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: unfortunately, it was not attached to your affidavit and I doubt if it's one of those marked or pre-marked by the Council for Prosecutors. As he said and admitted earlier, he did not or they did not mark all of the annexes in your affidavit.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. If I may, check ko lang po, Your Honor, para sigurado po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wala sa iyo ngayon. Inaanap ko po rito. Wala nga pong annex yan eh. Wala
Sen. Imee Marcos: sa annex at wala rin sa affidavit. Kasi yung mga media na tinutukoy sa ibang pahina eh yung mga nag-interview nung Zoom conference.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Dito ho yung certified through copy daw,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor. If I may, Your Honor, please. Can I assist on this regard if the court will allow?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Only if you can produce a copy of the November 6th subpoena, counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Exactly, Your Honor. The documents are present. They are in the possession at present of the witness, Your Honor, please. They may not have been physically attached to the affidavit investigation but they do exist in the records of the case as separate pre-marked documents, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Is Council saying that therefore the affidavit is defective or wrongful and that November 6 is not the right date? What then is the right date?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: With all due respect, we object to the use of the term.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Defective. Council, we shall await. Let
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the document speak for itself.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The witness is now in the process.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, it was the witness who
Sen. Imee Marcos: said that it was a mistake, not
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: me. I know, it doesn't make the entire affidavit of investigation defective. No, I
Sen. Imee Marcos: merely said the date was wrong because that's what he said. Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Imee Marcos: It's just been brought to my attention that in fact, Presiding Officer, two documents were issued on November 6. Not only the subpoena to ABS-CBN, but further, the affidavit of investigation regarding the October 18 press con. Can we please be clarified? As to these two documents, which don't seem to appear in the affidavit nor in the annexes provided.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let's first wait for the witness to answer the first question, Senator Judge Margos. Yes, Attorney
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Lutok. If I may, Your Honor. Ito ho
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: ang Sabina Duchesne-Taycom. Yung date ho ng appearance niya is December 11.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Appearance po, tinatanong 'yung date ng subpoena. Date ng subpoena, Your Honor, is 6th day of November 2024, which I believe is a typo, kasi magkakasunod ho ito doon sa mga initial namin na media personalities.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lotoc, typo na 'yung affidavit mo, typo pa 'yung subpoena?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What are you looking at, the subpoena or the affidavit? Dalawa 'yan, eh. What are you looking at, Atty. Lotoc?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Subpoena, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, the subpoena is dated November 6.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Okay. And the affidavit also is November 6. Dalawang typo carried over.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Asan yung affidavit? Hindi ko pa nakita, ma'am, yung affidavit na November 6. Ikaw ang kumirma eh.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yung
Sen. Imee Marcos: affidavit of investigation mo na binigay, pati yung amended, carried over din. Yung first draft na re-neject ng DOJ, yung ikalawa, parehong November 6.
Sen. Imee Marcos: Pirmado ninyo eh.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Page 6, Council. Paragraph 14 of his affidavit of investigation.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. It's November 6, 2024 ang nakasulat yan.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, typo din yan? Is it your testimony na typo din yan?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I believe so, Your Honor. Kasi ang intention namin dyan is...
Sen. Imee Marcos: Sa palagay mo, ano yung tamang date kung mali yung November 6?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Sa pinanainisya namin sa media personalities. Dapat magkakapareho. Yes, magkakasunod po yun. Okay,
Sen. Imee Marcos: sige. Maraming salamat. Thank you very much, Presiding Officer. Damang salamat. Salamat po, ma'am.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Sen. Judge Marcos. Sen. Bam Aquino, and then we proceed to Cross.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, can
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, can we just point out one thing?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Atty. Vinluan.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, regarding that matter, Your Honor, may we just manifest, Your Honor, for the record that Not only in paragraph 14, page 6, does the November 6, 2024 date appear, it also appears on the footnote. Footnote 12, November 6, 2024. So, I don't think, we just want to read for the record, footnote 12, subpoena to Francis Torral, head, ABS-CBN News, dated 06 November 2024. In addition to that, if you look at the subpoena,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And paragraph 14 also is on 06 November 2024, a subpoena was issued to ABS-CBN News.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Now,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: it
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: is actually, it states that a copy of the video pertaining to the 18 October 24 press conference. And when you look at the subpoena itself, can you just ask for time?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The subpoena, if you look at the subpoena, there's an attachment and the photo contained therein actually pertains to the 18 October 2024 press briefing. So in other words, Your Honor, this is a substantive, this is not a mere typographic.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, Your Honor. Counter-manifestation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ito po po yung
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Continuation po ito nung tanong ko kanina tungkol sa general denial tsaka specific denial. Pero bago yun, Atty. Vin Luan, let me ask Atty. Lotoc, kanina po tinanong kayo kung bakit niyo tinuloy yung kaso while you continued with filing. Sabi niyo po kanina, hindi naman siguro siya magsisinungaling. Siya meaning the vice president. Could you just quickly tell me what do you mean by that? Hindi naman siguro siya magsisinungaling.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, the surrounding circumstances at that time, yung atmosphere, sabi ko nga galit na galit siya at madiin yung kanyang mga pinitawang salita at ito ay nagugat pa sa mga naunang event.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So doon, nung winika niya na wag kang mag-alalamam sapagkat may Sa security ko sapagkat may kinausap na akong tao. From the point of view of the NBI, we believe that... So you took it as truth? Yes. Okay.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: In succeeding interviews, I'm sure nag-imbestiga ka, meron bang pagtanggi dito sa pagkausap sa isang tao na papatay kung may mangyari kay Vice President Duterte? Meron ba kayong napanood o naimbestiga na pagtanggi nito in the succeeding interviews?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. I think there was a video dated November 26, 2024.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Doon sa video na yon, instead na i-deny niya yung nangyari noong November 23, nire-iterate pa ho niya, Your Honor, and admit po niya na indeed may kinausap siyang tao. So
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: inulit pa,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: kumbaga? Opo. Okay. So
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: let me repeat my question to the defense. So far, wala pang... Actual statement si Vice President Duterte na tinatanggi itong pagkausap sa isang hitman. And for the benefit of the public, magkaiba ho kasi yung general denial sa specific denial. Ang general denial, hindi ko ginawa yan. Wala akong kasalanan. Yung specific denial, hindi ko ginawa ito mismo mga bagay-bagay na ito. Hindi ko yung nakita sa sagot ng depensa. So I asked the defense, is there a denial that The Vice President actually spoke to a person to kill the individuals that we're talking about, Atty. Vin Luan. Sabi niyo meron. Could you point us to where it is in your answer?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, I just want to clarify because specific denial is a legal term. So in other words, we just want in order to satisfy the query of Senator Judge Aquino, We will give him a copy of our answer and we highlighted certain portions thereof, particularly paragraph 3 and paragraph 197. Can
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: you read both paragraphs please? I mean kami dito binabasa naman namin yung mga sagot ninyo. Sineseryoso namin yan, no? So, can you read the two, please?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It reads, the rest of the allegations in the articles, including the supposed evidence attached therein, are specifically denied for being false, misleading, impertinent, mere conclusions of fact and law, and subject to the affirmative allegations and special and affirmative defenses below. That's
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Article 3.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Paragraph 3, Your Honor.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: That's Paragraph 3. So, the rest, itong mga iba.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Sorry, paragraph 197.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It says there finally no such purpose contemplated by law was attained or could have been attained precisely because the respondent did not have any purpose other than simply answer a speculative inquiry. So that is our position on the matter.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: So your position is that is enough of a specific denial to the allegation na may kinausap na hitman si Vice President Sara?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor, because we discussed in our answer that the presumption never shifts. It is in light of our discussion that it is the burden of the prosecution to prove their claim, considering that according to our laws, he who alleges must prove. And so we just presented our arguments accordingly. Okay. So
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: I'm sure, Atty., sa inyong summation, you will argue this, that the burden of evidence has shifted. Pero hindi niyo po na take into account na ito mismo'y galing sa vice president natin.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, to clarify, the burden of proof is with the prosecution and not with the defense.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In fact, Your Honor, according to our laws, even if we do not present evidence, if they do not overcome that threshold, Your Honor, then we believe that our client is entitled to...
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: So ang sagot po nyo, and this is my final question, Presiding Officer, ang sagot po nyo, kailangan i-prove ng prosecution na merong hitman. And you're not denying that the Vice President spoke to a hitman?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: No, we are denying that, Your Honor. It's just that that was our presentation and our
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: answer. Okay. So, for the record, you are denying that the Vice President actually spoke to a hitman na, in fact, ang sabi nga ni Atty. Lotoc, hindi siya nagsisinungaling, sinasabi nyo, actually, nagsinungaling siya at wala siyang kinausap na hitman. Yan pong sinasabi ninyo?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor. I don't know what's the frame of mind of Atty. Lotoc, but that is our answer, Your Honor.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Maraming salamat Atty. Thank you.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Any instance that the vice president had come out on TV or radio saying that, hindi, joke only, nagkamali ako.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Ano lang ito, nagbambuha. Kasi si Tatay Digong nung araw sinasabi niya yun eh. Papatayin ko siya. Tapos mamaya, ah joke only yan. Nagloloko lang ako. Parang ganun. So at no particular point in time, has she issued a denial that she said these statements? Aside from what you submitted to this court as a Blanket denial.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: There is your order and we just reserve our right to present that evidence at the proper time as well, Your Honor.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Okay, so there's a video or recording that was done maybe a month or during the period of time that she had mentioned this that she was denying because we'd like to see that as well. That would weigh in heavily on our decision because kung nayon lang po nagpalabas ang
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Depensa ng denial, parang after the fact na eh, kasi nagkaroon na po tayo ng impeachment trial. We'd like to see that if you have that kind of evidence.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: very much, Mr. President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Sen. Judge Zubiri. What is the pleasure of Sen. Judge Alan Cayetano?
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: I'm not going to ask a question, just for clarification. May I just put it on the record?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The gentleman may proceed and he has two minutes.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: If you look at the articles of impeachment, Article 4, Respondent Vice President Sara Duterte committed culpable violation of the Constitution, high crimes, and betrayed public trust by contracting for the assassination by the President, the First Lady, and the former Speaker of the House by making grave threats and actively inciting sedition against the public. To be fair to the prosecution, I think it was asked of them that Merely threatening for you is already impeachable either high crimes, grave threats or by culpable violation. But there is a difference between saying that that mere statement is impeachable by alleging that she did in fact contract someone to kill. Because if you look at the next page, It is the position of the prosecution of the House of Representatives. The fact that responded, contracted an assassin no longer requires further proof as it is already established under the matter of the light of our own public admission. That's a conclusion of law.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: As far as I'm concerned, ang understanding ko, the prosecution did not stop short by saying that by merely uttering that, that is impeachable. They went further to say that they are alleging that she did in fact
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: In fact, nowhere in her words, assassin, in the words of the vice president was assassin or contracted. Contracted means may kontrata. Sinabi niya lang may kinausap siya. And yung assassin came from, at least on these documents, from them. So I just want to clarify because baka yung manunod, bakit nga naman hindi kailangan i-prove nasabi in public? What I wanted to clarify, those are two different things.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Can I reply to that?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No need to reply. Senator-Judge Cayetano was not asking a question. He was merely making a manifestation for the record. Let's move on. Counsel for the respondent, if you're ready with your cross, you may proceed.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. But unlike the DOJ, it is not a prosecutorial body. Correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In fact, you have investigators and not prosecutors. Am I right?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Now, in relation to this case, what you did was only fact-finding investigation, correct? Fact-finding and recommendation, sir. And recommendation, not preliminary investigation.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Not preliminary.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Because that function is with the DOJ, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And in the course of your fact-finding investigation, you subpoenaed witnesses, correct? Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Conducted interviews? Yes, sir. Gathered evidence?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. Okay. Now, thereafter, you transmitted the result of your fact-finding investigation to the DOJ, correct? Our recommendation, sir, yeah. Okay. We learned from Agent Kalilong last time, just to clarify, that there were two transmitters.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Correct.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The first transmittal was on January 30, 2025, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. Can we flash that on the screen? For the benefit of our senators, that is page 7 of the Articles of Impeachment Annex G9 or GGGG. Alright. Now, if you look at the document, This was received by the DOJ also on the same day, so January 30, 2025, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Well, it is not clear, but it can be read. If I may be allowed to use a pointer, Your Honor? You may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: do so, Counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It's quite unclear, but actually, if you look at the actual document, it can be read as January 30, 2025. Do you confirm this?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't have the document, Sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Well, we have a hard copy and I asked my co-counsel to show the document.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Co-counsel may approach.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: 30.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, hindi siya clear, Your Honor. Alright. Now, this was addressed to Prosecutor General Fadulyon, correct? Yes, yes. Okay. And NBI's recommendation was for one count of inciting to sedition and three counts of grave threats. Am I right? Yes, sir. Now, attached to this transmittal letter was your affidavit of investigation. I won't bother to read the body but it says there that it was attached to that transmittal letter, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Because of course, the transmittal letter won't be empty. It has to contain something, correct?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, let the witness—my move that the witness be allowed to answer first before the counsel asks a follow-up question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness will please answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think 'yung copy ng first affidavit is nasa DOJ na.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So there was an affidavit of investigation, because Agent Calilung also confirmed this last time. I just want a clarification from you. There was a first affidavit of investigation dated January 30, 2025, but we never saw this because it was never released, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think nasa DOJ for purposes of case build-up.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But didn't you keep a receiving copy for your office?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: in other words, you have a copy of this January 30, 2025 affidavit of investigation, correct?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I move that the kind of witness finish his answer first before the council.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly wait for the witness to finish his answer.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We will comply, your honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Well,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: personally, I believe na nandoon sa DOJ yung copy and then yung sinubmit sa amin is yung
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Unang certification is stating na kailangan niyong i-comply itong seven requirements.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. Now, there was also an investigation data form attached, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I don't have the copy, Your Honor. But if you know, if there is an investigation
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: data form that was attached
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: to it, correct? Okay. Now, very well. Now, the DOJ thereafter evaluated the case.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Part of the DC-15 requirement, Your Honor. No,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: it's a
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: yes, sir. It's answerable by yes or no. Your Honor, the witness is in the process of answering a question. He is intelligent enough to answer the question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness finish his answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Part of the requirement of the DC-15, Series of 2024, if I'm not mistaken, the Circular has directed the prosecutors To proactively engage in the investigation of crimes or in the criminal investigation.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Kaya yung ginagawa namin nung nag-submit kami nung transmittal, ang purpose nun for evaluation ng ating prosecution at the same time for case build-up. So pag nakita ng prosecutor na may kulang,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Part ho ng evaluation saka case build up process, nagbibigay ho sila ng recommendation ng NBI. May kulang kang ganito, may kulang kang ganito, hindi pa sa sufficient, i-comply niyo muna ito. Part ho yun ng DC-15 requirements. Alright,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: clear. So in other words, the evaluation is to determine if the recommendation is sufficient or insufficient for the purpose of preliminary investigation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Kase build up so that the transmitter or referral would be able to comply the requirements of preliminary investigation. At
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: any rate, preliminary investigation is the next step, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor, after the evaluation and case building process.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Can you receive this evaluation or response from the DOJ? Am I right?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You mean the certification, sir?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, the first certification... No, if
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: only you received...
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Again, again, again. The witness is in the process of answering the question and the council is excited to propound the follow-up question. Let the witness answer first.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Same ruling, same reminder. Witness, kindly proceed to answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Again,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: sir? What was the question?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, you received the response from the DOJ?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, certification dated February 5, 2025.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Oh, no, no. That's not my question. But anyway, let me direct your attention to a certification issued by the DOJ through Senior Assistant State Prosecutor J. V. Lawrence B. Bandong and approved by Senior Assistant State Prosecutor Herbert Calvin P. Abugan dated February 5. For the benefit of this honorable court and the Filipino people watching, this is Articles of Impeachment Annex G. 9 as well, pages 10. Atty. And
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: 11. May we ask that the witness peruse this certification?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Just a manifestation, Your Honor. Annex G. 9 is actually not numbered. So, pages 10 and 11 was based on the PDF file or the soft copy. But the hard copies are not actually numbered. Noted. So, Mr. Witness, was this the response from DOJ following your January 30, 2025? Yes, sir. So this certification contained the DOJ's evaluation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Part of the requirement. Again, again. Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The witness is still answering. Let the witness answer first before propounding the next question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And the NBI received this February 5 certification, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I'll help
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you. There is a note received on the upper right that is unclear. Can we flash that on the screen as well? It is unclear. But it appears to have been received on February 5, 2025, correct? So more or less six days after your transmittal. Do you confirm this?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, before the witness answers the question, I would like to commence my objection on the ground of relevance. May I explain, Your Honor, please? This witness testified that what they filed with the NBI with the DOJ is a February 10 February 10 affidavit investigation and here comes the defense now asking questions as to the first affidavit of investigations that the NBI submitted which the DOJ asked them to correct and to provide additional information which they complied with and what is now at issue is the February 10
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What is the point of digging into a prior affidavit investigation when what this witness identified is a later affidavit investigation that is now being considered by the DAO? The question is simple, what's the relevance?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection is overruled. It goes into the credibility of the witness as well as his ability to testify as to his investigative report. And witness is competent enough anyway.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Witness may answer? Yes, Your Honor. No, Your Honor. We received that letter on 10 February 2025 based on the second letter submitted to Hon. Richard Anthony D. Fadulion signed by Judge Jaime B. Santiago. It states here that on 10 February 2025, this Bureau received the certification dated 05 February 2025, where the evaluating prosecutors referred the case for case build-up, citing reasons thereof.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Then in that case, Your Honor, we have a problem because this is— Oh, Your Honor, objection! I'm not yet— Objection!
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly let counsel finish.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Because, like, as I mentioned a while ago, Your Honor, this forms part of the records of this honorable court. This was submitted as page 10 to 11 of Annex G. 9. This is part of the court's record and we also received this. These are not our documents.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: These are
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: not our documents, Your Honor. These are part of the records of the court. This came from them and they attach this to the articles of impeachment. Your Honor, we have all the right to confront each and every document because that forms part of
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the charge against our client.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Now, if Atty. Lotoc is saying, Your Honor, if I may just be allowed to finish,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: it was received on February 10, we just want to manifest, counter-manifest, Your Honor, that there is a received stamp here since February 5.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, this is not highly... Counsel, the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: presiding officer already overruled the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection of counsel for the prosecutors and... I thought you would end up with a question. Kindly proceed with your cross-examination.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, in other words, you deny that it was received on February 5, 2025 as seen here in this document that is part of the records of the Senate Impeachment Court?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, first, Your Honor, hindi ako yung nag-receive niyan. Then, pangalawa, ang nakapirma rito ang dating director namin, Jaime B. Sanchago, at ang sinasabi niya... On 10 February 2025, this mural received the certification dated 05 February 2025.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, anyway, I'll move on to a new point. This certification noted seven items and we went through this the last time with Agent Kalilong so I won't delve on that but basically just to go through this very quickly the first point says that there is no affidavit of the person so no affidavit The second note is the press briefing conducted on October 18, so no TSN and affidavit of the person taking the TSN. Number three is annexes I and K with markings, so no affidavit of recorder and no TSN and affidavit. Number four, annex L did not indicate who made such TSN, so incomplete information. Number five, the affidavit of Juan Patria Morales, so no USB. 6. Only the minutes of the meeting with several per- So no affidavit. But I'd like- Oh, Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that's my objection now.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I'm
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: just reading
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: it, Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor. Where's the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: question? Wait
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: for the question. I'm going to the question. I'm just laying the basis, Your Honor. Now, I'd like to highlight note number 7. Please allow me to read that portion. Or at least the latter portion thereof. It says there, In the instant complaint, only the NBI executed an affidavit. And there was no participation on the part of the offended parties. As it appears, NBI is not the offended party for the crime of grave threats. My question is this. So based on note number 7, according to the DOJ, the NBI is not the offended party, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on number 7, NBI is not the offended party for the crime of grave threats. Okay,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: very well. So, the offended parties, if at all, are President BBM, the First Lady, and the former Speaker, correct? Yes, sir. At any rate, all these, the seven notes that I mentioned, are all deficiencies in the first affidavit of investigation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It's not deficiency, Your Honor, because the affidavit, the first affidavit we've submitted is substantial in terms of establishing the evidence
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: required.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: This requirement is a matter of complying the required quantum of evidence required under DC-20. And if I may, sir, the purpose of submitting our referral to the Department of Justice is for preliminary investigation which under the The NPS rules, the new rules under the NPS, the law enforcement agency can submit a complaint affidavit or in fact submit a complaint before the DOJ for purposes of preliminary investigation. The requirement that the affected party should have the complaint affidavit is not an indispensable requirement and so for us, the preliminary investigation is concerned. You saw for us the preliminary investigation. Very
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: well. Now, based on that answer, I'd just like to point your attention to the portion of this certification dated February 5, 2025. Next to the box, stick with an X. Kindly allow me to read if we can highlight that portion.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay? It says here, and you can read with me, insufficient for the conduct of preliminary investigation and must first be referred for case build-up. So this is my question, I'll do it in Filipino. So in other words, nakulangan yung DOJ, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: For purposes, Your Honor, of satisfying the elements, I mean the required quantum of dividends, the DOJ required us to attach the filibits and other documents like the DSN, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Thank you. And the DOJ itself mentioned this, correct? Or said this, correct? Based on the
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: certification.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. In fact, let me direct your attention to the portion after I quote, must first be referred for case build-up. Can we flash that also on the screen? And allow me to read. The complaint slash referral does not contain all the necessary evidence to prove the essential elements of the crime. Therefore, it is recommended that the same be first referred for case build-up. Okay? Now let me get this straight. I'll summarize first and then I'll ask the question. So the subject incident happened on November 23, 2024, and the NBI conducted fact-finding investigation, as you said. You subpoenaed individuals, conducted interviews, gathered evidence among others, as you said also, and the NBI spent over two months or until January 30, 2025 for this process. Is this a fair summation of what we had just discussed?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I don't think so, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: don't agree. And yet, when the NBI transmitted the case to the DOJ on January 30, 2025, the DOJ found it to be insufficient for the conduct of preliminary investigation.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, Your Honor. Continuing objection as to the relevant series of questions as to the prior affidavit investigation which was corrected in February 10, 2025. Continuing objection, Your Honor. The continuing
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection is noted. Same ruling by the court. Witness may answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The fact that the Department of Justice issued another certification
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: on
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: February 14, 2025, and it states here that the referral is sufficient for conduct of preliminary investigation and that it contains all the necessary evidence to prove the essential elements of the crime and should be docketed for preliminary investigation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the permission of the parties, Atty. Lotoc, that's the second certification?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The second certification.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondents.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, we will go to that. In other words, based on this certification, the DOJ did not affirm the NBI's recommendation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No. Part of the process of evaluation and case build-up, the DOJ require us to comply with the requirements na iniingin nila gaya ng mag-attach kayo ng affidavit, mag-attach kayo ng TSN. Pero wala akong sinabi ang DOJ doon na hindi substantial yung aming affidavit. Ang narequire lang nila mag-attach kayo ng… yun nga yung affidavit.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Narecord yung video at then yung TSN, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Well, according to you, but we just... Oh, no, you're argumentative.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection! Argumentative! Argumentative, asked and answered. Move on, counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay, that's interesting because there was a 2025 impeachment complaint filed against VP Sara also on February 5, 2025. If you know, if you know.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The date is important because there was also an impeachment complaint filed against VP Sara on February 5, 2025. Correct? You're not familiar? That's okay. If I may refresh your memory, this was the fast-track 2025 impeachment complaint signed by the 115 representatives.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If a ground arises, counsel can object. The term fast-tracked? Oh, Your Honor. You are labeling a process made by the House of Representatives as fast-tracked.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, move on. Move on and ask your question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: If you know, if this coincides with that impeachment complaint that was signed by the 215th representative. Objection.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There's no basis. This counsel, this witness, again, already said that he is not aware that on that day there was an impeachment complaint. There's no basis for that question. Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness already answered. The counsel for prosecutor is correct. Witness already answered. He's not familiar with the filing of an impeachment complaint on that date.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: At any rate, this pertains to the November 23. November 23, 2024 video, correct? Objection vague, Your Honor. What's the question referring to a video? Objection vague. Kindly restate your question, Counsel. The complaint. The complaint that was filed against the Vice President also pertains to the November 23, 2024 video.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, complaint. Again, vague complaint. Fired on that date.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Well, if he knows. He already answered he doesn't. Who knows? He might all of a sudden recall. Do you know? Are you familiar with that, Mr. Atty. Lotoc?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I said, Your Honor, hindi ako familiar ng filing sa impeachment.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You're not familiar. Okay, I'll move on to a new point then. Now, did you rectify your January 30, 2025 affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: January 30, 2025, Affidavit of Investigation. In short, the first affidavit of investigation.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We complied with the requirements of the Department of Justice.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. Did anybody ask you to rectify?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: What do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: mean? What do you mean? Did you receive any directive from anybody to rectify that affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection argumentative. The question was us. He said we complied and then he's now asking the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: same question. I'm asking who?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I'm asking if there is another person who directed you to satisfy the requirement.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overall, witness will answer. Witness is an intelligent witness aside from the fact that he's a lawyer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, when we received the certification dated 05 February 2025,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ito ho yung kinumplay namin. Alright.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And you added affidavits executed by your agents, correct? To your revised affidavit of investigation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, we didn't revise the affidavit of investigation. We just produced the affidavits of the fact that the video was recorded and there was DSN. Yun ho yung inattach namin sa affidavit of investigation. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you are denying that you... You produce a revised affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, when you say kasi revised affidavit, binago namin yung affidavit namin. Hindi ho namin binago, Your Honor, yung affidavit namin. Nag-require ho ang Department of Justice. Kulang kayo ng affidavit as to the fact na nirecord niyo yung video. Kulang kayo doon sa affidavit kung sino nag-execute ng TSN, etc. But not the substance ng affidavit, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, I'll go back to the point later, but let me highlight one very important observation, okay? Your January 30, 2025 affidavit of investigation included a transmittal letter, as you said, as well as an investigation data form or IDF, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala akong kopya dito, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You don't have a copy, okay. In fact, let's show that IDF. Page 12, this is page 12 of Annex G. 9 for the benefit of this honorable court as well. Okay, this is an investigation data form. You're very familiar with this document because you're an investigator, correct? Now, this was—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly wait for the witness to answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah. Investigation data form, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: so in other words, the IDF serves like a cover letter for your affidavit of investigation, correct? Yes, sir. Okay. And the transmitter letter along with this IDF was received by the DOJ, correct? Yeah, I believe so, sir. Now, my question is this. Was the investigation data form also received by the DOJ?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't have personal knowledge.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But you were the one who caused the filing of the affidavit attached to this affidavit of the investigation data
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: form, correct? I instructed
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: the agent on case as well as the executive officer. Pag kumpleto na, pwede ninyo nang i-file yan sa Department of Justice for purposes of evaluation and case build-up if warranted.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. But here, upon perusal of this investigation data form, there is a stamp received in the upper left portion of this data investigation form. And I'd like to note your honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And for the benefit of the court, can I ask my co-counsel also to distribute among the senator judges a printed copy so that they can peruse this document better as well as the witness so he can confront.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: There is a stamp Department of Justice received but it appears that it was initially stamped February 2, 12, 2025. But there is a marking, a manual marking that converted it to January 30. And there is also a word there, J-A-N. So January, January 30 ang lumabas. My question to you is this, the stamp says Department of Justice, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, wala akong hawak na document.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You can perceive it. And mind you, these are not our documents. These are part of Annex G-9 of the Articles of Impeachment. So these are not our documents.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, I would like to object now. The witness already said that he is not aware as to the actual filing because he only asked his agent on case to investigate. And then now, the witness is being propounded the question as to what appears on the stamp, as to the time or date of receipt by the DOJ. So the witness said he is not competent to answer that. Your Honor, please. Oh, wait, wait. I'm not done. That's the first one. Your Honor, please. No need for the court to rule, but I am registering my continuing objection to this series of questions as to the prior affidavit of investigation, when in fact this witness already said that he complied with all the requirements by the DOJ and came up with a February 10, 2025 affidavit of investigation. So I move that it be noted, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The continuing objection of counsel for the prosecutor is noted. But counsel, as pointed out by counsel for the respondent, this is part and parcel of the complaint that the panel of prosecutors filed before this court. If the witness knows, he may answer.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So the question is: the stamp says Department of Justice, correct? It's a very basic question.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, I don't know, Your Honor. No,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: based on this document, the only question is, it says Department of Justice, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As I've said, Your Honor, hindi ako ang nag-file. May inutusan ako. Do you see it in the screen? Do you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: see it in the hard copy? Counsel asked and answered. Move on. That's the response of the witness.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Will you agree that considering that this was supposed to be received by the DOJ, it is only the DOJ that has the authority to change the date?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, you ask the DOJ, sir. Wala akong hindi-agent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Alright. Counsel for the prosecution, kindly avoid. Alright, but this is not
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: from the DOJ. This is your copy. This is a receiving copy. So when you received back your receiving copy, you did not bother checking this portion? Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor, hindi ako personally nag-receive niyan.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But this is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: your affidavit of investigation. Objection. Argumentative, Your Honor. Ask and answered. Asked and
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: answered. Move on, Counsel. Alright.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: My question to you now is this. The discrepancy is not one days or two days. The discrepancy is from Feb 12 to January 30. So it is a substantial discrepancy. My question to you is this. Who changed this date? Objection.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, Your Honor. That's misleading, Your Honor. My goodness. That's misleading. This council assumed that somebody changed what? The council failed to... Atty.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: R.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But my more important observation is this. Objection, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You are supposed to ask questions. Yes, I will go to the question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I will go to the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kindly
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: allow council correspondent to finish his question. He may just still be laying the basis. You may proceed, counsel. That's precisely what
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I'm doing, Your Honor. Can I direct everyone's attention to the date appearing at the bottom portion of this document?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Council, technically not everyone. Just the witness.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: let's see if the witness can answer your question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It says here February 11, 2025. So in other words, and it says here subscribed before NBI agent Ricarte. In other words, the date of the document is February 11. But it was received on January 30, 2025 by the DOJ. Do you have any explanation for this? That's the question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection. This witness is incompetent to attest to that exactly because he said he is not
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: aware of this series of facts. I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: know where the council for respondents is going. Unfortunately for him, his line of argument was already nipped in the bud when this witness said he is not aware of that. He should move on to other points. Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor. The witness said that this investigation data form was attached to the original affidavit of investigation. And we want an explanation why there is a discrepancy
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: on the date.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: witness is a lawyer. He
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: has an experience, Your Honor, in filing cases. We just want to know, Your Honor. We want to get to the bottom of this. Are you
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: object to that? Considering also, Your Honor, that this is about transparency...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Will the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: parties please settle down? If the witness knows, Atty. Lutok, do you know? Can you explain the discrepancy or are you personally aware of the discrepancy?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I cannot explain this, Your Honor. Unang-una hindi ako nakapirma dito, hindi ako nag-receive, at wala akong idea dito sa... But
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lutok, you see the point that the Council for Respondent is trying to make, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That the date of receipt... This was changed to 1.30, January 30, but it was subscribed to on February 11. Meaning, you see it, but you have no personal knowledge how that came about.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Move
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: on, Counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: doesn't this demonstrate that the document was tampered with?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Doesn't this demonstrate, if you know that this... This document was tampered with. Objection, Your Honor. Exactly.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: He's now arguing with our witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sustained. Move on, counsel. Move on to your next topic, counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, but you agree, Atty. Lotoc, that the IDF is not a simple cover letter, correct? Ask and answer, Your Honor. Okay. In fact, it is an affidavit, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: An
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: IDF is an affidavit,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: correct? An ID... I don't think so, Your Honor. It's not an affidavit, Your Honor. The
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: investigation data form... It's not an affidavit. So you don't agree. So in other words, this certification part here, and with the subscribed and sworn to, it is for you, this is not an affidavit?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Argumentative, Your Honor. Your Honor, I just made
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: my question more specific, Your Honor. There is a part here, subscribed and sworn to, and the witness is, I want to ask the witness if he considers this document as an affidavit despite this portion.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: What's the answer? Is it an affidavit or not? Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Natok, is this sworn to?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Is this document sworn to the... What's the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: title of the instrument again? Can you go up?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Investigation data form, your honor. Is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: an investigation data form subscribed and sworn to by the person filing it?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: To
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: your knowledge.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, your honor. There is subscribe and sworn to before this 11th day of February and signed by the administering officer.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. And as law practitioners, we know that when we file a case before the office of the... City Prosecutor, this actual page is signed and subscribed before the public prosecutor, correct? If you know, you are a lawyer and you are a supervisor of your department. I'm just asking a basic question. As a law practitioner, as a lawyer, you know that this IDF is... Signed and
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: subscribed before the public prosecutor when you file a case, correct? If I may object,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor. Continuing objection as to the relevance of this series of questions.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Same ruling. Witness may answer if he knows.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, Your Honor, before the prosecutor?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Correct. In normal cases, the IDF is subscribed and sworn to before the public prosecutor, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, in this case, Your Honor, it was administered by
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Assistant Director Glenn Ricarte, Your Honor. Okay,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I'm glad you pointed that out. Isn't Ricarte from the NBI?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, he is
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Assistant Director. In
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: other words, this is a DOJ document, but you made your subscription before an NBI agent. Isn't that supposed to be before the DOJ agent?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, I don't have personal knowledge on those details, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Alright,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: but what is worse, if I can direct your objection. You know, this council is in the habit of inserting, adding
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: value
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: to
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: what is otherwise— If we may just
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: be allowed to continue, Your Honor, this is our time. We've given them enough leeway, Your Honor, after more than hours. Let him lay
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the basis of his question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All right, can I direct your attention to the upper right portion of this IDF? It states docketed 3-7-2025 and there is a docket number XVI-INV-25C-00048. Again, the source of this document is not the DOJ. This is your receiving copy, correct? In fact, this was part of the subpoena documents which you sent to the House of Committee on Justice, correct? Objection. Compound questions. Two questions. Kindly reform, counsel. So, all right. My question is this, okay? So, do you confirm that there is a marking on the upper right which says docketed 3725? And there's a docket number assigned?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: In this document, sir, yes.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All right. We manifest your honor that this is still the same Annex G-9. So in other words, you're telling this court that this document was subscribed on February 11, 2025, received on January 30, 2025, and docketed. On whatever it is, July 3 or March 7, 2025. Is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that what you're saying? That's compound. That's compound. You're asking two dates and asking for one question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, I just described the document as it is.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Exactly.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Compound question. Ask one question per date. That is exactly the genius why we don't allow compound questions. You are asking two questions and asking this witness to answer once. That's dangerous. That's
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: compound question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Proceeding Officer, we clarify the matter. Questions were earlier asked already with respect to the February subscription and the January 30 receipt. Insofar as the docketing is concerned, do you see the numbers and or dates 3-7-25, Atty. Latok?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor, in this document there is number 3-7-25.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And for clarity, NPS docket means National Prosecution Service.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Is that correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: it's a
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: docket of the National Prosecution Service.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Proceed, Counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All right. So now I am showing you pages 169, 168 to 169 also of Annex G-9. This pertains to the affidavit of Agent Calilung, which is an attachment now to the revised You added this document to rectify the January 30 affidavit of investigation, correct? You added this document in order to rectify the January 30, the first affidavit of investigation, correct? And we will confront you with the document. Again, these are not our documents.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The document was signed by Agent Mark Calilung and subscribed and sworn to before Atty. Van Homer Angluben.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. So, in other words, I just want to take a look at the date. Can we flash the date? So when you received the February 5 certification from the DOJ, you executed this, and it was February 10.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection revised. The witness already said that they did not revise it. They just complied. Misleading. Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel, kindly settle down. The question, Atty. Lotoc, is did you add in order to comply with the DOJ requirement this affidavit signed by Agent Kalilong? And it's the date February 10th.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Meaning in compliance with the DOJ observation, is this one of the affidavits that you added? And is it dated?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Although I don't have my record, it appears so, Your Honor, based on the document shown to me by the Council.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Both as to the fact that it was one of the affidavits added and as to the date. Atty. Latok. Yes, Your Honor. I am
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: showing you another affidavit. This is page 178-179 of Annex G-9. This now pertains to the Gueran affidavit. This was also an attachment to the revised Affidavit of investigation.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection again, Your Honor, please. The continuing use of revise when this witness already said that they did not revise anything. They just complied with the requirement. That's now misleading. Your Honor, many times over, many times over, misleading.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All right, just to put this issue at rest, Your Honor, I'm confronting the witness with a letter to... Richard Anthony D. Fadulion, dated February 11, 2025. And I want to read, Your Honor, the last paragraph thereof. It says, To support our recommendation, attached herein is the revised affidavit of investigation. This is not our document. This is the NBI's document. Can Attorney Lotoc be confronted with this document, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Lotoc, please answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. It was signed by Then Director Judge Jaime B. Santiago Can you confirm the last sentence for the record? Can you read it for the record?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: To support the recommendation attached herein is the revised affidavit of investigation, including its attachment. Can
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you repeat the word before the word affidavit of investigation, please?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Ask an
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: answer, Your Honor. Ask an answer. Then I'm not misleading after all.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection, Your Honor. That's an unnecessary statement. Counselor, you're supposed to ask questions and not make these remarks.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Councils, kindly settle down. We're about to wind up the day. All right, I'm
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: showing you now pages, proceed, 178 to 179 of the revised affidavit of investigation. Can you be confronted with that document?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: date is February 10, 2025. I just want to confirm the date if that is correct.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: As it appears from the document.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As it appears here, 10th day of February 2025. Very well.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I am showing you now pages 187 to 188 of Annex G-9, also a Kalilong affidavit, which is an attachment to the revised affidavit of investigation. Can we flash the date of that document?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: What's the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: question? Also February 10? So in other words, you attach this to your revised affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It appears here. 10th day of February 2025, sir. And
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you attached it to your affidavit of investigation, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: As an attachment, sir. All right, very good. Now, showing you 199 to 200 of Annex G9. Now, this is the Asuncion affidavit. And I'll make a point in a couple of questions, Your Honor. Can you just confirm the date also, and if it was attached to your revised affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 10th day, it appears here, 10th day of February 2025.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All right. So it was attached also to your revised affidavit of investigation.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Assumption.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes. All right. Now this is the question. I'm showing you now page 112 of Annex G-9, another Kalilong affidavit.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Did you also add this to rectify your January 30 affidavit of investigation or the first affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We have here a soft copy, affidavit of transcription. Was this also a document that was lacking in your first affidavit of investigation, which you added to your revised affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Again, Your Honor, registering my continuing objection as to the relevance of this series of questions that is turn to Cross-examine this witness. What's the relevance?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: consuming the entirety of the defense's  Noted. Same
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: ruling. Witness, may I answer?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Again,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor. Was
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: this also part of the revised affidavit of investigation to rectify the defects that we highlighted a while ago?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No, there was no rectification. There was no defect. Again, this is part of the compliance.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: All right,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: if you want to use that term. So in other words, after you received the Feb 5 certification, this was also one of the documents that you attached to your revised affidavit of investigation, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I believe so, part of the compliance. All
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: right. My issue is this. Let me direct your attention to the bottom portion of this affidavit. It says here, In witness hereof, I have— Can you zoom that in? I can't read it.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The date is February 3, 2025. Can you zoom that in? So in other words, you are trying to convince this court that when you— What's the question?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What's the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: question?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: This is the question. You're trying to convince— Are you trying to convince this court that you executed this affidavit prior—
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Objection. Misleading. He
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: did not execute the affidavit. I don't know. Sorry. You attached this affidavit prior— To the February 5, 2025 certification?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Prior to what, Your Honor? February 10?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. You received a certification on February 5, 2025, correct? And you said that you added affidavits after receipt thereof. Now, you mentioned a while ago that this was one of the affidavits that you added, and yet the date came prior. To the DOJ certification dated February 5, 2025.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you confirm this?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Gaya po ng number two, the press briefing.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ito, Your Honor, gaya ng number one, there is no affidavit of the persons who recorded the video entitled BP November 23 Press Con at Batasan through OBS. When in truth and in fact, kasama ho na and attached na doon,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So in other words,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you're telling this court that the DOJ made this mistake?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Not necessarily, Your Honor. Pwedeng hindi nakita ng prosecutor na naka-touch na yun. Kasi lalo dun po sa date eh. Na January 30 yung execution ng Affidavit of Authentication. Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, Your Honor, before we continue, I'm noticing something, Your Honor, please. The defense is in the process has been presenting portions of an alleged document and they're making notes. I don't think that's proper your honor. When you present a document, you present the document as if you don't make annotations. Exactly your honor. That's not proper your honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We are presenting the actual document and we're confronting it. This is just to address your honor what was intimated by the senators that they want to be able to Uh follow the discussion your honor using
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the screen
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: if I my my problem with that your honor please because it's like you
presenting your observation on a document and you're showing that to the court when what you're supposed to do is just to confront this witness with a
document without any annotations that's just my observation honor
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: noted
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel please proceed for respondent please proceed meaning uh but
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: If you go to the contents right it says here and let me read the press briefing conducted on October 18 2024 was not recorded and or stored in a DVD no video submitted and there was no TSN of the said briefing and do you confirm now that this this uh note on feb 5 uh was actually addressed by the affidavit submitted by
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Atty. Eugen Calilong This note was satisfied by the submission of the affidavit by Eugen Calilong. What affidavit, sir? The affidavit of transcription dated February 3.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: But can I see the affidavit, sir? The one that
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: we showed a while ago. It pertains to the same, because if you read here, if I may be allowed to read paragraph 1, can you zoom that in?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Paragraph 2. It says there, in relation to the ongoing investigation, the undersigned was that to transcribe. So this transcribed the screen-recorded video of the press conference of VP Sara on 18 October 2024. So in other words, this was exactly what the DOJ required, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, based certification na in-issue ang sabi ng DOJ, the press briefing conducted in October 18, 2024 was not recorded. And was stored in a DVD. There was no TSN of the said briefing and the necessary affidavit of the person taking the TSN.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And yet, on its face, this was, because the date is February 3, on its face, this was executed prior to the Feb 5, 2025 certification, which noted this requirement.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: As I've said, Your Honor, ang nag-uusap po dyan ng prosecutor at saka si Agent Kalilong, may mga... There were attachments in the first affidavit that the prosecutor did
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: not notice. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: that's your answer okay so but but the thing is if i uh let's go back to the idf investigation data form now the docket number that is indicated here is xvi ind 25c-0008 but in the feb 5 2020-2025 Certification. Can we flash that?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The docket number is different, appears to be different. It's XVI-EVAL-INV-25A-0049. Moreover, in the subsequent DOJ certification dated Feb 14, 2025, the docket number is also XVI.EVAL
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Do you confirm the difference in the docket numbers?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, no personal knowledge. DOJ ang naglagay ng docket number na 'yan.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But do you confirm that it was different? These are all received copies.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Asked and answered, Your Honor, please. Asked and answered. Argumentative.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: No, the question—the answer is not responsive.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Asked and answered, Counsel. Move on.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Despite
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the discrepancy in docket numbers, you still decided to push through with the handling of this case, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, I cannot confirm on the numbers because it's the DOJ who placed that number, sir. I repeat, it would be better if you ask the Department of Justice, sir. But
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: insofar as you are concerned, you are the complainant in this case, correct? Insofar as you are concerned, what is the correct docket number? Is it the one ending in 0049? I will
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: now object.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Or is it the one ending in 0049?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What they used, Your Honor? I will now object on the ground of misleading. You showed two docket numbers which appear different. And you have yet to establish that there is a wrong one and a correct one. And you have not established that. This witness said he is not aware of that. You have not established that there is something to be corrected. That's why the objection now, Your Honor, please. That's misleading. You assume that something is wrong that has to be corrected. Misleading.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, witness is not competent to answer your question. He already responded that this is a DOJ forum and he is not aware and that it might be proper to ask the DOJ instead at the proper time. Move on with another point, counsel. I think unless there's another inconsistency, you can move on to another inconsistency or another point.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You're just one last on this point. But in terms of what you followed, because as we know, you submit subsequent pleadings. As to these two docket numbers, which one did you follow, the 00048 or the 0049?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, I don't have the record here, Your Honor, if I can check my own record.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you have it now?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, can you give him a copy of his record?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Chair finds that relevant because in filing additional pleadings or other materials to the DOJ, they need to indicate the NPS number. For reference, so which one are you following? Which one did you follow subsequent to this?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: may
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: we
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: just manifest for the record that the witness is perusing the IDF investigation data form that is attached to the Articles of Impeachment, Annex G-9.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, this is the document from the defense, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I cannot confirm, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Move on, Counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: This is as received, correct? So in other words, you just received the document and you didn't bother to check?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, let him finish, but indeed it is argumentative. Move on to the next question, Counsel. With the permission of Senator Judge Tulfo, can we, are you winding up or not yet? Counsel, not yet?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Far from it, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Then Senator Judge Tulfo is recognized.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What is the pleasure of Senator Judge Tulfo?
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Just a manifestation.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: You may proceed, sir. And a question as well. Mr. Witness,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: a
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: lot of questions were asked to you regarding the filing with the Office of the DOJ in particular regarding the docketing, dating, subscription from the investigation data form. Now, can you tell this court what exactly is your role and what did you do in relation to the filing of this investigation data form?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. I instructed the Executive Officers as well as the Agent 1 case to file our referral to the Department of Justice. So sila na ho ang nag-ayos niyan, Sir, insofar as the Investigation Data Form, insofar as other requirements. Ang instruction ko is comply with the requirement given by the Department of Justice and then You submit it, and then kung ano yung kanilang guidance, you comply with it.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Okay, Mr. Presiding Judge, in my humble opinion, I think the errors in the investigation data form should be answered by the receiving office, and I think he's not— I mean, hindi siya talaga yung dapat sumagot sa mga katalungan na binabato sa kanya ngayon. Mukhang hindi siya really not qualified at sumasablay-sablay tong taon to. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Senator Judge Erwin Tulfo, thereafter, Senator Judge Alan Gaetano.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Quick question, Mr. Presiding Officer, to the witness and to the prosecution or prosecutor here. You have two minutes, sir.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Mr. Witness, when was the case filed against the VP?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The first one was the affidavit, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We filed in January 30, if I'm not mistaken.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: What year was it?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 2025, sir. And then, the Department of Justice required compliance because they said in the first certification, insufficient for conduct of preliminary investigation and must be referred for a case build-up. Now, what we did,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We complied with their requirements. And then, come 11 February 2025, we resubmitted our affidavit of investigation, Your Honor.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Where is this case? Has it been approved by DOJ or not?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think the preliminary investigation is ongoing.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: One-year preliminary investigation? One year. Over one year. January to January is one. February, March, April, May, June, July. Is it normal for the DOJ to conduct a preliminary investigation for over a year?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Witness? I can't answer, sir. You can't answer?
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Could it
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: be you're not asking them, Sir, what's the problem? Why haven't we yet
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: been able to file
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: a case against you
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: in court?
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: You're not asking? What I know, sir, Your Honor— You didn't ask them why? Is there still something missing from the DOJ? What is missing?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If the referral, Your Honor, is already in the DOJ, hands-off na kami doon. Sila ang magde-decide doon kung paano nila ipaprocess 'yung dokumento.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Kaya hindi po kayo nagtataka? Hindi kaya, sir, dito sa mga nakita po natin, mga ebidensya rito, mukhang sablay-sablay, parang minadali ho ninyo. Kaya nagkakaproblema ho tayo sa mga korte natin na dini-dismiss ang mga kaso dahil kulang ang mga dokumento at parang minadali. But nevertheless, you don't have to answer me that. Let me direct my question to the prosecutors. As a prosecutor, ito po ang mga ebidensya na nakita po natin, hindi pa rin ninyo ni-review? Hindi ninyo nakita itong inconsistencies? Doon nga po sa sinasabi ng defense na pinirmahan, sinubscribe, pero mas maaga 'yung pagtanggap.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, as to whether we perused that, Your Honor, please, unfortunately, we were not party to the preparation of these documents.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: No, but this was submitted as evidence, right?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor, please. That's why this witness is more than competent to answer that. But the main point of the prosecution, Your Honor, please, they already filed and complied with these requirements and addressed these defects, if you may, by filing a February 10, 2025 affidavit of investigation. That's why, if you have observed, our good Senator-Judge, we have been objecting as to the relevance of this. Exactly because what is in contention now is the latest affidavit of investigation that is now pending before the DOJ, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: All right. Just a quick manifestation to the NBI. Mr. Witness, next time po pag nag-sampa kayo ng kaso, make sure— kaya nga I was asking you kanina, I already have this feeling something is wrong. Sobrang tagal na sa DOG ng kaso ninyo. There's something wrong with the case. Siguro po, next time, make sure na yung kaso yung isasampa ninyo is airtight.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Yes, Your
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Honor. Yes, Your
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Honor. Yes, Your Honor. Yes, Your
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Honor. Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Quick manifestation. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. Senator-Judge Erwin Tulfo. Senator-Judge Alan Cayetano, you have two minutes, sir.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Less than two minutes. Quick clarification lang. So, January 30, affidavit of investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: January 30. February 5, DOJ says [unclear]?
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: At February 5, 'yun din ang filing ng impeachment complaint against Vice President Sara Duterte. And then, which you said wala kang knowledge doon. I'm just looking at the dates. Then February 10, 'yung revised na—doon sa ginamit ng DOJ na word, insufficiency—'yung one to seven, napunan, no? Or whatever the term is.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir. I think so.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Pero hindi siya pwedeng attachment nung una kasi January 30 sinubmit yun eh. So hindi ka naman pwede magsubmit ng January 30 na attachment mo February 3. So you went 3 days into the or 4 days into the future kasi may 31 yung January.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, sir, siguro ang…
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Makakasagot po niyan si Agent Kalilong, sir, since iya ang signatory doon. I
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: don't think you can answer it. Point ko lang, hindi logical na it was an attachment sa January 30 because wala pang February 3 noon eh. So hindi pwedeng post-dated affidavit. Second question lang, sa parehong affidavit of investigation na sinubmit, Walang input doon ang PSG, ESAF, PSC, ESAF, CIDG. So kayo lang yan.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: A statement, Your Honor, yung ina-touch po namin.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Yes. So what I meant is that questions kanina nung many here, including the Senate President, Wyn Gaceliana, did you consult the investigation ng PSC, etc. So nung finile nyo to, Walang input directly or indirectly ang Presidential Security Command, ang ISAF, ang PNP, CIDG, and anyone else, the National Security Council. So, purely NBI ito.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: No personal knowledge kung mayroong correspondence ng ibang agency with the Director.
Sen. Alan Peter Cayetano: Hindi kayo puwedeng walang personal knowledge kasi ikaw nag-file, eh. Ikaw nakapirma doon sa affidavit. So you would know whether doon sa affidavit na 'yon they had input or not. No one else could know because you're the one who signed, eh.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Insofar as the Cybercrime Division is concerned, kami po 'yung gumawa niyan. Yes. So the answer is they had no input. Hindi ko alam kung—well, insofar as the affidavit is concerned, amin po 'yon, Your Honor. Now, kung correspondence between other agencies and the NBI, hindi ko na po alam kung may usapan 'yon.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator Judge Cayetano, Senator Judge Monteveros. Thereafter, Senator Judge Heresito. Am I correct, JV? Senator Judge Monteveros is recognized. You may proceed. You have two minutes, ma'am.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Salamat po, Mr. Presiding Officer. Less than two minutes din po. Atty. Lotoc. Sa gitna nung DOJ certification dated February 5, 2025 at yung pag-submit nyo ng kumpletong affidavit of investigation na tinanggap na ng DOJ, may nagbago po ba sa diumanong sinabi ng vicepresidente?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala po. Wala.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Sa gitna ng DOJ certification dated February 5, 2025 at yung pag-submit niyo ng kumpletong affidavit of investigation na tinanggap na ng DOJ, may nagbago po ba sa rekomendasyon ng NBI?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala po, Your Honor.
Sen. Risa Hontiveros: Salamat po, Atty. Lotoc. Salamat po, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator-Judge Hontiveros. Senator-Judge Ejercito, you may proceed, sir, when you're ready. You have two minutes.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Atty. Tony Lotoc, may dagdag-glarification lang.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: The DOJ pointed out in its certification, yung pong pinakita kanina noong February 5, 2025, that the NBI is not the proper offended party to file a complaint for grave threats and referred its initial referral for case build-up. As a result of the referral for case build-up by the DOJ, did the NBI later submit? Afidavits or Statements from the Offended Parties, namely, si Presidente Marcos, First Lady, at si former Speaker, Martin Robualdez.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi na po, Your Honor, nung sinabit namin yung aming referral, yun po yung last phase ng investigation, and I think yung prosecutor na ho mag-i-issue ng summons sa mga parties involved. Ang purpose lang ho namin, to comply with the requirements. A preliminary investigation po.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: But earlier sa inyo pong statement, sinabi nyo na ang isa sa mga factors sa pag-evaluate ng threat, if it is really serious, is through the determination of the relationship between the parties. Sinabi nyo po yun kanina. Yes po, Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: So did you try at least to get the statements of the President, the First Lady? Or the Speaker of the House. Former Speaker.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ang pinagbasihan po namin yung Honor yung official statement nila dun sa website ng Presidential Communications Office. And then yung public statement ng former Speaker during the plenary session on November 25, 2024, Sir. So that was the
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: basis yung pong nasa PCO website. So you did not bother to get the statements from the offended parties?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think nung nakita ko namin yung video na nag-issue ng statement yung presidente, na-establish ko namin yung requirement kung ano yung treatment ng presidente nung marinig niya yung utterances ng vice-presidente. So nung nakita namin yun, May reaction. Ang sabi nga niya is nakakabahala. Based sa aming primary jurisdiction, nag-i-start to kami ng investigation, sir.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: Kanina rin tinanong kayo tungkol doon sa
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: revised affidavit of investigation, which you submitted after the DOJ referred to the case for case build-up in its certification doon nga sa February 5, 2025.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: You mentioned that it's just a compliance on the part of the NBI.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, ito ho yung part ng evaluation at saka case build-up process. Pag nakita ho ng prosecutor na may kulang pang mga attachment para ho mabuo maging pulido yung kaso. Nagbibigay sila ng mga requirement o NBI, kulang ka nito, kulang ka nito, i-comply mo ito para maidakit natin sa preliminary investigation. So normal
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: lang po yun sa investigation agency na magsabita additional evidence or revise the affidavits after the case is referred back by the DOJ for case build-up. As
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: part po ng evaluation at case build-up process, nagtutulungan ho dyan, Your Honor. Yung prosecutor and then yung investigator, base doon sa requirement ng DC-15, Your Honor.
Sen. Joseph Victor “JV” Ejercito: You mentioned that, last point Mr. Presiding Officer, you mentioned that the case before the DOJ is still ongoing. Yes po. So as of today, Atty. Lotoc, there is still no determination by the DOJ if the case referred by the NBI should be filed in court because there is prima facie evidence of reasonable certainty of conviction.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, wala po po kaming nare-receive any updates from the Department of Justice. Ang alam po namin is nasa PI Pahusya preliminary investigation process, Your Honor. Thank you, Atty. Lutok. Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Thank you po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Noted. And under the records, Atty. Vinluan, you may continue with your cross. Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor, I believe that there's a hanging question. Insofar as the NBI is concerned, what docket number did they follow? 00048
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: or 0049? What's the response of the witness, if he knows?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, I don't have the complete affidavit.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So I cannot confirm, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So you do not know what NPS docket number the NBI is using whenever it files subsequent pleadings to the DOJ regarding this case?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Definitely there is that IDF, there is that NPS. Hindi ko lang po, Your Honor, ma-insure kung anong NPS number po yun.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ang ginagamit ninyo?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ang ginamit. Pero nandodon po yun, your honor. Naka-attach po yun sa affidavit of investigation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Proceed, counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, you cannot confirm which, between the two, you... As of the moment, hindi ko po hawak yung...
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, but what if we show you, as I said,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: what if we show you the certification dated February, two certification,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: can you be
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: guided?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: As can answer, your honor. Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: he already looked at the documents earlier before the senator judges intervened and he couldn't... Mr. Witness, Mr. Attorney Loto, what document did you peruse earlier? The annex to the impeachment complaint, right?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Annex to the... That
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: was the document shown to you by counsel for the respondent earlier? Yes, Your Honor. Upon your perusal of that document, can you say... What the NPS docket number is that NBI uses?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, isa lang ho ang nandito na IDF.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So isa lang yun nandito, Your Honor, hindi ko humakita yung isa pa. Ang nandito na naka-attach na IDF is yung 11 February 2025.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So kung ito ho ang tinutukoy,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ang nakasulato rito na NPS docket number 16-INV-25C-00048,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor. Your Honor, the certifications, the two certifications also
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: has docket numbers. Can we just ask him to peruse this so that... He can make up his mind which of the two docket numbers they followed. Then
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: confront him with the document council. What is your council showing him?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We are showing the document February 5 and February
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: 14. Which as I mentioned contains 0049 as the ending docket number. Maybe just know, Your Honor,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: if that was the docket number that was followed by the NBI following the filing.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before you answer, Atty. Lotto, counsel, the first form, can you bring it up again? That's not an investigation form, right? That's a DOJ form.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, this is a receiving copy, Your Honor, because all of these were subpoenaed again from the NBI but not from the DOJ. So these were transmitted to the House Committee on Justice. By Sabtina.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: By who? The NBI? Submitted by the NBI. That's correct, Your Honor. And this was the basis that was used by the House Committee on Justice in filing the articles of impeachment before this impeachment court. So in other words, Your Honor, the agencies involved herein are just four. The DOJ, the NBI, the House Committee on Justice, and the Senate. And the line of questioning is very simple. We want to get to know to the bottom of the tooth. How were these documents altered? If at all.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: If at all.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: There's no basis for saying it's altered. Council, Atty. Lutop, what is your observation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Isa lang ho yung nandito na IDF. Uulitin ko po, Your Honor. Mayroon na ho ditong NPS bucket number. At yung date po is 11 February 2025, Sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: At yung isa? Yung isa, yung sa certification, Your Honor. Hindi sa IDF. Hindi siya IDF, Sir. That's what I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: was asking about earlier.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ang certification noon pinapakita sa akin, Your Honor. Hindi po IDF na isa.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We're trying to show the Feb 14, the latest certification for
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the revised.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: yung nandito na pinapakita sa akin is yung certification from the DOJ, 05 February 2025, and investigation data form.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Feb. 11, 2025
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 25A.00049, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So the 49 is the latest one and it's thus valid?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, I believe so. Ito yung may sufficient for... Alright.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. Now, let me direct your attention to the subpoena issued against the Vice President on April 29, 2025.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: This is the subpoena and
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the issue is that The docket number is 0048. In other words, VP Sara was made to answer to the earlier case that was docketed as such. Do you confirm this? You were part of this, correct? As the complainant.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, can I object now, Your Honor, please? If I may, Your Honor, please?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: What's the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: objection? If I may, I will explain.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I would like to object, Your Honor, please. This witness is incompetent because he is now being confronted with docket numbers supplied by agencies other than him. If he knows, Your Honor,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: he was the complainant. Your Honor, he was the supervising agent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, this is a DOJ document. Objection is sustained. Witness is not competent to answer these questions. You can call your witness to testify as to these documents belonging to the DOJ. Kindly move on, Counsel. We've been at this for quite some time. I'll move on.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: My next question is, the NBI's own evaluation is merely recommendatory in nature, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Recommendation. Okay. It
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: is not binding upon the DOJ, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The DOJ will assess, Your Honor, and evaluate the recommendation.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But it's not
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: binding upon the DOJ. Now,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the answer to the question, Attorney Lutok, you're a lawyer, you know the answer to this question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. It's not binding upon the courts, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your recommendation, it's
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: not binding upon the courts, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor. So, in Filipino, para maintindihan ng lahat, kahit sabihin ng NBI... Ask an answer, Your Honor. Ask an answer. Kahit sabihin ng NBI
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: na may grave... He's just translating into... The question is not yet... But the same question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. Kahit sabihin ng NBI na may grave threats or inciting to sedition, it is not binding upon the DOJ, correct? Ask and answered. The
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question earlier was with respect to the courts. Correct, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor. Insofar as the DOJ is concerned, Mr. Witness.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Insofar as the DOJ is concerned, the DOJ will evaluate. At pagkulang pa ho yung mga requirements. The
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: question is,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: are your findings binding on the DOJ?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Not necessarily, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, no.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: No. Alright. So, in other words, rekomendasyon lang ang kayang ibigay ng NBI, correct? Ask and answer. Ask
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: and
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: answer,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In fact, you attended hearings before the House Committee on Justice in April of this year, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so. Nag-appear ako. Hindi ko lang sigurado kung anong date yun. Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I would like to object to this, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: As
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: an answer, Your Honor. No, no, wait, wait, wait, wait. It's being confronted with—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, kindly wait for counsel for the prosecution.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: This is highly improper. This could fly if this is a committee on justice hearing, but this, with all due respect, is still a court of law. You cannot present clippings like that and confront the witness with that. That's not proper. You should be presenting documents. You cannot do props. Your Honor, please, this is highly irregular. Ask questions. Ilicit facts from this witness, don't use props.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Can I get a ruling on that, Your Honor? Because this is for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the purpose of— Counsel is
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: not yet asking any question. He's just laying the basis by asking if he attended previous hearings in the House to test the credibility, perhaps to elicit either contradictory statements or confirmatory statements. Counsel, please proceed.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And one of the committee members there, I think it was Representative Zendanya, even asked for the elements of inciting to sedition. Do you
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: recall that?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so, sir. He
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: also asked for the elements of grave threats, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, if I remember it right.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala akong, hindi ako ang tinanong yata. Alright, it was
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: another person but also from
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: NBI, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so, sir. And
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the NBI explained the elements of these felonies during that hearing, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi ako ang nag-explain nun. But
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: another person from the NBI did and you were present, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In fact, Representative Luistro even asked that the salient portions of your affidavit of investigation be flashed on the screen during that hearing, correct? If you can recall.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Siguro yun, Honor, pero di ko maalala. You're not sure. Okay, that's okay. And when asked whether VP Sara's acts constituted grave threats and inciting to sedition, the NBI answered in the affirmative, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I think so, sir. Now, my next question is very simple. Did the NBI at any point in that hearing clarify with the House Committee on Justice and the Filipino people watching then that its own evaluation is not binding upon the DOJ?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Did you clarify?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't think wala akong tanong na ganun sa amin, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So you were not able to clarify that, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala ako kasing tanong. Anong ika-clarify ko? Okay.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, you were not given an opportunity to clarify your own evaluation. This is a different question. Wait for the question. That this is not binding upon the courts. So, was there an opportunity for you to explain that it was not binding upon the courts?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala akong question doon. Alright.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, in other words, there was no opportunity in that hearing. To clarify that your evaluation was mere recommendatory.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ask and answer, Your Honor, please. Four times over. The first question was
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: binding upon the DOJ. The next question is binding upon the courts. The next question is the nature of the recommendation. Did you clarify at any point in that hearing that your recommendation was merely recommendatory? The question
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: was, did they clarify or not? Answer kindly, Atty. Latok.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Wala pong question sa amin na ganoon, Sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Very
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: well. Let's do that now. For the benefit of this honorable court and the Filipino people watching, when the NBI evaluated DP Sara's acts to be grave threats or inciting to sedition, is that binding upon the DOJ?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, ask and answered. This is now the third circle.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Already
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: asked and answered several times. I'll move on, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Will you agree with me that according to our laws,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The authority to determine guilt or innocence of a person lies with the courts. Yes, sir. Not with the DOJ.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. Not with the NBI. Yes, sir. Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, I will now object now, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: He's competent enough to answer. Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor, he already answered. Kindly settle down. I know it's late and I know both parties are tired. Kindly wait for the chair to recognize you before speaking.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If I may be recognized, I am now objecting on the ground of relevance of this series of questions. The defense might forget that we are an impeachment court. And whatever the DOJ may rule on, whatever the court may rule on, the same complaints filed by the NBI against the Vice President, it has no bearing on these impeachment complaints. What I am saying is, the issue in this case, the question is: did the Vice President betray public trust when she declared before the public that she already contracted a person?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, that's not the proper venue for any manifestation on the part of the prosecution.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, finish. Kindly state your objection, counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Relevance. Exactly your order, please. As to what the court will do, as to what the DOJ will do on the complaints filed by the DOJ, by the NBI, they have nothing to do with the issue in this case. The question is whether the Vice President betrayed public trust. By contracting an assassin to kill the president, the vice president, sorry, to kill the president, the first lady, and the former state house. Objection
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: again, your honor. It's not
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the proper, irrelevance.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, you know what you're doing as well. I'm so kindly limited to your objection.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Irrelevance, your honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondent, the court gets it, okay? You don't have to spend that much time on this matter. The court gets it. I think the senator-judges are well aware of the limitations of the power of the NBI and the DOJ, as well as the power of the court to decide on the innocence or guilt of the parties. You've established that point. Move on.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In other words, it is only the proper courts that can determine the guilt or innocence of VP Sara in terms of grave threats or inciting. It's a direct question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, asked and answered. Kindly move on. Again, the court gets it. I think the senator-judges get it as well, as well as the people who are listening.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. My question is this. Are you aware of any final verdict by any court that VP Sara is guilty?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Same. Same,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Same. If he's aware. Witness will answer if he knows.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, insofar as the NBI Cybercrime Division is concerned during that time, I'm not aware. So,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: insofar as this case is concerned, no final verdict yet?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't know, Your Honor. I don't know.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So far as the investigation of the NBI is concerned, no personal knowledge.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. Now, let me move on to a new point. Do you know what motu proprio means?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Motu proprio means on your own or out of your own initiative, correct? Yes, Sir. Sa madaling salita, voluntary?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Not really, Sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Wala nag-utos?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Under the law, we acted based on the law, Sir. Because it is our primary jurisdiction. To undertake investigation, should there be a threat against the security or assault against the person of the President, the Vice President, the Senate President, the Speaker of the House, and the Chief Justice?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Very well. Now, my question is this. Insofar as this case is concerned, did the NBI conduct an investigation motu proprio?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The fact, kanino, kanino, Your Honor, yung sinatanong niyo? Conducted an investigation, kanino po?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Insofar as this case is concerned, did you conduct a case motu proprio?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, the NBI conducted an investigation motu proprio on November 23, 2024. And on that same date, Your Honor, the Department of Justice directed the NBI to conduct an investigation on the matter.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Partly motoproprio, partly directed by the DOJ. Is that what you're saying? No, Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: With or without the directive from the DOJ, the NBI has primary jurisdiction on that case and therefore we can investigate on that particular case.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, but a while ago during your direct examination, you admitted that the DOJ secretary directed you, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: During that day, yes, sir. After na ma-instruct ako ng director, nag-imbestiga. Then, thereafter, the Department of Justice directed the NBI na mag-conduct ng investigation.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And did you follow that directive?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, it's the Department of Justice. Why should not I follow, sir?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Aren't you
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: an independent body?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, under the law, Republic Act 10867, it states there that the Department of Justice can direct the NBI to conduct investigation. Any investigation when the public interest so requires, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay, so the NBI is under the DOJ, correct? Definitely, sir. And the DOJ is under the Office of the President, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir. Under the Executive Branch, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Meaning the Secretary of the DOJ is under the Office of the President, correct? No question
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: to that, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: No question. So BBM has control over both the NBI and the DOJ, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: What do you mean by control, sir?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: What's your interpretation of control? You seem to be a smart man.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The Department of Justice and the Office of the President, insofar as the function of the NBI is concerned, hindi sila nakikialam doon. Kung ano yung findings ng NBI, kung anong recommendation, sinasubmit po namin ito sa Department of Justice. And then yung Department of Justice, i-evaluate po nila, and then mag-a-undergo ng process ng case build-up. Ang patunay na yung una naming sinubmit hindi tinanggap ng Department of Justice, meaning ang Department of Justice, pag nakita niya na hindi tama o kulang yung requirement ng NBI, hindi niya ito karakarakang tatanggapin, Your Honor. That's why, insofar as the DCE 15 is concerned, nag-require sila ng mga eco-comply namin and then nag-comply kami. That's the time the Department of Justice received our referral. Oh, very
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: well. Just to help you answer, I'll ask a more pointed question. At the time the investigation against VP Sara was being conducted, did BBM have control over the NBI or DOJ?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: At the time of the investigation? Yes. Well, being the head of the executive branch, sir, yes. The President is the head of the whole of the executive branch.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Very well. Did BBM at any point intervene in this investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Of course not, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, did you just admit to this court that there was no participation on the part of BBM?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, the purpose of the submission of the affidavit is for preliminary investigation, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So let me clarify. You received instructions to conduct an investigation against VP Sara from the DOJ, which is under the Office of the President, and in that investigation BBM was allegedly one of the offended parties.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, Your Honor, hindi ako nag-a—
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: There's no question yet. There's no question yet. And yet, BBM has control over both the NBI and the DOJ. Is that a fair assessment?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, I will object now. Asked and answered. Same point, Your Honor, please, many times over. Control of the President over the DOJ, control of the DOJ over the NBI, asked and answered many times over.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the structure involving the NBI, the DOJ, and the Office of the President, don't you
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: think that there was bias against VP Sara?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: will allow that. I would like to object, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, again, kindly wait for the Presiding Officer to recognize you. Witness may answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Our investigation, Your Honor, is evidence-based.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Nung pinag-usapan namin ito, nung inanalyze namin ito, nung nag-follow kami ng mga phases at analysis, we believe We agree that among ourselves na buo ang ebidensya, kumpleto ang ebidensya, na comply natin yung requirement ng prima facie case with reasonable certainty and conviction. So sinubmit namin yan sa DOJ na ang paniwala po namin ay kumpleto at na comply namin yung requirement.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Either way, the NBI can initiate its own investigation when necessary, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The NBI can initiate its own investigation. In
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: fact, you mentioned RA 10867, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And please allow me to read Section 5(g) thereof. It says: cases involving threats to security or assaults against the President, the Vice President, Senate President, Speaker of the House of Representatives, and Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. You confirm this, correct? My next question to you is this: while you conducted a motu proprio investigation to help BBM, FL, and the former Speaker, did you also conduct a motu proprio investigation to help VP Sara?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. The fact that we sent a December 2, 2024 letter, we informed the Vice President na iniimbestigahan din namin 'yung alleged threat laban sa kanya. So kailangan namin makakuha ng valid information, confirmed data, or any apparent violation of our Revised Penal Code or any special law. 'Yun ho 'yung purpose ng letter namin, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: To inform the Vice President na iniimbestigahan din namin 'yung alleged threat sa kanya.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes or no answer? Can we ask the— No, no, no. Mr. Witness—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Lotoc, this is the second time you've mentioned your December 2 subpoena.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: curiosity of the presiding officer has been picked. In your subpoena of December 2, you issued a subpoena to the Vice President for evidence in a certain investigation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No mention was made of either the investigation pertaining to threats against the President or even threats against the Vice President. But it's the second time you've mentioned that the intent of this one is for the threat against the Vice President. What is your basis, sir, when the subpoena does not contain such a specification of the evidence you will obtain from her?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, yung subpoena, nakafocus po yan doon sa investigation namin on the alleged grave threats at inciting to sedition during that time. Yung investigation naman, insofar as the Vice President threat to her life is concerned, meron nung kaming separate na letter nung December 2. Ah, hindi
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: subpoena, letter.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Letter po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Do we have that on file or on record somewhere? Yes, Your Honor. Is it the pre-marked?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Marked during trial earlier, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: By Agent Galilong?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: By this witness, Atty. Lotoc. That would be P-Roman numeral 4-5. Identified by the witness earlier, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: P-4-5?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 4-5.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Addressed to Atty. Lim?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Atty. Lotoc? Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Honor, I have questions relating to that, Your Honor. Just
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to clarify from the witness, are you referring, Atty. Latok, to the letter addressed to Atty. Lim signed by Assistant Director Ricarte? Yes,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor. Assistant Director. This
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: is the one that's referring to the alleged attempt of NBI to investigate the threats against the Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Okay.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proceed.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. In fact, since we're on the topic, let me direct your attention to that NBI letter issued by Glenn Ricarte dated December 2, 2024. Again, for the perusal of the senator judges, this is pages 155 to 158 of the AOI's Annex G-9. Do you confirm this? That this was sent out to the Vice President?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We have this document, Your Honor, signed by ADA. Glen Ricarte Dated 02 December 2024 Alright,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: and do you confirm that the date is December 2, 2024?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on these documents, sir, yes.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, let me read, and read with me please, the last two paragraphs. And I'll be very, I'll try to be very clear. It says here, we are hoping that we have assisted you properly. Can we flash that, please?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We are hoping that we have assisted you properly. We would be grateful if the Vice President will visit the NBI and participate on the ongoing investigation. As the schedule of her appearance, she is anticipated to appear on... Can you read the date please?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: 11 November 2024 at 10 AM at the Office of the Director, National Bureau of Investigation. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you provided the date. You provided the time and the place where VP Sara is supposed to appear, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, since ang naka-sign po rito, yung Assistant Director, wala akong personal knowledge, I think this is typo kasi nga nag-reply ang lawyer ng Vice Presidente.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Either you have personal knowledge or not, but neither can you say typo. If you don't have personal knowledge, you cannot say typo.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Sorry, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, which is it? So,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you don't have personal knowledge? I don't have personal knowledge, Your Honor. Hindi po ako ang simulat sa letter na ito.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. Again, Your Honor, this is an attachment of the affidant's or the witness's own affidavit of investigation. I understand, Your Honor, and he has been very repetitive on this, that there are documents there that He did not sign but when you attach something to your own affidavit your honor you're supposed to even to at least review them and clearly he did not review and he's even the head he mentioned that he's the supervisor now my next
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: question is objection objection laying a value to the testimony of the witness that's improper you ask him questions don't add
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: value
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: You stated a while ago that the reason why you did not pursue VP Sara's investigation in order to help her was because of her non-appearance, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We issued two subpoenas. The first one and then we gave her a chance again to give us information and then she did not appear for the second time,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: sir. But you said the second one was not a subpoena, it was a letter, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, the letter is the basis that we conducted motu proprio investigation on the alleged threat against the Vice President. The purpose of the two subpoenas is also, base sa usapan namin ng then-Director Jaime B. Santiago, pag nag-appear ang Vice Presidente, tatanungin din po ng Director namin, 'Ma'am, puwede mo bang i-share sa amin ano 'yung threat sa life mo? Baka meron kang information na puwede naming pagsimulan.'
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, allow the Presiding Officer. Sir, you referred to the letter and the subpoena. As I pointed out earlier, the subpoena does not make mention that you're asking for evidence about the threats against the Vice President. You just said in your subpoena, 'for information regarding what is under investigation by your office.' Now, in this letter that you referred to, signed by Assistant Director Ricarte, nowhere can I find that you're asking the Vice President information about the threat against her. You quoted several instances about the Vice President's statement against the President, but I cannot see a reference to the threat against the Vice President. Now you're telling me again that you intended to ask her when she comes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: answer po? Of course, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Kung pwede ko pong basahin. Please, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Kindly guide us
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: po.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Quote, This Bureau wishes her well and we would acknowledge if she can find a convenient time to visit the NBI since according to her, she received threats on her life as well. As part of its mandate, the NBI would like to inform her that we are also investigating on the said threats. Her appearance to the NBI will aid us in the expeditious investigation on the said threats, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And then this is the basis for the issuance of your two subpoenas against her.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi po. Ang dalawang subpoena, Your Honor, is para doon ho sa grave threats and inciting to sedition.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ah, para doon na po?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Opo. 'Yon po 'yung purpose ng dalawang subpoena.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Letter lang 'yung sa kanya tungkol sa threat sa kanya?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Letter lang.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: And then kung ano 'yung mga itinatanong at itatanong ng NBI sa kanya, in-explain ho dito sa letter na ito kung ano 'yung nature ng complaint.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung mga allegation laban sa kanya.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Atty. Lutok. Counsel,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you may proceed. But the long and short of it, in that December 2024 letter, you provided a November schedule, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, I cannot answer to that.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Ang signatoryo ang makakasagot, sir. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: in other words, she could not have attended that November 11, 2024 because as of the date of the letter, it was already December 2, 2024, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, Your Honor, 'yung second letter na sinubmit ng lawyer niya, ang sabi niya lang doon, the Vice President is confident that the NBI will conduct an investigation on the alleged threat against her life.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, but despite this error, do you still maintain that the investigation that you conducted was thorough? You used that word a while ago.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: My office is concerned, since hindi na ako may hawag dyan, baka merong ibang tinask ang aming director para dyan, sir. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: as early as December 2, 2024, the NBI has been investigating regarding the threats against VP Sara, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: When we issued the first subpoena and then when we issued the letter dated 02 December 2024,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: After more than one and a half years of investigation, has the NBI come up with a recommendation?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ask and answered, Your Honor. Ask and answered. Kanina pa. No. Recommendation on the threats against VP Sara.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer. Witness
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may answer. This is the investigation pertaining to the threats against the Vice President's life. Okay. Thank you, Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, since wala ho kaming validated information, wala ho kaming nakitang confirm doon sa allegation, threats against her life.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So no, that's okay. Meron
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: din bang affidavit of investigation para kay VP Sara, gaya ng ginawa ng NBI para kay BBM, FL, at former speaker?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Since wala ho pa kaming validated information, wala ho kaming mapagsimulan. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: in other words, meron para kay BBM, FL, at former speaker? Pero wala kay VP Sara.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Argumentative, Your Honor. Argumentative.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: That's a
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: factual question, Your Honor. Ask and answer. Move on, Counsel. If no affidavit of investigation, is there any written report on that investigation?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Anong investigation po, Your Honor? Yung
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: against VP Sara. May written report man lang ba?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, ang makakaalam ho niyan, yung aming intelligence service, sila ho ang may pool of information from different offices.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But as far as you know, wala pang written report on this?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, during that time, and so far as the cybercrime investigation is concerned, wala akong nakita na gano'n, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Wala pa? Noong time
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: na yun, sir. In
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: other words, since wala pang written report, wala pa rin opportunity si VP Sara to supplement any report that you have.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, wala akong idea kung mayroon ng written report ang aming intelligence service. Ang alam ko, kung ano lang yung nangyari during nung investigation namin, Cybercrime Division Investigation.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, I'll move on to a new point. Now, as an investigating body, the NBI is called to be impartial, correct? Yes, sir. Meaning, you have to evaluate both sides, not just one side, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: What do you mean both sides?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The offending party side and the offended party side. Yes, sir. Alright. In other words, you evaluate the side of the complainant and you also evaluate the side of the respondent, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Evaluate the side of the complainant.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. So, did the NBI do that in its investigation insofar as the case against VP Sara?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Precisely, Your Honor, the reason why we issued a letter dated December 2, 2024 is to elicit information from the Vice President herself kung meron po bang validated information or to ask her kung sakaling nag-appear siya, Ma'am, baka meron kang pwedeng pagsimulan namin.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, kahit representative, wala akong may dumating sa amin na magbibigay sa amin ng informasyon para pagsimulan ng investigation.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But didn't the council appear? So she participated through council, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The council, your honor, only stated na yung threat is, again, yung six months ago na nag-conduct ko kami ng open source investigation, wala akong kami nakitang validated talaga, sir. So wala kami mapagsimulan. Saan kami magsisimula?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think so, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Mendoza of Manila Times,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: also attended with
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: counsel.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It was reported to you. I think Magsambol, Andre, yes. Yun yung report sa akin ni Agent Kalinong, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: How about Rubrico of SMNI?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, yung anim ho na yan, as far as I know, na-issue namin ng subpoena, I think yung iba dyan hindi ho nag-appear kasi yung isa nasa China. Mayroon siyang parang understanding.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, I'm not asking about those. I'm just asking about the people that participated.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness is in the process of answering. Let him finish.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Are you done, Atty. Lutok?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, and these people were interviewed by NBI agents, correct? By NBI agents, sir. Okay, the NBI agents included Kalilong, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: For Magsambol and Reyes, Gueran. For Mendoza?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, sir. I think. All right. But Asuncion? For Rubrico, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Asuncion also. All
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: right. And the Q&A was recorded, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah. I think may transkripiata. All right. Very well. After
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: the interviews, the NBI agents executed affidavits, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Attesting to the interviews conducted.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Let's go through the minutes of the meeting attached to the affidavit of investigation. There were four sets of minutes of the meeting. Correct? One for Reyes, one for Mendoza, one for Magsambol, and one for Rubrico.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Do
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: you confirm this? May I check first the document, sir?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Your Honor, may we ask, Your Honor, that my co-counsel confronts the witness, not the prosecution's counsel. This is our turn, Your Honor. And we want to use the official copy, which is the copies court. The impeachment court's copy, your honor. So we don't know what copy the prosecution's lawyer is confronting the witness with.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, please comply.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Alright,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: so minutes of the meeting. So there were four sets, one for Reyes, one for Mendoza, one for Magsambol, and one for Rubrico. Now based on the minutes of the meeting... May I check first, sir? Okay, go ahead.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Mendoza.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Magsambol.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Rubrico.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: 20 questions, sir. And how long did the interviews last, if you know?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think ang report sa akin na nag-appear sila, nag-participate sila sa interview, but doon sa timeline, no personal knowledge, sir. Ang nakakasagot nito yung mismo yung nag-interview, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In that interview, they were asked about their personal knowledge on the November 23, 2024 presscon, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, the question was where were you on November 23, 2024 at about 12 a.m. to 1 a.m. Yes,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: your answer is yes. There
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: is that question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Now, during this interview, according to the minutes also that you're now perusing, a video of the presscon was shown, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, it says here, is that Zoom meeting the one in the video? Okay.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: At this juncture, the agent showed the video.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tony Lutop, kindly just answer yes to abbreviate the proceedings or no? Yes, yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: sir. Okay, my question
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: is this. Did the NBI show the entire video to the interviewee or just portions thereof?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Ang
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: makakasagot niyan yung owner, yung nagkanta ko ng interview. If you know.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I'm not sure, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Didn't you provide instructions to the NBI agents regarding the showing of the video?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, the instruction is whether or not nandodon ba sila nung nangyari yung press conference nung November 23. Yeah,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: but will you agree with me that for the investigation to be impartial, the NBI should have shown the entire video and not just certain portions thereof? That
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I cannot answer kung pinakita nila yung buong video ang instruction, ko yung honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Part ng investigation is to ask them kung nag-participate sila o may personal knowledge sila during the online press conference of the November 23, 2024.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, but let me direct your attention to page 189 also of Annex G-9. This pertains to the minutes of the meeting of Kalilong. If we can flash that on the screen and if my co-counsel can confront the witness. It says here, and I want to read, in the top portion it states,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: 1024H and 1057H, December 4, 2024.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Meaning, the interview took place on December 4 from 1024 to 1057 AM. Is that correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Military time?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, it appears in that document, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. So in other words, 23 minutes lang yung interview?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on that document, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: O hindi niyo talaga mapapakita yung whole video, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on that document, kung ganyan lang yung timeline niya, yes, Your Honor, hindi.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Kasi two hours mahigit yung video ni VP Saray, correct?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ask and answer, Your Honor. Ask and answer. I'm just emphasizing the
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: time, Your Honor. Kaya nga, objection
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: eh.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator Judge Soto is recognized. What is your pleasure, sir?
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer, Mr. President. To satisfy the curiosity of our group here, we were asking each other, why did you invite these four media personalities?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor, because they were there based on our investigation.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: They were
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: there in the presscon?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir. They participated.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: The whole presscon?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: The whole presscon, sir.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: So why do you have to show the entire presscon again?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Precisely, Your Honor, that's the point. We just want to Establish whether, sinabi ba ito ng vice-presidente? At sinabi nila na yes, yan yung sinabi ng vice-presidente. Yung point po yun na may kinundrata siya, may kinausap siyang tao.
Sen. Vicente C. Sotto III: Ah, kaya yun lang ang pinakita niyo, hindi niyo pinakita yung buhok? Because they were there? Yes. The entire time? Are you sure they were there the entire time?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: They were there, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Okay, thank
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: But you cannot have personal knowledge? They
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: may have exited the Zoom
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: meeting, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yeah, yung nakita ko dun sa video, ang pinakahuling nag-exit, I think tatlo yata yun, sir.
Sen. Paolo Benigno “Bam” Aquino: Pero
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: most of the time, nandoon ho yung mga media personalities, nagtanong po sila, nag-inquire po sila, at nag-participate po sila doon.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, at any rate, each participant was asked, and I quote, in paragraph 11 of the affidavit, or the minutes, it says here, Do you hear? The statement of VP. Yes, wag ka mag-alala ma'am sa security ko kasi may kinausap na ko. Which ends in, and then he said yes, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yeah, base rito, yes. Okay. So sa madaling salita, insofar as the interviews conducted by the NBI, wala nang tanong tungkol sa ibang statement ni VP Sara nung presscon, tama?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Basi dito sa document.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yan lang ang tinanong nyo. Tama. Yan lang. Yan lang ang statement na yan ang tinanong nyo.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Basi sa document, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Didn't you have enough time to ask about other statements made by VP Sara in order to establish context?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor. Yes
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: or no? If you can, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Let the witness answer.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: The presiding officer already directed a more responsive answer.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Nung November 26 video, nakikita ko namin na may admission na ginawa, nireiterate ng vice president. That's not
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: my question. My question is, did you have enough time to ask
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: about... That
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: is his answer. No, no, no. Atty. Lutok, the question was, did you show any other video or parts of the video other than this one?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Based on the document, sir, ito lang ho yung mga tinanong ko. Ano yung nandito sa document?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Walang ibang part ng video. Based on the document. Based
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: on the document. Ito lang po, Your Honor. Okay.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright. In other words, the agents focused only on this one statement by VP Sara, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Based on
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: the interview, sir. And the Q&A used a targeted question, correct? Based on the document, sir.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: We asked them kung nandodon sila o nag-participate sila o kung narinig ba nila yung utterances na yun.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Was just about one minute. Ask and answer, Your Honor, please. The
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: same topic many times over.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, I understand that you're trying to emphasize a point, but to manage the court's time, kindly move on to your next question.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So you think that by showing only a portion of the video, that portion was taken out of context?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, we authenticated the whole video and we saw what happened on that online press conference.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: By the way, did the interview we sign the minutes of the meeting?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: So far as the late Saidin Reyes.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: If you know, I'll go through it one by one. I think may huli yata na walang firma yung isa namin. Can
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: we direct your... But you know as a lawyer that if a document is unsigned, that document will be treated as a mere scrap of paper, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So that is the standard operating procedure, correct? That you sign the document, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes or no? Yes or no? I don't know kung yung tama
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: yung ibinigay na docs. Ang signatory ho dyan si Atty. Asuncion. Yeah.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In fact, let us show that document for the benefit of this court.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Let me direct your attention to pages 203 to 207 of Annex G-9. This pertains to the minutes of the meeting involving Rubrico of SMNI. Can we display first the first page? So the interviewer was Ria Vanessa Asuncion?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Hindi pa siya sure kung good morning or good afternoon. And she conducted the interview, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: It appears so in that document, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: but let's go on to the signature page now.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, in other words, Jason, there appears to be a signature above the name Jason Rubrico. Alright, can you state for the record whether Atty. Ria Vanessa D.S. Asuncion signed this document? In
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: that document, no signature by Atty. Ria Vanessa Asuncion.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, wasn't this a failure to observe SOP on your part?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think we have to ask Atty. Vanessa, baka meron siyang... But again,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: you're the supervisor of these minutes of the meeting and you were the one who attached these documents, your affidavit of investigation. Anyway, I'll move
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: on to a new point.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: My only point is this, Mr. Lotoc. We are talking here about filing a case against the Vice President of the Philippines, who is the second-highest official of the land, and you used an unsigned document as part of your exhibits. Is that what you're trying to tell the court?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You can ask Atty. Ria Vanessa D. Asuncion, the executive officer, kung ano ang nangyari.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, so let's go through the affidavits that were executed after the interviews. Okay, pahabol na ito lahat, tama?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Kasi this was pursuant to the Feb 5 certification eh, so hinabol nyo ito lahat, tama?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Hindi yung hinabol, kinumply ho namin yung requirement ng DOJ.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Ah, you want to use the term nagkinumply. Okay, sige. The interviews were in November to December 2024, but the affidavits were in February 10, 2025, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yung mga interview mismo, November to December 2024, kinundak. Pero yung mga affidavits attesting to those interviews, February of 2025 na in-execute, tama?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: At any
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: rate, this was made pursuant to the Feb 5 DOJ certification, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Okay. So in short, hinanapan kayo ng DOJ ng affidavits. That's why you attach additional ones to the revised affidavit of investigation. Is that what happened?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, the affidavit was not revised. May mga attachment lang ho na nirequire yung Department of Justice. So kinumpulay ho namin. Even
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: your own director referred to it as revised, diba? So let's not make an issue about that. Exactly. I'm just asking if these were attached to the second affidavit of investigation. So, in other words, the agent who executed these affidavits were John Mark Kalilong, Gueran, and Asuncion, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: And each agent executed their own affidavit, correct?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: All were based on their personal knowledge, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, sir, based on their personal knowledge. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: nothing was supplied to any agent, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I don't understand the question, sir. So
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: nothing was supplied, ibig sabihin hindi binigay sa kahit anong agent yung isusulat niya doon sa affidavit. Independent nila ginawa lahat yan.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yung affidavit ng mga agent? Yes, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: In other words, what you're telling this court is that these are bona fide affidavits. And not template affidavits, correct? Bonafide and not what, sir? Template. Yung hindi pinirmahan lang basta.
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Well, I think you can ask, sir, the one who signed the affidavit, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Again, this is part of your affidavit. These are attachments to your affidavit of investigation. So you should have checked this at least, correct?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Sa practice namin, may mga templated na talaga kung common na yung...
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Thank you. Thank you. So, in
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: other words, you use template affidavits. Let me direct your attention to the affidavit of John Mark Kalilong, pages 170 to 171, of the Articles of Impeachment's G-9. Allow me to read a portion of its paragraph. Five. It says there, no joke. Can we flash that on the screen?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: It
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: says there, no joke. No joke. Nagbili na ako.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Sige. Can we focus on that part?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yan.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So, here.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Yan. So, no joke, no joke. Nagbili na ako mama. Here. On the bottom portion. Nagbili na ako mama pag namatay ako. Alright? Do you confirm that there is a typographical error in the spelling of mam? Which was incorrectly spelled as mama.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, Your Honor, with all due respect, Your Honor, please, what's the relevance of a typographical error from being mama? We will demonstrate
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: that, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I'm
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: just laying
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the basis.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What's the relevance? On a
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: short leash, counsel, show the connection and relevance.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Can we confirm first, your honor, if he confirms that there's a typographical error on Kalilong's affidavit?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: I think since the signatories here are Agent Kalilong and Atty. Vanang Luben, sila ho ang makakasagot.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Alright, so we cannot confirm.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So let me direct your attention to the affidavit of Geran, Agent Angely Jean Geran, pages 178 to 179 of AOI's Annex G-9. Again, let me read from paragraph 5 as well. It says here, Can we zoom that portion? No joke, no joke. Tagbiling na ako mama pag namatay ako. Do you confirm that there's also a typographical error in the spelling of the word ma'am, which was also incorrectly spelled as mama?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You can ask the one who signed this affidavit, sir.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: So you cannot confirm also?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: You can ask,
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Your Honor, the one who signed it. One last.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Pages 199 to 200 of Annex G. 9 as well. This is now the affidavit of Priya Asuncion. Can I go to paragraph 5 also? No joke, no joke. Nagbili na ako, mama. Can you also confirm that there's a typographical error in the spelling of
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: mama,
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: which was also incorrectly spelled as mama?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Again, you can ask the one who signed the affidavit. Alright, so
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: in other words, all three affidavits contain the exact typographical error of the word mama. Same paragraph number. And do you still maintain that these affidavits were independently executed?
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Mr. Presiding Officer?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before I recognize Senator-Judge Zubiri, counsel, I think inamin naman ni Atty. Lotoc na may mga templates sila, kumbaga may mga dekahon silang affidavits. Tama ba, Atty. Lotoc?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So posibleng isa ito sa mga dekahon ninyong affidavit? Is that possible?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor. Kasi same lang ho 'yung [unclear]. Siguro 'yung pag-copy-paste diyan, kung anong unang nakopy-paste doon sa [unclear], 'yun na ho 'yun.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kaya nga, kasi parehong number five, parehong [unclear], di ba? Meaning may point naman 'yung counsel for respondent. So, it's possible that isa ito sa mga dekahon ninyong affidavit?
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Senator-Judge Zubiri, what is your pleasure, sir?
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: sa Bisaya pa, Your Honor, Murag Abugado. But yes, we appreciate the fastidiousness of the good counsel for the defendant on looking at all these particular issues. But due to the lateness of the hour, Your Honor, and I've been being egged by my colleagues here, we've been here for six hours, 2 to 8, 2 p.m. to 8. May we request maybe counsel for the defense or the body that we just adjourned tonight and continue tomorrow because all these details after a while I'm sure these gentlemen and ladies both for their counsel and for the prosecution has not even eaten dinner and many of them are probably tired from sitting as I am tired from sitting for six hours. May we take that break your honor and just continue tomorrow at 2 p.m. For the continuance of the impeachment court, Your Honor. Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May I know how much longer is the cross of counsel for the respondent?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Before I answer that question, Your Honor, we just manifest that this is the first time that the Vice President through counsel is confronting the witnesses against her. Of course, she did not participate during the House Committee on Justice for the reasons that were...
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: Already stated in our petition for certiorari. So, to answer that question, about halfway, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We're not cutting short your time to cross-examine, counsel. We're just simply inquiring to find out if you can either simply wait for it to finish or continue tomorrow.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We're okay with either, Your Honor. But to also indulge Senator Judge Subiri, we can have a continuance, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay, there being no objection on the part of counsel for respondent, given that we're cutting for tonight his cross-examination.
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: One last administrative point, Your Honor. Considering the change in schedule because of the continuance, may we inquire of the prosecution if they still intend to present—
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: We will get to that, counsel. We will decide on that before we adjourn. For the meantime, Court would like to excuse Atty. Lotoc with a reminder that the subpoena for him to attend tomorrow's hearing still stands and he will continue to testify under the same oath. Thank you, Your
Atty. Jeremy C. Lotoc: Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You are excused, Atty. Lotoc. Thank you for your time and cooperation and see you again tomorrow, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: For some administrative matters, we are in receipt of the memorandum from the Council for the Respondents with respect To the issuance of subpoena for bank records and AMLC records as well as BAR records. Do we have a similar submission from the council for the prosecutors?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly furnish clerk reports instructed to furnish all senator judges with a copy of the same with a reminder that we will be hearing the oral arguments of the parties on these two matters on Wednesday. After the presentation of the testimony of the witnesses of the Council for the Prosecution, what is the pleasure of the Honorable Defensor?
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: We have no other matters to discuss, Your Honor. We will await the final ruling of the Court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Chair would like to recognize Senate President Gatchalian.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Thank you, Mr. Presiding Officer. Pursuant to our discussion earlier on the subpoena for NBI Director Melvin Matibag, and pursuant to the discussion with Senator-Judge Alan Cayetano and myself, and to give ample time to the senator-judges to study, to look at the pieces of evidence, as well as to propound their questions, may I propose to let him come to the Senate on Monday? I was looking at the letter from the NBI, and indeed the activity in Bangkok is quite important. It is the regional summit on scam-center compounds and transnational organized crime, which will be held on Tuesday. We were also looking at the flights to Bangkok, and there are flights at night, Mr. Presiding Officer. So what we can do is allow him to come here on Monday and then propound our questions. And if ever we don't finish it, we can request him to come back again after his activity in Bangkok.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the understanding, of course, Senate President Gachalian, that the testimony of the witness given in direct examination would be meaningless unless he is thoroughly cross-examined.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, should we not finish his testimony on Monday, it shall be continued on the next trial date until the cross-examination, redirect, and if at all, recross shall have been finished by the parties. Subject to that understanding. Is there any objection to the motion of the Senate President to issue the subpoena for the attendance of Director Matibag on Monday, July 20?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 2 o'clock in the afternoon. There being none, same is approved. Now, to clarify, the Honorable Defensor may ask, who is your witness for tomorrow? I understand we still have two witnesses online, namely Atty. Lopez and Capt. Bellio. Is that correct, sir?
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: That's correct, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And you will be presenting Atty. Lopez first?
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Based on our earlier manifestation. We're supposed to present her next, after Law Talk, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: After the culmination of the cross, if at all, redirect and recross of Atty. Law Talk.
Rep. Lorenz R. Defensor: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you very much. Any other points that any other senator or judge would like to raise? Any other points the parties would like to raise? Counsel for Respondent, given that the Honorable Defensor already said yes. Nothing further?
Atty. Mark C. Vinluan: We are okay with that presentation, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: There being no other matters to take up, and given the lateness of the hour, and as manifested and moved by Senator Judge Zubiri, there being no objection, the trial is hereby adjourned until 2 p.m. of Tuesday, July 14, 2026.